<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../../tools/docbook-dtd/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="fbodbc205-configure">
  <title>Firebird ODBC Configuration </title>
  <para>The configuration settings you make in an ODBC data source description 
  (<quote>DSN</quote>) define the attributes for connecting to a specific database. 
  On Windows, a dialog box captures parameters that correspond to the connection 
  attributes.  On Linux, the parameters are configured manually in text (.ini) 
  files.</para>
  
  <section id="fbodbc205-config-windows">
    <title>Configuring a DSN on Windows</title>
    <para>First, find the applets in the Administrative Tools section of the machine
    where you are going to set up a <quote>channel</quote> through which your application
    program is going to connect with a Firebird database, either on the same 
    machine or elsewhere in the local or wide-area network.</para>
    <para>On a 64-bit machine, you will find two such applets:
    <figure id="fbodbc205-systemdsn-001">
      <title>Selecting a DSN setup applet on Windows</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
        <!-- actual image size is 597px X 464px -->
          <imagedata fileref="images/fb_odbc_system_dsn_001.png" format="PNG"
           width="496px" depth="385px"
           scalefit="1" align="center" />  <!-- 83% -->
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    For the purpose of our example, we want to pick the item <firstterm>ODBC Data Sources 
    (32-bit)</firstterm>. Obviously, if we had installed the 64-bit driver with the 
    intention of using it for a 64-bit application, we would pick the 64-bit item from 
    this menu instead.
      <important>
        <title>Run as Administrator!</title>
        <para>Don't left-click the item:  right-click and, from the context menu, select 
        <classname>Run as Administrator</classname>.  This is necessary because you are 
        about to set up a <command>System DSN</command>.</para>
      </important>
    </para>
    <para>  
    Click on the tab labelled <quote>System DSN</quote>, where you will begin setting up
    your DSN.
    </para>
    <para>
    <figure id="fbodbc205-systemdsn-002">
      <title>Selecting the Firebird driver for the DSN</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
        <!-- actual image size is 673px X 493px -->
          <imagedata fileref="images/fb_odbc_system_dsn_002.png" format="PNG"
           width="498px" depth="365px"
           scalefit="1" align="center" />  <!-- 74% -->
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    Click <classname>Add...</classname> on the first screen to bring up the list of
    drivers on the next.  Select the <command>Firebird/InterBase(r)</command> driver,
    then click Finish.
    </para>

    <section id="fbodbc205-config-windows-settings">
      <title>The DSN Settings</title>
      <para>After clicking <classname>Finish</classname> on the previous screen, you are presented
      with a form into which you will enter the parameters for a connection and will be able to
      test that they all work.
      <figure id="fbodbc205-systemdsn-003">
        <title>Setting up parameters for the DSN</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
          <!-- actual image size is 467px X 442px -->
            <imagedata fileref="images/fb_odbc_system_dsn_003.png" format="PNG"
             width="397px" depth="376px"
             scalefit="1" align="center" />  <!-- 85% -->
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      </para>
      <para>
      <table id="fbodbc205-config-dsn">
      <?dbfo keep-together='auto'?>
        <title>Parameters for the DSN Configuration</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="colParam" colwidth="1*"></colspec>
          <colspec colname="colBlurb" colwidth="2*"></colspec>
          <thead>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="center">Parameter</entry>
              <entry align="center">Entry</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Data Source Name (DSN)</entry>
              <entry align="left">REQUIRED.  A unique, meaningful name indicating the
              type of connection or its use.  Make it brief as you can expand the
              narrative elsewhere.  Examples: &quot;Connect from FbEmbed&quot; or &quot;ConnectFbServer&quot;</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Description</entry>
              <entry align="left">Optional.  Could be used to provide more details about the data source.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Database</entry>
              <entry align="left">REQUIRED. Full address of the database, as required for an embedded
              or network connection.  If the connection is remote, it can be in TCP/IP or WNET format.
              TCP/IP is recommended.  Firebird database aliases are supported.  Refer to 
              <link linkend="fbodbc205-examples-connection">Connection Examples</link>.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Client</entry>
              <entry align="left">May be required. Local path to the Firebird client library.  For embedded
              connections to a sub-V.3 Windows server, it can point to the copy of
              <filename>fbembed.dll</filename> in the application directory;  otherwise, point it to where
              you have located the bitness-compatible Firebird remote client library unless you are certain
              that the correct library will be found automatically in a system location.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Database Account</entry>
              <entry align="left">Optional, since login credentials can be captured during connection
              to a Firebird database. If it is not configured, the ODBC interface will prompt for a
              user ID (UID or USER) at connection time.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Password</entry>
              <entry align="left">Optional, since login credentials can be captured during connection
              to a Firebird database. If it is configured, it should be the password for the supplied
              User ID.  Otherwise, the ODBC interface will prompt for a password (PWD or PASSWORD)
              at connection time. Any password configured is encrypted automatically and saved in
              <filename>odbc.ini</filename>. Storing the password here should not be a security
              risk.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Role</entry>
              <entry align="left">Optional.  If it is defined and the login is by SYSDBA, role is ignored;
              otherwise, the login credentials, whether stored or captured at connection, must have been
              granted that role prior to the login attempt.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Character Set</entry>
              <entry align="left">May be blank.  Sets the default character set of the client.</entry>
            </row>

            <row valign="middle">
              <entry namest="colParam" nameend="colBlurb" align="center">Options (set here in DSN or specify dynamically)</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry namest="colParam" nameend="colBlurb" align="left">Transaction parameters</entry>
            </row>

            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Read (default write)</entry>
              <entry align="left">Transactions are read/write by default. Check to make transactions read-only.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Nowait (default wait)</entry>
              <entry align="left">The transaction will wait if it encounters a lock conflict. Check to
              have the transaction return an error immediately upon encountering a lock conflict.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Lock timeout</entry>
              <entry align="left">When a transaction is set for WAIT conflict resolution, express the length of
              time in seconds until the lock times out and a lock conflict error is returned
              (<function>isc_lock_timeout</function>).</entry>
            </row>

            <row valign="middle">
              <entry namest="colParam" nameend="colBlurb" align="left">Other optional parameters</entry>
            </row>

            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Dialect</entry>
              <entry align="left">SQL dialect for the client to use in accessing the database.  The only valid
              options for Firebird are 1 or 3.   Note, Dialect 1 is not compatible with quoted identifiers; Dialect 3
              will not accept strings delimited by double quotes.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Quoted Identifier</entry>
              <entry align="left">Causes pairs pairs of double quotes to be treated solely as delimiters of
              case-sensitive object identifiers.  Attempts to pass double quotes as string delimiters will
              be treated as errors in both dialects.  Note, double-quoted strings have always been
              illegal in Dialect 3.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Sensitive Identifier</entry>
              <entry align="left">This option affects the way the client treats the property
              <function>SQL_IDENTIFIER_CASE</function>. <function>SQL_IC_UPPER</function> (value=1) is the default,
              treating all identifiers as stored in upper case characters.  Check to select
              <function>SQL_IC_SENSITIVE</function>  (value=3) to have the interface treat all identifiers
              that are not in all upper case as though they were case-sensitive.  This is not recommended!
              For an explanation, see Note (1) below.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">Autoquoted Identifier</entry>
              <entry align="left">Default is NO.  The effect of checking this is to change
              the setting to YES.  In that case, every identifier in every statement will be
              double-quoted automatically.  The need to set this on would be highly unusual and
              would need to be well understood to avoid non-stop errors.</entry>
            </row>
            <row valign="middle">
              <entry align="left">SCHEMA options</entry>
              <entry align="left">Drop-down list offering three options for treatment of
              SQL schemas, which Firebird does not support.  Normally, leave this at the
              default setting <classname>Set null field SCHEMA</classname>.  For some details,
              see Note (2) below.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      </para>
      
      <note>
        <title>Note (1) regarding <quote>Sensitive identifier</quote></title>
        <para>If this setting is checked on, it would cause this
        statement
          <literallayout class="monospaced">
  SELECT A.Test_Field FROM Mixed_Caps_Table A
  ORDER BY A.Test_Field
          </literallayout>
        to be converted to
          <literallayout class="monospaced">
  SELECT A.&quot;Test_Field&quot; FROM &quot;Mixed_Caps_Table&quot; A
  ORDER BY A.&quot;Test_Field&quot;
          </literallayout>
        </para>
        <para>The following would result in a wrong conversion:
          <literallayout class="monospaced">
  Select A.Test_Field From Mixed_Caps_Table A
  Order By A.Test_Field
          </literallayout>
        gets converted to
          <literallayout class="monospaced">
&quot;Select&quot; A.&quot;Test_Field&quot; &quot;From&quot; &quot;Mixed_Caps_Table&quot; A
&quot;Order&quot; &quot;By&quot; A.&quot;Test_Field&quot;
          </literallayout>
        </para>
      </note>

      <note>
        <title>Note (2) regarding SCHEMA settings</title>
        <para>Some applications generate SQL statements automatically, based on
        user inquiries, on the assumption that the target database supports
        namespaces and SQL SCHEMAs. For example,
          <literallayout class="monospaced">
 select SYSDBA.COUNTRY,SYSDBA.CURRENCY from SYSDBA.COUNTRY
          </literallayout>
        or
          <literallayout class="monospaced">
  select * from SYSDBA.COUNTRY
          </literallayout>
        </para>
        <para>This selection of schema settings attempts to prevent clashes with
        applications that do this kind of thing. The drop-down list offers the three 
        variants:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>Set null field SCHEMA</listitem>
            <listitem>Remove SCHEMA from SQL query</listitem>
            <listitem>Use full SCHEMA</listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para><classname>Set null field SCHEMA</classname> is the default, causing the 
        SCHEMA element to be set NULL whenever it it is specified as part of a query.
        The result is a query that Firebird can process.</para>
        <para><classname>Remove SCHEMA from SQL query</classname> filters the namespace 
        references from the statement whenever the SQLExecDirect command receives 
        a request such as
          <literallayout class="monospaced">
  select SYSDBA.COUNTRY,SYSDBA.CURRENCY from SYSDBA.COUNTRY
          </literallayout>
        transforming it before passing it to the API as
          <literallayout class="monospaced">
  select COUNTRY,CURRENCY from COUNTRY
          </literallayout>
        </para>
        <para><classname>Use full SCHEMA</classname> is reserved for a future in which Firebird
        has the capability to process these concepts itself&mdash;perhaps in Firebird 4. In 
        that event, the driver will have no need to screen out these constructions.</para>
      </note>
      
      <para>Click on the <quote>Test connection</quote> button to confirm that 
      your configuration is good:
      
      <figure id="fbodbc205-systemdsn-004">
        <title>Testing the Configuration</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
          <!-- actual image size is 467px X 442px -->
            <imagedata fileref="images/fb_odbc_system_dsn_004.png" format="PNG"
             width="397px" depth="376px"
             scalefit="1" align="center" />  <!-- 85% -->
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      </para>
      <para>If all is well, click OK, return to the main form and save the 
      configuration by clicking OK there, too.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="fbodbc205-services-button">
      <title>The Services Button</title>
      <para>The Services button launches a number of server management utilities
      through a GUI management console.  It is described later in 
      <link linkend="fbodbc205-services">The Services Interface</link>. </para>
    </section>
  </section> <!-- fbodbc205-config-windows -->

  <section id="fbodbc205-linux-config">
    <title>Configuring a DSN on Linux</title>
    <author><firstname>Pavel</firstname><surname>Cisar</surname></author>
    <para>Configuration depends on the Linux distribution but, somewhere in
    <filename>/etc</filename> or <filename>/etc/unixODBC</filename>, should be two
    files named <filename>odbc.ini</filename> and <filename>odbcinst.ini</filename>.</para>
    <para>Add to odbcinst.ini:
      <programlisting>
[Firebird]
Description     = InterBase/Firebird ODBC Driver
Driver          = /usr/local/lib64/libOdbcFb.so
Setup           = /usr/local/lib64/libOdbcFb.so
Threading       = 1
FileUsage       = 1
CPTimeout       =
CPReuse         =
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>Add to odbc.ini:
      <programlisting>
[employee]
Description     = Firebird
Driver          = Firebird
Dbname          = localhost:/opt/firebird/examples/empbuild/employee.fdb
User            = SYSDBA
Password        = masterkey
Role            =
CharacterSet    =
ReadOnly        = No
NoWait          = No
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <section id="fbodbc205-linux-config-test">
      <title>Testing the Configuration</title>

      <para>UnixODBC has a tool named <classname>ISQL</classname> (not to be confused
      with Firebird's tool of the same name!) that you can use to test the connection,
      as follows:
        <literallayout class="monospaced">
  isql -v employee
        </literallayout>
      </para>
      <para>If you have connection problems, make sure that the directory
      where you placed the Firebird ODBC shared library, e.g.,
      <filename>/usr/local/lib64/libOdbcFb.so</filename>, is on the system loadable
      library path.  If not you could set:
        <literallayout class="monospaced">
  export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=$LD_LIBRARY_PATH:/usr/lib/odbc
        </literallayout>
      or, more simply,
        <literallayout class="monospaced">
  export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=/usr/lib/odbc
        </literallayout>
      </para>
      <para>If you still have problems, the next thing is to try an <function>strace</function>
      to try to identify them:
        <literallayout class="monospaced">
  strace -o output.txt isql -v employee
        </literallayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
