  <chapter id="rnfb40-general">
    <chapterinfo>
      <title>General Notes</title>
    </chapterinfo>

    <para>Thank you for reviewing this Firebird 4.0 Beta release.  We cordially invite you to
    test it hard against your expectations and engage with us in identifying and fixing any bugs
    you might encounter.</para>

    <para>ODS13 is introduced and it's a major ODS upgrade, so older databases cannot be opened 
    with a Firebird 4 server. At this point in development, nothing more than a backup/restore is 
    needed if you want to upgrade an existing database for your beta testing. The engine library
    is named <filename>engine13.dll</filename> (Windows) and <filename>libEngine13.so</filename> (POSIX).  
    The security database is named <filename>security4.fdb</filename>. Binaries layout and configuration 
    are unchanged from Firebird 3.</para>
    <note>
    That said, you can copy the Firebird engine library from the Firebird 3.0 distribution package
    (named <filename>engine12.dll</filename> (Windows) and <filename>libEngine12.so</filename> (POSIX),
    and located inside the <filename>/plugins</filename> sub-directory) to continue working with
    databases in ODS12 without needing a backup/restore. However, new features introduced with
    Firebird 4.0 will not be accessible.
    </note>
    <para>Known incompatibilities are detailed in the <link linkend="rnfb40-compat">Compatibility 
    Issues</link> chapter.</para>

    <section id="rnfb40-general-bugreport">
      <!-- Level 1 section -->

    <title>Bug Reporting</title>
    <para>Bugs fixed since Firebird 3.0.5 and Firebird 4.0 Beta 1 release are listed and described
    in the <link linkend="rnfb40-bug">Bugs Fixed</link> chapter.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you think you have discovered a new bug in this release, please make a
        point of reading the instructions for bug reporting in the article
        <ulink
          url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/en/how-to-report-bugs/">How
        to Report Bugs Effectively</ulink>, at the Firebird Project website.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you think a bug fix has not worked, or has caused a regression, please locate
          the original bug report in the Tracker, reopen it if necessary, and follow the instructions
          below.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Follow these guidelines as you attempt to analyse your bug:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Write detailed bug reports, supplying the exact build number of your Firebird kit. Also
          provide details of the OS platform. Include reproducible test data in your report and post
          it to our <ulink
          url="http://tracker.firebirdsql.org">Tracker</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You are warmly encouraged to make yourself known as a field-tester of this beta
          by subscribing to the <ulink
          url="mailto:firebird-test-request@lists.sourceforge.net?subject=subscribe">field-testers'
          list</ulink> and posting the best possible bug description you can.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you want to start a discussion thread about a bug or an
          implementation, please do so by subscribing to the <ulink
          url="mailto:firebird-devel-request@lists.sourceforge.net?subject=subscribe">firebird-devel
          list</ulink>.  In that forum you might also see feedback about any tracker ticket you
          post regarding this Beta.</para>
        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>

    </section>

    <section id="rnfb30-general-docs"><!-- Level 1 section -->
      <title>Documentation</title>
      <para>You will find all of the README documents referred to in these notes&mdash;as well as many
      others not referred to&mdash;in the doc sub-directory of your Firebird 4.0 installation.</para>


      <para><emphasis>--The Firebird Project</emphasis></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
