<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- For standalone validation, uncomment the following DOCTYPE declaration. -->
<!--
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
-->
<article id="docbuildhowto">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>How to get and build the Firebird manual module</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Paul</firstname>

      <surname>Vinkenoog</surname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1 id="docbuildhowto-introduction">
    <title>Introduction: Purpose of this Howto - Intended audience</title>

    <para>This Howto explains, step by step, how you can download and build
    the manual module from the Firebird Project at SourceForge.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>What is this "manual module" anyway?</title>

      <para>The manual module is part of the Firebird Project at SourceForge.
      It is a collective effort, aimed at producing comprehensive and accurate
      documentation on the Firebird RDMS (Relational Database Management
      System).</para>

      <para>It is important to understand that the manual module contains the
      documentation in <emphasis>source form</emphasis> - to be more precise:
      in Docbook XML format. These sources need to be processed
      (<firstterm>built</firstterm>) to obtain easily readable docs, which can
      then be published on the Internet.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Apart from the manual module, is there any other Firebird
      documentation?</title>

      <para>Yes! At the time of this writing, practically all useful Firebird
      documentation has been produced outside the Firebird manual module. We
      are still in the beginning stages of filling the module with
      documentation. In fact, one of the reasons this Howto is written is that
      it may help would-be docwriters to overcome their first hurdles.</para>

      <para>If you are looking for ready Firebird documentation and lots of
      it, your best starting places at this moment are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.ibphoenix.com">http://www.ibphoenix.com</ulink> -
          the IBPhoenix website.</para>

          <para>Follow the links <literal>Downloads -&gt; Main
          Downloads</literal> and <literal>Development -&gt; General
          Documentation</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=doc">http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=doc</ulink>
          - the Firebird Project's documentation page.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Do I really have to build the docs myself? Isn't there an easier
      way?</title>

      <para>Sure there's an easier way. As soon as a piece of documentation
      reaches a certain level of maturity, as well as after significant
      updates, it is published - as PDF and/or HTML - on the Firebird website.
      You can find all the docs we have published via the Documentation
      Subproject homepage:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=devel&amp;sub=doc">http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=devel&amp;sub=doc</ulink></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>You should download the manual module and build the docs yourself
      if and only if:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You want to check on the absolutely latest state of the docs.
          (Be aware though that one of the reasons a version has not yet been
          published may be that it contains errors.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You want to help write documentation yourself.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You're interested in learning how this doc building stuff
          works, and/or you think DIY is more fun than an easy file
          download.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If one of the above applies to your situation, this Howto is for
      you.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docbuildhowto-getting-the-module">
    <title>Getting the Firebird manual module from SourceForge</title>

    <para>The manual module is part of the Firebird CVS repository at
    SourceForge. In order to download it, you need a piece of software called
    a <firstterm>CVS client</firstterm>. This section describes the necessary
    steps to get the software and the manual module. The actual doc building
    will be discussed in the next main section: <xref
    linkend="docbuildhowto-building-the-docs" />.</para>

    <sect2 id="docbuildhowto-whatiscvs">
      <title>What is CVS?</title>

      <para>CVS means Concurrent Versions System. It is a tool to manage
      software development, useful both for single developers and for
      teamwork. Practically all projects at SourceForge use CVS to store and
      develop their code base. The Firebird CVS tree is divided into several
      so-called <firstterm>modules</firstterm>, the manual module being one of
      them.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docbuildhowto-cvs-clients">
      <title>CVS clients</title>

      <para>Downloading a module from a CVS repository is called
      <firstterm>checking out</firstterm> in CVS lingo. To do that, you need a
      CVS client; they exist for practically every operating system. Here's a
      list of CVS clients for some popular OS'es:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Linux, BSD and other Unices</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Command-line CVS is often pre-installed. If it isn't, use
              the admin tools of your distribution to install it - you'll
              typically find it in the development category. If that doesn't
              work for you, get it at <ulink
              url="http://www.cvshome.org/">http://www.cvshome.org</ulink></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>gCvs - a graphical CVS interface, at <ulink
              url="http://cvsgui.sourceforge.net/download.html">http://cvsgui.sourceforge.net/download.html</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Windows</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Command-line CVS at <ulink
              url="http://www.cvshome.org/">http://www.cvshome.org</ulink></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>WinCVS: Very powerful, but maybe a bit overwhelming if you
              are new to it. At <ulink
              url="http://cvsgui.sourceforge.net/download.html">http://cvsgui.sourceforge.net/download.html</ulink></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>TortoiseCVS: A Windows Explorer plugin. Brilliantly
              designed, very intuitive. Lacks some of the more advanced CVS
              functions, but has everything you need. Get it at <ulink
              url="http://tortoisecvs.sourceforge.net/download.shtml">http://tortoisecvs.sourceforge.net/download.shtml</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Mac OS X</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Mac OS X comes with command-line CVS already
              included.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Fink (Unix tools for OS X) contains a newer version of
              CVS. <ulink
              url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/index.php">http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/index.php</ulink></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>MacCvsX at <ulink
              url="http://cvsgui.sourceforge.net/download.html">http://cvsgui.sourceforge.net/download.html</ulink>
              - same project as gCvs and WinCvs. Note: OS X version still in
              beta.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>MacCVS Pro at <ulink
              url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/maccvspro/">http://sourceforge.net/projects/maccvspro/</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Mac Classic</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>MacCvs at <ulink
              url="http://cvsgui.sourceforge.net/download.html">http://cvsgui.sourceforge.net/download.html</ulink>
              - same project as gCvs and WinCvs</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>MacCVS Pro at <ulink
              url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/maccvspro/">http://sourceforge.net/projects/maccvspro/</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Others</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Try your luck at <ulink
              url="http://www.cvshome.org/">http://www.cvshome.org</ulink>,
              <ulink url="http://www.google.com">google</ulink> for it, or ask
              in the gnu.cvs.help newsgroup or on the firebird-docs mailing
              list.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Get one or more of the abovementioned clients and install
      according to the instructions that come with it. After that, you are
      ready to check out the manual module.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docbuildhowto-checking-out">
      <title>Checking out the manual module</title>

      <para>There are two ways you can check out the manual module: as an
      anonymous user, or with your SourceForge login name. The last method is
      often termed SSH checkout (because it uses a Secure SHell) or EXT
      checkout (because it uses SSH as an EXTernal protocol).</para>

      <para>Everybody can check out anonymously. Members of the Firebird
      project can also check out with their SourceForge login. (If you have an
      SF account but you aren't a Firebird project member, you can only check
      out anonymously.)</para>

      <para>If you are a project member, you'll usually want to check out with
      your SF login because</para>

      <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
        <listitem>
          <para>An anonymous checkout is not always up to date (delay may be
          several hours to several days);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you are going to contribute to the manual module yourself,
          you <emphasis>must</emphasis> checkout with your SF login or you
          won't be able to commit (= upload) your changes back to the
          server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>We'll describe both methods in the following subsections, starting
      with anon checkout. <link linkend="docbuildhowto-ssh-checkout">Click
      here</link> to jump to the subsection on SSH checkouts.</para>

      <sect3 id="docbuildhowto-anon-checkout">
        <title>Anonymous checkout</title>

        <para>The checkout procedure depends on which client you use. We'll
        give you the exact instructions for command line CVS, and generic info
        to be used with other clients.</para>

        <sect4 id="docbuildhowto-anon-checkout-commandline">
          <title>Anonymous checkout using command line CVS</title>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If you are in a graphical environment, open a command
              window.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>First, you have to verify the password with the server and
              store it locally. Give the command:</para>

              <para><command>cvs
              -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sf.net:/cvsroot/firebird
              login</command></para>

              <para>When prompted for a password, just hit
              <keysym>Enter</keysym>, because the password for user
              "anonymous" is empty. Your CVS client will store the password
              for later reuse, so you can skip this step in the future, as
              long as you don't login with other passwords in between.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Now you can get the manual module. Give the
              command:</para>

              <para><command>cvs -z6
              -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sf.net:/cvsroot/firebird checkout
              manual</command></para>

              <para>If all goes well, a directory called
              <filename>manual</filename> will by created below your current
              dir, and the manual source tree will be downloaded into it. You
              can now build the docs - read further <link
              linkend="docbuildhowto-building-the-docs">here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="docbuildhowto-anon-checkout-otherclients">
          <title>Anonymous checkout using other clients</title>

          <para>There's too much variation to give exact instructions for all
          CVS clients here. Consult the help or documentation for your own
          client. Elements you may need to fill in at some point are:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>protocol</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>this must be set to pserver (password server)</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>authentication method</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>same as protocol</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>server</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>cvs.sourceforge.net</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>repository</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>/cvsroot/firebird</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>user name</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>anonymous</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>module name</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>manual</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>cvsroot</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>usually a combination of server and repository,
                sometimes even with user name prepended (e.g. in WinCvs):
                cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/firebird or
                anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/firebird</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>Fill in the necessary data and give your client's checkout
          command. If the checkout succeeds, you now have a local copy of the
          manual module on your computer and are ready to build the docs. Read
          further <link
          linkend="docbuildhowto-building-the-docs">here</link>.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="docbuildhowto-ssh-checkout">
        <title>SSH checkout (with your SF login name)</title>

        <para>To be able to perform an SSH checkout, a secure shell client
        must be present on your system. On most Unix systems, as well as on
        Mac OS X, <application>OpenSSH</application> is installed by default.
        If not, check the distribution CD's or get it from <ulink
        url="http://www.openssh.com">http://www.openssh.com</ulink>. This site
        also contains pointers to other SSH products for OS'es not supported
        by OpenSSH. Note however that installing and configuring SSH on some
        platforms (including Windows) is not a trivial task. You can make life
        easier for yourself by choosing a CVS client that has SSH built in,
        like <application>TortoiseCVS</application> for Windows.</para>

        <para>As for the checking out itself: just as with anon checkouts, the
        procedure depends on which client you use. Again, we'll give exact
        instructions for command line CVS, and generic info for other
        clients.</para>

        <sect4 id="docbuildhowto-ssh-checkout-commandline">
          <title>SSH checkout using command line CVS</title>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If you are in a graphical environment, open a command
              window.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>First, make sure that you have an environment variable
              called <envar>CVS_RSH</envar> with the value <quote>ssh</quote>
              (or whatever your SSH client is called). How you must do this
              depends on your OS. On a DOS/Windows command line, use
              <command>set CVS_RSH=ssh</command>. Under Linux/bash:
              <command>export CVS_RSH=ssh</command>.</para>

              <para>You may want to make this envvar permanent so you can skip
              this step in the future. How to do this depends on your OS.
              Consult its documentation if necessary.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Give the following command to get the manual module
              (substitute <quote>username</quote> with your own SF
              username):</para>

              <para><command>cvs -z6
              -d:ext:username@cvs.sf.net:/cvsroot/firebird checkout
              manual</command></para>

              <para>Enter your password when prompted for it.</para>

              <para>If all goes well, a directory called
              <filename>manual</filename> will by created below your current
              dir, and the manual source tree will be downloaded into it. You
              can now build the docs - read further <link
              linkend="docbuildhowto-building-the-docs">here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="docbuildhowto-ssh-checkout-otherclients">
          <title>SSH checkout using other clients</title>

          <para>There's too much variation to give exact instructions for all
          CVS clients here. Consult the help or documentation for your own
          client. Elements you may need to fill in at some point are:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>protocol</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>this must be set to ext (or SSH, or SSL)</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>authentication method</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>same as protocol</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>server</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>cvs.sourceforge.net</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>repository</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>/cvsroot/firebird</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>user name</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>your SourceForge user name</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>module name</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>manual</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>cvsroot</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>usually a combination of server and repository,
                sometimes even with user name prepended (e.g. in WinCvs):
                <literal>cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/firebird</literal> or
                <literal>username@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/firebird</literal></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>Fill in the necessary data and give your client's checkout
          command. If the checkout succeeds, you now have a local copy of the
          manual module on your computer and are ready to build the docs. You
          can also commit changes you make locally back to the
          repository.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docbuildhowto-building-the-docs"
         xreflabel="Building the Firebird docs">
    <title>Building the Firebird docs</title>

    <para>The manual module comes with a build tool called Ant to produce the
    HTML and PDF docs from the DocBook XML source. Ant is a Java tool; it
    needs a recent version of Java 2 installed on your system.</para>

    <para>In the next subsections we will show you:</para>

    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Where to get Java 2</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How to set up the environment for the doc build process</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How to build the HTML and PDF docs</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>If you already have a recent version of Java 2 installed, you may
    <link linkend="docbuildhowto-setup-build-env">skip the first
    step</link>.</para>

    <sect2 id="docbuildhowto-get-java2" xreflabel="Where to get Java 2">
      <title>Where to get Java 2</title>

      <para>Download and install <emphasis>only one</emphasis> of the
      following:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Java 2 Runtime Environment, Standard Edition - often
          abbreviated as J2RE SE.</para>

          <para>Go to <ulink
          url="http://www.java.com/">http://www.java.com/</ulink> and follow
          the links to the download pages. Get the version for your own OS.
          Clicking on a "Download" or "Get it now" link may lead to windows
          popping up, asking you if it's OK that Sun Microsystems installs
          stuff on your computer. If you agree, practically everything will be
          installed automatically. If that makes you feel uneasy, you can also
          download the installation program manually and run it
          yourself.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Java 2 Software Development Kit, Standard Edition - or J2SDK
          SE.</para>

          <para>This is a much larger package, and it also contains the J2RE
          SE. If you want the SDK, go to <ulink
          url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/">http://java.sun.com/j2se/</ulink>
          and get the latest stable version. When you have to choose between
          JRE and SDK, take the SDK. (Yes, you can also get the J2RE from
          here, but you can get it easier and quicker from the link in the
          first option.) Download the installation program and run it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If you don't understand the difference between the two, go for the
      first option: the Java 2 Runtime Environment. You don't need the SDK to
      build the Firebird docs.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docbuildhowto-setup-build-env">
      <title>How to set up the environment for the build</title>

      <para>The build scripts need an environment variable
      <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> pointing to the Java 2 install
      directory.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>On Windows, this is typically something of the form
          <filename>C:\Program Files\Java\j2re1.4.2_01</filename>. To be sure,
          check if there's a directory called <filename>bin</filename>
          underneath it, and if this <filename>bin</filename> subdir contains
          the file <filename>java.exe</filename></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>On Linux, it may be <filename>/usr/lib/java/jre</filename> or
          <filename>/usr/java/j2sdk</filename>, or... well, it can be a lot of
          things. Same check applies: there should be a subdir
          <filename>bin</filename> underneath it containing an executable file
          <filename>java</filename> (without the <filename>.exe</filename>
          this time).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If you're lucky, the <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> envvar is already
      present and correct. If not, you have to set it yourself, e.g. under
      Windows with <command>set JAVA_HOME=C:\Program
      Files\Java\j2re1.4.2_01</command> or under Linux/bash with
      <command>export JAVA_HOME=/usr/lib/java/jre</command>. (Note: these
      paths are just examples; they may or may not be the same as
      yours.)</para>

      <para>Tip: make the <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> envvar permanent so you
      won't have to set it again and again. How to do this depends on your OS.
      Consult its documentation if necessary.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docbuildhowto-buidling-output-docs">
      <title>Building the HTML and PDF docs</title>

      <para>If you've made it here in one piece, you are finally ready to
      build the Firebird docs. Here's what to do:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you haven't done so already, this is the moment to read the
          <filename>ReadMe</filename> file that lives in the
          <filename>manual</filename> directory. It may contain important
          information not (yet) included in this Howto.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you are in a graphical environment, open a command
          window.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Unless the <filename>ReadMe</filename> instructs you
          otherwise, go to the folder <filename>manual\src\build</filename>
          and give the command</para>

          <para><command>build</command> (in Windows), or</para>

          <para><command>./build.sh</command> (in Linux)</para>

          <para>If everything was set up correctly, you now get a number of
          output lines ending with <literal>BUILD SUCCESSFUL</literal>, and
          mentioning some <firstterm>build targets</firstterm> (things you can
          build).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Now you can build something more substantial, e.g.</para>

          <para><command>build defaulthtml</command> or</para>

          <para><command>build pdf</command> or</para>

          <para><command>build docs</command></para>

          <para>Whatever you build will wind up in the directory tree under
          <filename>manual\dist\docs</filename></para>

          <para>Note: If you build the PDF target, you will receive tons of
          error messages. You can safely ignore them, as long as one of the
          last lines reads <literal>BUILD SUCCESSFUL</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>That's it - you are now a certified Firebird doc builder.
      Congratulations!</para>

      <para>If you want to write docs for the Firebird Project yourself, also
      read the <link linkend="docwritehowto">Firebird Docwriting
      Howto</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docbuildhowto-cvs-update">
    <title>Keeping your manual module up to date</title>

    <para>The manual module is a work in progress. Contributors commit changes
    to it on a regular basis. Some time after your initial checkout, your
    local copy will be out of sync with the repository at SourceForge. Of
    course it would be a waste of bandwidth if you had to check out the entire
    module time and again, only to update those few files that have changed.
    Moreover, doing so would overwrite any changes you may have made yourself.
    That's why CVS has an <command>update</command> command. With
    <command>update</command>, only the <emphasis>changes</emphasis> are
    downloaded from the server, and your own local changes are preserved. (In
    the event that another contributor has changed a file in the same spot as
    you, a conflict is signaled and you must edit the file in question to
    solve it.)</para>

    <para>Updating is dead easy. If you use command line CVS, go to the
    <filename class="directory">manual</filename> directory and type:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><command>cvs -z6 update -d</command></para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>This command is the same whether you checked out anonymously or with
    your SF login and password. CVS knows which server to contact and how to
    authenticate you because this information is saved in the <filename
    class="directory">manual/CVS</filename> subdirectory, which was created
    automatically when you first checked out the module. The only difference
    is that if you checked out with login and pass, you will also be prompted
    for your password when you run <command>update</command>.</para>

    <para>If you use another CVS tool, look for its <command>update</command>
    command or menu option.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docbuildhowto-troubleshooting">
    <title>If things go wrong</title>

    <para>If the build process fails, this may be due to a too old Java 2
    version. See <xref linkend="docbuildhowto-get-java2" /> for more info on
    getting the latest version.</para>

    <para>If anything else goes wrong and you can't get it right, ask for help
    on the firebird-docs mailing list. Please give a good description of your
    problem so we can help you better. If you aren't on the firebird-docs
    mailing list yet, visit <ulink
    url="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/firebird-docs">https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/firebird-docs</ulink>
    for information and subscription.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>