<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="docwritehowto">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>How to write documentation for Firebird</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Paul</firstname>

      <surname>Vinkenoog</surname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-introduction" xreflabel="Intro-section label">
    <title id="docwritehowto-intro-title"
    xreflabel="Intro-label">Introduction</title>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-purpose">
      <title>Purpose of this Howto</title>

      <para>This Howto discusses the various aspects of writing documentation
      for Firebird. It is intended for people who want to help write
      documentation for the Firebird project, or who at least strongly
      consider to do so. After reading this Howto, you'll have all the
      necessary knowledge to start writing Firebird docs in our chosen format
      DocBook XML.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-assumed-knowledge">
      <title>Assumed knowledge</title>

      <para>Before reading this Howto, check with yourself if you know:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>What the Firebird manual module is.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>What CVS is, and how to use a CVS client to download the
          current manual module.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>How to build the current Firebird documentation from your
          downloaded manual module.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This knowledge is essential if you are going to contribute to our
      documentation project. If you feel unsure about one or more of these
      points, you should first read the <link linkend="docbuildhowto">Firebird
      Docbuilding Howto</link>, and then come back here.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-topics">
      <title>Topics discussed in this Howto</title>

      <para>We start off with some short chapters about:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The firebird-docs mailing list.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Picking a subject.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Making an outline for your document-to-be.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>After that we'll take some time to explain the basics of DocBook
      XML, because that's the format we'd like you to deliver your docs in.
      Topics discussed include:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>DocBook XML - what is it?</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Reasons why we prefer DocBook so strongly to other
          formats.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Tools you can use to produce DocBook texts.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Don't worry if DocBook doesn't mean anything to you yet: the
      required knowledge can be learned in less than an hour, and chances are
      that you will benefit from this knowledge in other projects too,
      whenever you have to write technical documentation.</para>

      <para>The next part is about the actual docwriting:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Setting up the document itself.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Using DocBook elements.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A word or two on language and writing style.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Using PostgreSQL docs as a basis - and what's with
          copyrights?</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Finally, we will show you how to add your finished doc to the
      Firebird project. Main topics in this section are:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Commiting your finished document to the manual module.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Where to ask for commit rights if you don't have them.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>What the dos and don'ts are once you have received commit
          rights.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-docmakers-hangouts">
    <title>Where the docmakers meet</title>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-homepage">
      <title>The subproject homepage</title>

      <para>The homepage of the documentation subproject is here:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=devel&amp;sub=doc">http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=devel&amp;sub=doc</ulink></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>It contains news about our activities, links to the docs we've
      already published, plans for the future, etc.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-fd-mailinglist">
      <title>The firebird-docs list</title>

      <para>If you're serious about writing docs for Firebird, the first thing
      you should do is subscribe to the mailing list where we discuss our
      plans and our work. This list is open to everybody, and subscribing
      commits you to nothing. Send an email to:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><email>firebird-docs-request@lists.sourceforge.net</email></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>with the word <quote>subscribe</quote> either as subject or as the
      first and only line in the message body. Alternatively, you can fill in
      the form on this webpage:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/firebird-docs">http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/firebird-docs</ulink></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>Whichever method you choose, you'll receive an email message from
      the list robot within minutes. Follow the instructions in that message
      and you're on the list.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-fd-newsinterface">
      <title>The Atkin news interface</title>

      <para>There's also a news interface for this and other Firebird-related
      mailing lists. Sometimes it works a little problematically - or not at
      all, although that's rare - and I wouldn't use it to post messages if I
      were you, but it's great for archiving and browsing purposes. The
      retention is pretty long too, so if you grab all messages that are on
      the server you'll have a nice piece of list history from before you
      joined.</para>

      <para>To access these newsgroups, point your favorite newsreader
      to:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para>news.atkin.com</para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>and get the groups list. Subscribe to the groups you like. Notice
      that the firebird-docs list maps to the group sourceforge.firebird-doc
      (without s) on the Atkin news server.</para>

      <para>Depending on the newsreader or browser you use, this link may also
      get you straight to the group:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><ulink
        url="news://news.atkin.com/sourceforge.firebird-doc">news://news.atkin.com/sourceforge.firebird-doc</ulink></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>You can post to the newsgroup even if you're not subscribed to the
      mailing list, but in that case your message will be held for approval by
      a human moderator. This means that your message will be delayed by up to
      a day (or more, on rare occasions).</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-picking-a-subject">
    <title>Picking a subject</title>

    <para>These guidelines may help you in finding a subject to write
    about:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>First make sure you know what's already there - nobody's waiting
        for three MS-SQL-to-Firebird conversion guides.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Then ask yourself what's missing, and what may be useful for
        Firebird users in general, or perhaps just for a specific
        group.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Also ask yourself what you would <emphasis>like</emphasis> to
        write about. The most logical choice would be a topic you are familiar
        with, but you can also pick a subject you'd have to learn more about
        first (this is much more work of course, but a great learning
        experience if you're willing to invest the time).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You don't necessarily have to write an entire book, guide or
        article. Maybe there are already people working on a larger
        production, which you can contribute to. Maybe you can write one or
        more chapters for a book. Or maybe you can supply raw documentation
        material for a subject you know very well.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Talk about your ideas - or your search for ideas - on the
        firebird-docs list. The posting frequency can be very low at times,
        but rest assured that if you post there, your message
        <emphasis>will</emphasis> be read, and replied to.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-preparation">
    <title>Preparing to write: make an outline!</title>

    <para>It's always a good idea to make an outline before you start to write
    the actual text. Setting up an outline will help you to <quote>get
    organized</quote>; it reduces the chance of forgetting something vital,
    and it will make the actual writing job a lot easier.</para>

    <para>You can follow these steps when making your outline:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Define exactly what you want your readers to learn from your
        work.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Divide the subject matter into logical units - chapters and/or
        sections and/or subsections.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make sure the order of the units makes sense, especially for a
        howto, tutorial or user's guide. That is: arrange the units in such a
        way that whatever the user has to do first, or understand first, also
        comes first in your documentation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Present your outline on the firebird-docs list at
        sourceforge.net and ask for comments.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Once you are satisfied with your outline, look it over thoroughly
    and decide whether you have all the (raw) information you need to start
    writing. Ideally, you want to have all the information ready before you
    start to write, because sometimes a formerly unknown piece of information
    may lead you to choose a different document structure. You'd better have
    that information while you're still in the outline phase, then.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-docbook-intro">
    <title>DocBook XML - an introduction</title>

    <para>The chosen format for the documentation in the Firebird manual
    module is <firstterm>DocBook XML</firstterm>. For those of you who are not
    familiar with XML and/or DocBook, short introductions to XML in general
    and DocBook XML in particular follow. Be aware that these introductions
    give a grossly oversimplified picture. But that's just fine: you don't
    have to be a DocBook XML expert in order to write Firebird docs. You only
    need some basic knowledge - which you can pick up in half an hour from the
    paragraphs below - and a little experience in applying DocBook XML tags to
    your texts (which you will gain soon enough once you start
    writing).</para>

    <para><link linkend="docwritehowto-docbook-xml-primer">Skip the general
    XML primer</link> if you know all about XML elements, tags, attributes,
    rendering, and multichannel publishing.</para>

    <para><link linkend="docwritehowto-docbook-authoring-tools">Skip both
    primers</link> if you're also an experienced DocBook author.</para>

    <!--To be added: a note for people who REALLY don't want to learn DocBook but still have something useful to contribute.

We don't want to miss useful documentation because of a "DocBook or bust" mentality.-->

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-xml-primer">
      <title>A very general XML primer</title>

      <para>XML stands for <firstterm>Extensible Markup Language</firstterm>,
      which is, simply put, plain text with markup tags. A typical XML text
      fragment may look like this:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;paragraph&gt;
&lt;loud&gt;'No!'&lt;/loud&gt; she screamed. &lt;scary&gt;But the bloody hand
&lt;italics&gt;kept on creeping&lt;/italics&gt; towards her.&lt;/scary&gt;
&lt;picture file="bloody_hand.png"/&gt;
&lt;/paragraph&gt;</programlisting>

      <sect3 id="docwritehowto-tags-and-attributes">
        <title>Tags and attributes</title>

        <para>In the example given above, the words and phrases enclosed in
        angle brackets are the markup tags. <sgmltag
        class="starttag">italics</sgmltag> is a <firstterm>start
        tag</firstterm>, <sgmltag class="endtag">italics</sgmltag> is an
        <firstterm>end tag</firstterm>, and <sgmltag class="emptytag">picture
        file="bloody_hand.png"</sgmltag> is a standalone tag, officially
        termed <firstterm>empty-element tag</firstterm>. XML tags are always
        formatted like this:</para>

        <table id="docwritehowto-table-XML-tags">
          <title>Format of XML tags</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Tag type</entry>

                <entry>Starts with</entry>

                <entry>Ends with</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Start tag</entry>

                <entry><literal>&lt;</literal></entry>

                <entry><literal>&gt;</literal></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>End tag</entry>

                <entry><literal>&lt;/</literal></entry>

                <entry><literal>&gt;</literal></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Empty-element tag</entry>

                <entry><literal>&lt;</literal></entry>

                <entry><literal>/&gt;</literal></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>Still referring to our example, the words
        <literal>paragraph</literal>, <literal>loud</literal>,
        <literal>scary</literal>, <literal>italics</literal> and
        <literal>picture</literal> are <firstterm>tag names</firstterm>. In
        the <sgmltag class="emptytag">picture...</sgmltag> tag, <sgmltag
        class="attribute">file="bloody_hand.png"</sgmltag> is called an
        <firstterm>attribute</firstterm>, with <sgmltag
        class="attribute">file</sgmltag> the <firstterm>attribute
        name</firstterm> and <sgmltag
        class="attvalue">bloody_hand.png</sgmltag> the <firstterm>attribute
        value</firstterm>. Attribute values must always be quoted; both single
        and double quotes are allowed.</para>

        <para>XML allows you to define any tags you like, as long as you build
        them correctly. So <sgmltag class="starttag">thistag</sgmltag>,
        <sgmltag class="starttag">thattag</sgmltag>, and <sgmltag
        class="emptytag">this_is_not_a_tag</sgmltag> are all valid XML
        tags.</para>

        <para>Clearly the tags themselves are not meant to appear in the final
        document (that is, the document as it is presented to the readers).
        Rather, they contain instructions that affect its appearance. XML,
        when used for writing documentation, is a typical <firstterm>source
        format</firstterm>, intended to be processed by software to produce
        nicely formatted output documents. This processing is usually called
        <firstterm>rendering</firstterm>.</para>

        <para>Some tags are unmistakably makeup instructions:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;italics&gt;kept on creeping&lt;/italics&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>means of course that the words <emphasis>kept on
        creeping</emphasis> must be displayed or printed in italics.
        However,</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;loud&gt;'No!'&lt;/loud&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>is a little less obvious. Should the word <literal>No!</literal>
        appear in boldface? Or underlined? Or again in italics? Or maybe this
        text is going to be read out aloud by a speech synthesizer, and the
        <sgmltag class="starttag">loud</sgmltag> tag instructs it to raise its
        voice? All these things are possible, and what's more: often a single
        XML source document is converted into several different output formats
        - say, a PDF document, an HTML web page, and a sound file. This is
        called <firstterm>multichannel publishing</firstterm>. With
        multichannel publishing, <sgmltag class="starttag">loud</sgmltag> may
        be translated to boldface for the PDF document; to a bold, red-colored
        font for the web page; and to a 50% volume increase for the
        synthesizer.</para>

        <para>Looking at the other tags, <sgmltag
        class="emptytag">picture...</sgmltag> is obviously an instruction to
        insert the image <filename>bloody_hand.png</filename> into the
        document, and <sgmltag class="starttag">scary</sgmltag>, well... this
        is even less clear then <sgmltag class="starttag">loud</sgmltag>.
        Maybe the phrase between the <sgmltag class="starttag">scary</sgmltag>
        tags has to drip with blood. Maybe frightening music must be played
        here. It all depends on the people who defined the tags, and the
        software they use to do the rendering.</para>

        <para>The <sgmltag class="starttag">paragraph</sgmltag> tag, finally,
        is a structural tag. It tells us something about the place that the
        lines have within the document's internal hierarchy. In the final
        document, paragraphs may or may not be separated by empty lines.
        Again, that depends on the rendering software and possibly also on
        user-configurable options. Other structural tags one might think of
        are e.g. <sgmltag class="starttag">chapter</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
        class="starttag">section</sgmltag>, and <sgmltag
        class="starttag">subdocument</sgmltag>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Special characters and Entities</title>

        <para>Because the character '<literal>&lt;</literal>' has a special
        meaning as the start of a tag, you can't include it directly as a
        literal value. Instead, if you want your readers to see an opening
        angle bracket, you type this:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <para><sgmltag class="genentity">lt</sgmltag></para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>That's an ampersand, followed by the letters
        <literal>l</literal> and <literal>t</literal> (for <emphasis>less
        than</emphasis>), followed by a semicolon. You can also use <sgmltag
        class="genentity">gt</sgmltag> (<emphasis>greater than</emphasis>) for
        the closing angle bracket, although that's not necessary.</para>

        <para>XML has lots of codes like this; they are called
        <firstterm>entities</firstterm>. Some represent characters, like
        <sgmltag class="genentity">lt</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
        class="genentity">auml</sgmltag> (lower a with umlaut) and some serve
        totally different purposes. But they all start with an ampersand and
        end with a semicolon.</para>

        <para>But wait a minute... if an ampersand marks the start of an
        entity, how do you include a literal ampersand in your text? Well,
        there's an entity for that too:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <para><sgmltag class="genentity">amp</sgmltag></para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>So this line of XML:</para>

        <programlisting>Kernigan &amp;amp; Ritchie chose '&amp;lt;' as the less-than operator for C.</programlisting>

        <para>will wind up in the final documents as:</para>

        <para><literal>Kernigan &amp; Ritchie chose '&lt;' as the less-than
        operator for C.</literal></para>

        <para>And here's some good news: if you use a dedicated XML editor to
        author your document, you can probably just type
        '<literal>&lt;</literal>' and '<literal>&amp;</literal>' anywhere you
        want to use them as literals. The editor will make sure that they end
        up as <sgmltag class="genentity">lt</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
        class="genentity">amp</sgmltag> in the XML as it is saved to disk.
        You'll find pointers to some XML/DocBook editors later in this
        Howto.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="docwritehowto-elements">
        <title>Elements</title>

        <para>There's one more important XML concept you need to know about:
        the <firstterm>element</firstterm>. An element is the combination of a
        start tag, a matching end tag, and everything in between. This
        <quote>everything in between</quote> is called the element's
        <firstterm>content</firstterm>, and it may include other elements.
        Elements are named after their tags, so we can talk about paragraph
        elements, italics elements etc.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Actually, elements are a more basic concept than tags: tags
          just happen to be the things that identify the elements. So it would
          be better to say that tags are named after their elements. But
          because tags are easier to recognize than entire elements, I thought
          I'd introduce you to them first.</para>
        </note>

        <para>This is an element:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;loud&gt;'No!'&lt;/loud&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This is also an element:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;paragraph&gt;This is an element containing &lt;bold&gt;another&lt;/bold&gt; element!&lt;/paragraph&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>Empty-element tags constitute an element all by themselves.
        These elements can have no content of course, because they don't have
        a <emphasis>pair</emphasis> of tags:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;picture file="bloody_hand.png"/&gt;</programlisting>

        <important>
          <para>Don't confuse content with attributes. Content lives
          <emphasis>between</emphasis> tags, attributes
          <emphasis>within</emphasis> tags. The empty element in the last
          example has an attribute, but no content.</para>
        </important>

        <para>I'm stressing the element concept here because most
        documentation tends to speak of <quote>chapter elements</quote>,
        <quote>title elements</quote> etc. rather than <quote>chapter
        tags</quote> and <quote>title tags</quote>. The terms are often used
        interchangeably, but there are cases where it's important to know the
        difference.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>XML Conclusion</title>

        <para>Good - that's about all you need to know about XML. By now you
        should have a general idea of what an XML text looks like, what tags
        and elements are, and what they are for. As said earlier, the picture
        is oversimplified but it's good enough for our purposes.</para>

        <para>It should also be understood that just writing away in plain,
        self-invented XML is pretty pointless unless you have processing
        software that understands <emphasis>your</emphasis> tags. How else are
        you going to turn your XML source into a nicely formatted, presentable
        document?</para>

        <para>Fortunately, we don't have to worry about developing our own
        element definitions and conversion software. There are a number of
        formalized XML types available, each defining a number of tags and,
        equally important, a number of rules on how to use them. DocBook XML
        is one of those types.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-docbook-xml-primer">
      <title>A DocBook XML primer</title>

      <para>DocBook was designed to facilitate the writing of structured
      documents using SGML or XML (but don't worry about SGML - we use the XML
      strain). It is particularly fit for writing technical books and
      articles, especially on computer-related subjects. DocBook XML is
      defined in its <firstterm>Document Type Definition</firstterm> or
      <firstterm>DTD</firstterm>: a set of definitions and rules describing
      exactly how a DocBook document should be structured. DocBook is rapidly
      becoming a de facto standard for computer-technical documents, and it is
      supported by a growing number of tools and applications.</para>

      <sect3 id="docwritehowto-docbook-characteristics">
        <title>DocBook XML Characteristics</title>

        <para>Important characteristics of DocBook - as opposed to
        <quote>general</quote> XML - are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The DocBook DTD defines a limited number of tags, and it
            gives exact rules on how to use them: what attributes are possible
            for a tag A, whether element B can be nested within element C, and
            so on. If you use undefined tags, or if you don't follow the
            rules, your document isn't DocBook anymore (and DocBook-supporting
            processing tools will probably break on it).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>DocBook tags always convey structure and semantics
            (meaning), <emphasis>never</emphasis> makeup. In DocBook, you'll
            find structural tags like <sgmltag
            class="starttag">book</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">part</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">chapter</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">section</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">para</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">table</sgmltag>; and semantic tags like <sgmltag
            class="starttag">filename</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">warning,</sgmltag> <sgmltag
            class="starttag">emphasis</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">postcode</sgmltag>; but nothing like <sgmltag
            class="starttag">font</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">bold</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">center</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">indent</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">backgroundcolor</sgmltag> - nothing that has to
            do with layout or makeup.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Because of this, a decision has to be taken somewhere on how
            the DocBook tags are translated into presentational makeup. This
            decision (or rather: the rendering rules) can be hardcoded in the
            tools but that would make things very inflexible. That's why the
            rules are mostly defined in <firstterm>stylesheets</firstterm>. A
            stylesheet is a document, usually in plaintext, that tells the
            tool stuff like:<blockquote>
                <para><quote>Print chapter titles in a 24-point black font;
                start each chapter on a new page; use italics for emphasis;
                render warnings in a bold, 12-point red font; use smallcaps
                for acronyms; etc. etc.</quote></para>
              </blockquote>This approach enables the user to alter the
            stylesheets if he or she doesn't like the appearance of the final
            document. It would be a lot harder - if not impossible - to alter
            the tools themselves.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="docwritehowto-docbook-benefits">
        <title>Benefits of DocBook XML</title>

        <para>DocBook has a lot of advantages for anybody writing technical
        documentation. These are the most important ones for us:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The number one advantage of using a source format like
            DocBook, which has no presentational markup whatsoever, is that
            the source document consists of pure, unpolluted,
            <emphasis>content</emphasis>. That in turn means that we have all
            our options open when it comes to translating the source to
            different output formats like HTML and PDF.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Another advantage is that DocBook is an open standard, not
            tied to any commercial application or even a particular OS. If you
            download the Firebird manual module, you can build the HTML and
            PDF docs from the DocBook source both under Linux and under
            Windows - and we can add support for more OS's if need be.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Because DocBook is all about structure and meaning, it will
            be surprisingly easy to transform your outline into a DocBook
            skeleton.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>With DocBook, you never have to worry about the makeup of
            your text. You never have to ask yourself if an 18-pt font would
            be better than a 24-pt one for section headers; you don't have to
            decide on the colors used for chapter titles, or if chapters
            should always start at the top of an uneven page. All you have to
            care about is <emphasis>structure</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>informational content</emphasis>. If you are used to
            writing text in e.g. Word, where you take makeup decisions all the
            time (ususally without even realizing it), this may take a little
            getting used to, but I can promise you: you'll soon get the hang
            of it, and after a while you will find this absence of makeup
            instructions a relief instead of a burden.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Many different people are producing docs for the manual
            module (well, actually that's a lie, but it may one day become
            true - let's remain optimistic). If all these people wrote in
            different formats, or even in one format like Word or HTML, their
            documents would all look very different because every contributor
            would make his or her own makeup decisions. Of course we could
            develop a set of makeup rules, but then every single docwriter
            would have to learn those rules, or at least have them handy while
            writing, and take care to apply them all the time. Nah... better
            put those rules in one central place: the stylesheets, and let the
            docmakers worry about documentation, not presentation. The
            stylesheets will ensure that all our documentation has the same
            look-and-feel.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If we don't like the makeup of our documents, we can easily
            change it if the makeup rules are in a stylesheet. Nothing needs
            to be altered in the DocBook source documents; all we have to do,
            after changing the stylesheets, is re-render the docs. Newly
            developed docs will automatically get the new look. Try to achieve
            that if the makeup is scattered in a thousand places all over the
            documents themselves!</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A DocBook document is pure text, which is ideal for use in
            CVS. Yes, a CVS tree can also contain binary files, but many
            useful features that CVS offers (showing the difference between
            two versions of a file, for instance) only work with text
            files.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Admittedly, none of these benefits is unique to DocBook. But
        DocBook has them all, and it's widely supported. That makes it the
        perfect choice for our Firebird documentation.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="docwritehowto-docbook-links">
        <title>DocBook documentation on the Internet</title>

        <para>Here are some links in case you want to find out more about
        DocBook:<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><ulink
              url="http://opensource.bureau-cornavin.com/crash-course/">http://opensource.bureau-cornavin.com/crash-course/</ulink></para>

              <para><citetitle>Writing Documentation Using DocBook - A Crash
              Course</citetitle> by David Rugge, Mark Galassi and Eric
              Bischoff. A very nice tutorial, even though most of the tools
              discussed are not the ones we use.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><ulink
              url="http://docbook.org/tdg/en/">http://docbook.org/tdg/en/</ulink></para>

              <para><citetitle>DocBook - The Definitive Guide</citetitle>, by
              Norman Walsh and Leonard Muellner. Don't expect it to be a
              beginner-friendly tutorial - in fact, the first part is quite
              intimidating if you're a DocBook newbie. The reason I mention it
              here is its great online element reference, which I often
              consult while I'm writing.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><ulink
              url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-Demystification-HOWTO/">http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-Demystification-HOWTO/</ulink></para>

              <para>The <citetitle>DocBook Demystification Howto</citetitle>
              is interesting if you want to know a little more about XML and
              DocBook than what we've told you here. It also contains quite a
              lot of material on SGML, and - again - on tools we don't use for
              the Firebird documentation subproject.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><ulink
              url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook">http://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook</ulink></para>

              <para>The DocBook open source project at SourceForge.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>

        <para>If you know of some other great online resource, please let use
        know by posting a message to the firebird-docs list.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-docbook-authoring-tools">
    <title>DocBook XML authoring tools</title>

    <para>Because DocBook is a non-binary format, you can use any plaintext
    editor like <application>emacs</application>,
    <application>pico</application>, <application>Windows
    Notepad</application> or <application>vi</application> to write your
    documentation. And indeed, some docmakers prefer this approach to other
    more sophisticated tools because it gives them full control over their
    text, and the hand-typed tags are always visible. But the penalty is that
    text editors can not <emphasis>validate</emphasis> your DocBook document:
    you'll only notice your mistakes when a build goes wrong. And the
    structure of your document - especially a large document - is also
    difficult to see in text mode, although a consistent use of multi-level
    indentation can do a lot of good here.</para>

    <para>If you choose this approach or want to try it out, it would be a
    good idea to at least take an editor that's capable of XML syntax
    highlighting. A very good one, and free at that, is
    <application>ConText</application>. Get it at <ulink
    url="http://www.fixedsys.com/context/">http://www.fixedsys.com/context/</ulink>.</para>

    <para>But for most people a dedicated tool is preferable. XML authoring
    tools usually have graphical interfaces to make the tags stand out nicely
    (and sometimes irritatingly); many allow you to collapse and expand
    elements so you can view the structure of your document and at the same
    time zoom in on the element you're working on; they may also let you
    switch between different views. Some have a special DocBook mode so your
    document can be validated as not only correct XML, but also correct
    DocBook.</para>

    <para>The author of this Howto has tried out a number of these tools (free
    ones, cheap ones, and evaluation versions) and found <application>XMLMind
    XML Editor</application> to be the most useful. This is a personal opinion
    of course; your experience may differ.</para>

    <para>Some XML editors you may want to evaluate:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><application>XMLMind XML Editor</application>, or
        <application>XXE</application> for short. The Standard Edition is
        free.</para>

        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/">http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/</ulink></para>

        <para>Runs on: Linux, Windows, Mac OS X. Requires Java, but you need
        Java anyway or you won't be able to build the docs from the sources -
        see the <link linkend="docbuildhowto">Firebird Docbuilding
        Howto</link>.</para>

        <para>Features: Tree view (all elements collapsible) and Styled view
        (chapters and sections collapsible). The latter is what I usually work
        in: it shows the document in a basic but clear word-processor-like
        layout, defined in a stylesheet that comes with the program. Both
        views can be active simultaneously. DocBook mode won't let you enter
        anything non-DocBook. Element chooser. Attribute editor. Edit and
        Search functions. Spell checker. Special character picker.
        Speedbuttons to create frequently used elements like sections, lists,
        tables, etc. What I miss is a plaintext XML source view.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><application>epcEdit</application>. € 89 for non-comercial use.
        Free 60-day evaluation.</para>

        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.epcedit.com">http://www.epcedit.com</ulink></para>

        <para>Runs on: Linux, Windows, Solaris. Requires Tcl/Tk 8.1 or above
        (included in package).</para>

        <para>Features: Structure tree pane. Element chooser. Attribute
        editor. Document pane can switch between plaintext and graphic XML
        mode. No special DocBook mode, but can validate any XML document based
        upon its DTD.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><application>Altova XMLSpy Home Edition</application>. $ 49.
        Free 30-day evalution.</para>

        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.altova.com/products_ide.html">http://www.altova.com/products_ide.html</ulink></para>

        <para>Runs on: Windows. (Also reported to run on Linux using Wine, and
        on Mac OS X using Virtual PC 6.)</para>

        <para>Features: Text, Grid (boxes-in-boxes), and Browser views. All
        elements collapsible except in Text view. Browser view is read-only.
        Element chooser. Attribute editor. Edit and Search functions. Special
        character picker.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><application>Altova Authentic</application>. Free.</para>

        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.altova.com/products_doc.html">http://www.altova.com/products_doc.html</ulink></para>

        <para>Runs on, Features: same as <application>Altova
        XMLSpy</application>, but lacks Text and Grid views. Has
        <quote>Authentic</quote> view instead, and a spelling checker.
        <application>Altova Authentic</application> is actually a frontend; it
        uses a restricted version of <application>XMLSpy</application> as
        backend.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This list is not meant to be exhaustive, but if you know a
    <emphasis>good</emphasis> XML editor (good from the perspective of a
    Firebird docwriter) that you think should be in here, please let us know
    via the mailing list.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-writing-docbook">
    <title>Writing your DocBook doc</title>

    <para>Hello - still with us? I know I spent quite some time explaining
    about XML and DocBook, but I really feel I had to do that because these
    are new concepts to a lot of people. Just giving them some links and
    telling them to go find out by themselves would probably lose us some
    otherwise valuable docwriters.</para>

    <para>Anyway, here we are: finally ready to start writing our doc. This
    section discusses setting up your DocBook document, and applying the right
    tags and attributes in the right places.</para>

    <para>Please read the <link
    linkend="docwritehowto-elements-hierarchical">subsection on hierarchical
    elements</link> even if you're a proficient DocBook writer, as it contains
    some guidelines specific to our project. After that, you can skip the rest
    of the DocBook subsections.</para>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-creating-the-doc">
      <title>Creating the document</title>

      <para>All our documentation is part of one big DocBook element: the
      <sgmltag class="starttag">set</sgmltag>. This is the topmost element in
      the DocBook hierarchy. Our set contains a number of <sgmltag
      class="starttag">book</sgmltag>'s, which in turn contain <sgmltag
      class="starttag">chapter</sgmltag>'s, and so on. The advantage of
      placing all the books in one set is that they can reference each other,
      i.e. you can insert links in your documentation pointing to an exact
      spot in another book.</para>

      <para>Fortunately, placing all the books in one big set does not imply
      that they also have to live in one big document. DocBook allows you to
      set up a main document as shown below. (Don't worry if you don't
      understand the section starting with "<literal>&lt;!DOCTYPE</literal>" -
      we already have a main document, you won't have to write horrible stuff
      like that yourself.)</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;

&lt;!DOCTYPE set PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "file:docbookx.dtd" [
    &lt;!ENTITY firebird-intro SYSTEM "file:fbintro.xml"&gt;
    &lt;!ENTITY firebird-sql-ref SYSTEM "file:fbsqlref.xml"&gt;
    &lt;!ENTITY ...&gt;
    &lt;!ENTITY ...&gt;
]&gt;

&lt;set id="firebird-books"&gt;
  &amp;firebird-intro;
  &amp;firebird-sql-ref;
  ...
  ...
&lt;/set&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>With the main document set up like above, the various books can be
      in separate files: <filename>fbintro.xml</filename>,
      <filename>fbsqlref.xml</filename>, etc., which we can edit
      independently. Such a file - yours, for instance - is roughly structured
      like this:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;

&lt;book id="fbintro"&gt;
  &lt;chapter id="fbintro-preface"&gt;
    ...
    ...
  &lt;/chapter&gt;
  &lt;chapter id="fbintro-installing-firebird"&gt;
    ...
    ...
  &lt;/chapter&gt;
  ...
  ...
&lt;/book&gt;    </programlisting>

      <para>Of course if you set up a new document it must be made known to
      the main set, but this is something we'll discuss with you when you're
      ready to start writing. (We don't give a general rule here because it
      depends on what you're going to write - a book, an article, a chapter, a
      couple of chapters... - and how your work fits in with the rest.)</para>

      <para>Every DocBook file must start with this line:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>If you write your documentation <quote>by hand</quote>, i.e. in a
      text editor, you must type that line yourself. If you use a dedicated
      XML editor it will be inserted automatically when you create a new
      document.</para>

      <para>You should always place your document in the <filename
      class="directory">src\docs\firebirddocs</filename> subdirectory of the
      manual tree.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-typing-text">
      <title>Typing text</title>

      <para>If you type your DocBook XML text in an text editor like
      <application>Notepad</application>, <application>emacs</application> or
      <application>ConText</application>, you can use linebreaks, indentation
      and multiple spaces just as you please. Every occurrence of
      <firstterm>whitespace</firstterm> (a sequence of one or more
      <literal>space</literal>, <literal>tab</literal>,
      <literal>linefeed</literal> or <literal>formfeed</literal> characters)
      will be converted to a single space character in the output. So
      this:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;section&gt;&lt;title&gt;Firebird Architectures&lt;/title&gt;&lt;para&gt;Now let's have a look at
Firebird's different architectures.&lt;/para&gt;&lt;itemizedlist&gt;&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;First, 
there's the so-called &lt;firstterm&gt;Classic Server&lt;/firstterm&gt;.&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Then there is &lt;firstterm&gt;Superserver&lt;/firstterm&gt; architecture.
&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;And finally, with the release of Firebird 1.5
we also have the &lt;firstterm&gt;embedded server&lt;/firstterm&gt;.&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;/itemizedlist&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>will result in the same output as this:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;section&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Firebird Architectures&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;para&gt;
    Now let's have a look at Firebird's different architectures.
  &lt;/para&gt;
  &lt;itemizedlist&gt;
    &lt;listitem&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;First, there's the so-called 
        &lt;firstterm&gt;Classic Server&lt;/firstterm&gt;.&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/listitem&gt;
    &lt;listitem&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;Then there is &lt;firstterm&gt;Superserver&lt;/firstterm&gt; architecture.&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/listitem&gt;
    &lt;listitem&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;And finally, with the release of Firebird 1.5 we also
        have the &lt;firstterm&gt;embedded server&lt;/firstterm&gt;.&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;/itemizedlist&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Needless to say, the second form is much easier to read and
      understand for a human. So if you type your XML by hand, format the text
      in such a way that the structure is as clear as possible. Like the
      prophets said: <quote>Indent! Indent! Indent!</quote> (Or was that
      repent? No, I'm sure it was indent.)</para>

      <para>If, on the other hand, you use a dedicated XML editor, hitting
      <keycap>Enter</keycap> may close the current <sgmltag
      class="starttag">para</sgmltag> and open a new one. Make sure you know
      how your editor behaves in this respect, and use the Enter key
      accordingly. Also check what happens to multiple consecutive whitespace
      characters, as some XML editors may use special tricks to preserve
      them.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-frequently-used-elements">
      <title>Elements we use frequently</title>

      <para>This section discusses the DocBook elements we use most in our
      Firebird docs. It includes lots of examples in DocBook XML format. If
      you use an XML authoring tool, what you see on your screen may look
      nothing like the examples given here, but if you open your XML file in a
      text editor - or choose a text view in your XML tool - you will see the
      actual XML. You may also have a look at the XML sources that are already
      in the manual module, to see how the other authors build up their docs
      and apply tags.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>This is a very long section, but don't let that discourage you.
        My advice is that you <emphasis>carefully</emphasis> read the
        subsection on hierarchical elements, and skim the others. Don't worry
        if there are things you don't understand at once, and by no means try
        to learn the material by heart! Just have this Howto handy when you
        write your doc, and revisit the element subsections from time to time
        (like when you need them).</para>
      </tip>

      <sect3 id="docwritehowto-elements-hierarchical">
        <title>Hierarchical elements</title>

        <para>The most common hierarchy is, starting at the top: <sgmltag
        class="starttag">set</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
        class="starttag">book</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
        class="starttag">chapter</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
        class="starttag">section</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
        class="starttag">para</sgmltag>. Section elements are a bit different
        from the rest in that there are two flavors of them:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>First, the <sgmltag class="starttag">section</sgmltag>
            element as quoted above. It can be used recursively, i.e. you can
            have a <sgmltag class="starttag">section</sgmltag> in a <sgmltag
            class="starttag">section</sgmltag> in a <sgmltag
            class="starttag">section</sgmltag>... This flavor has the
            advantage that you can move entire subtrees up or down in the
            hierarchy without having to change the tags.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Then there's the <sgmltag class="starttag">sect1</sgmltag>,
            <sgmltag class="starttag">sect2</sgmltag> ... <sgmltag
            class="starttag">sect5</sgmltag> range. These elements must be
            properly nested, with <sgmltag class="starttag">sect1</sgmltag> at
            the top, <sgmltag class="starttag">sect2</sgmltag> within <sgmltag
            class="starttag">sect1</sgmltag> etc. You cannot put a <sgmltag
            class="starttag">sect3</sgmltag> directly in a <sgmltag
            class="starttag">sect1</sgmltag>. This is less flexible than
            <sgmltag class="starttag">section</sgmltag>, but in practice it
            rarely hurts. After all, the same <quote>rigidity</quote> applies
            to <sgmltag class="starttag">set</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
            class="starttag">book</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
            class="starttag">chapter</sgmltag> and we can live with that,
            too.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
          <para>In previous versions of this Howto, the <sgmltag
          class="starttag">sectN</sgmltag> series was recommended for
          presentational reasons. Due to improvements in the stylesheets, this
          is no longer an issue. Pick whichever you want.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Books, chapters and top-level sections should always have an
        <firstterm>id</firstterm> and a <firstterm>title</firstterm>. The id
        allows an element to be referenced from another part of the document,
        and even from another document in the set. <sgmltag
        class="attribute">Id</sgmltag> is an attribute, which means that it
        appears within a tag; it's not visible in the rendered docs (except in
        the HTML source text; moreover, top-level section ids are used for the
        HTML file names). <sgmltag class="element">Title</sgmltag> is an
        element, often the first child element to be found in its parent. The
        content of the title element will appear in the output docs.</para>

        <para>If you write a book or an article, it's also a good idea to
        include a <sgmltag class="starttag">bookinfo</sgmltag> or <sgmltag
        class="starttag">articleinfo</sgmltag> element, where you can put
        author information (and more).</para>

        <para>The following example gives you an idea of how to structure your
        document:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;

&lt;book id="usersguide"&gt;

  &lt;bookinfo&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Firebird Users Guide&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;author&gt;
      &lt;firstname&gt;William&lt;/firstname&gt;
      &lt;surname&gt;Shakespeare&lt;/surname&gt;
    &lt;/author&gt;
  &lt;/bookinfo&gt;

  &lt;chapter id="usersguide-intro"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;para&gt;
      Hello! This is the introductory text to the Firebird Users Guide.
    &lt;/para&gt;
  &lt;/chapter&gt;

  &lt;chapter id="usersguide-download-install"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Downloading and installing Firebird&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;para&gt;
      In this chapter we'll demonstrate how to download and install Firebird.
    &lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;section id="usersguide-download"&gt;
      &lt;title&gt;Downloading Firebird&lt;/title&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;
        To download Firebird from the Internet, first go to the following URL: etc. 
        etc. etc.
      &lt;/para&gt;
      ...more paragraphs, possibly subsections...
    &lt;/section&gt;
    &lt;section id="usersguide-install"&gt;
      &lt;title&gt;Installing Firebird&lt;/title&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;
        Installing Firebird on your system goes like this: etc. etc.
      &lt;/para&gt;
      ...more paragraphs, possibly subsections...
    &lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;/chapter&gt;

  ...more chapters...

&lt;/book&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>Some rules and remarks:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>First, notice again that attribute values must always be
            quoted. (But if you fill them in in an attribute editor, don't
            insert them: the editor will take care of the quotes.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <sgmltag class="element">title</sgmltag> of a book or
            article may appear in the <sgmltag class="element">book</sgmltag>
            or <sgmltag class="element">article</sgmltag> element itself, but
            also in the <sgmltag class="element">bookinfo</sgmltag> or
            <sgmltag class="element">articleinfo</sgmltag> element. It is even
            legal to include it in both, but in that case the two <sgmltag
            class="element">title</sgmltag>'s <emphasis>must</emphasis> have
            the same content. In other words: pick one or the other, not both,
            if you want to stay out of trouble.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> attributes must
            be unique within the entire bookset.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Within a book or article, all <sgmltag
            class="attribute">id</sgmltag>'s should start with the same
            lowercase word, e.g. <literal>usersguide</literal>, followed by a
            dash, followed by one or more other lowercase words. Examples are
            <literal>usersguide-intro</literal> and
            <literal>usersguide-download-install</literal>. This is not a
            DocBook requirement, but our own convention.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>As you can see in the example, <sgmltag
            class="element">chapter</sgmltag>'s and <sgmltag
            class="element">section</sgmltag>'s can start directly with one or
            more <sgmltag class="element">para</sgmltag> elements. But once
            you include sections in a chapter, or subsections in a section,
            you can't add any more <sgmltag class="element">para</sgmltag>
            elements after them, only within them. Good DocBook-aware XML
            editors simply won't let you do such a thing, but if you type your
            DocBook XML by hand this is something you need to be aware
            of.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you use an XML editor, chances are that you rarely have
            to create <sgmltag class="element">para</sgmltag> elements
            explicitly. For instance, if I insert a <sgmltag
            class="element">chapter</sgmltag> or a <sgmltag
            class="element">section</sgmltag> in <application>XMLMind XML
            Editor</application>, the first - empty - <sgmltag
            class="element">para</sgmltag> is automatically created. And when
            I type text in a paragraph and hit <keycap>ENTER</keycap>, that
            paragraph is automatically closed with a <sgmltag
            class="endtag">para</sgmltag> and a next one created.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><link linkend="docwritehowto-other-writing-aspects">Skip the
        rest of the DocBook elements subsections</link> if you already know
        everything about DocBook elements.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Lists</title>

        <para>DocBook offers various list elements, of which three are used
        frequently:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">itemizedlist</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>An <sgmltag class="element">itemizedlist</sgmltag> is used
              to enumerate items whose order is not (very) important:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;itemizedlist&gt;
  &lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Oranges are juicy&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Apples are supposed to be healthy&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Most people find lemons way too sour&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;/itemizedlist&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>The items in the list are generally marked with a bullet
              in the rendered output docs:</para>

              <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                  <para>Oranges are juicy</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Apples are supposed to be healthy</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Most people find lemons way too sour</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">orderedlist</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use an <sgmltag class="element">orderedlist</sgmltag> when
              you want to stress the order of the entries:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;orderedlist numeration="loweralpha"&gt;
  &lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Pick the lock&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Rob the house&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Get arrested&lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;/orderedlist&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>By default, arabic numerals will be placed before the
              items, but you can change this with the <sgmltag
              class="attribute">numeration</sgmltag> attribute. Here's how the
              above example is rendered:</para>

              <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha" spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                  <para>Pick the lock</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Rob the house</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Get arrested</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">variablelist</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A <sgmltag class="element">variablelist</sgmltag> consists
              of a number of terms and their descriptions or
              definitions:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;variablelist&gt;
  &lt;varlistentry&gt;
    &lt;term&gt;Tag&lt;/term&gt;
    &lt;listitem&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;A piece of text enclosed in angle brackets&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;/varlistentry&gt;
  &lt;varlistentry&gt;
    &lt;term&gt;Element&lt;/term&gt;
    &lt;listitem&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;A start tag, a matching end tag, and everything in between&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;/varlistentry&gt;
  &lt;varlistentry&gt;
    &lt;term&gt;Content of an element&lt;/term&gt;
    &lt;listitem&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;Everything between the matching tags&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;/varlistentry&gt;
&lt;/variablelist&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>The list you are looking at right now, enumerating the
              different types of lists, is a <sgmltag
              class="element">variablelist</sgmltag>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Links</title>

        <para>You can create hyperlinks to targets in your own document, in
        another document in the set, or on the Internet.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">link</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para><sgmltag class="element">link</sgmltag> is the generic
              element to point to another location in the document or set. The
              <sgmltag class="attribute">linkend</sgmltag> attribute must
              always be present - its value should be the <sgmltag
              class="attribute">id</sgmltag> of the <firstterm>link
              target</firstterm> (the element to jump to).</para>

              <programlisting>Click &lt;link linkend="docwritehowto-introduction"&gt;here&lt;/link&gt; to jump to the 
introduction.</programlisting>

              <para>In the rendered document, the word "here" will be
              <firstterm>hot</firstterm>, that is: a clickable link pointing
              to the introduction.</para>

              <para>[Advanced stuff follows, feel free to skip it and jump
              right to the next element: <sgmltag
              class="element">xref</sgmltag>]</para>

              <para>There's also an empty-element version of <sgmltag
              class="element">link</sgmltag> (notice the
              <literal>/&gt;</literal> at the end):</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;link linkend="docwritehowto-introduction" endterm="docwritehowto-intro-title"/&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>This link points to the same location as the previous one,
              but now the hot text is determined automatically by the content
              of the element which has the id <sgmltag
              class="attvalue">docwritehowto-intro-title</sgmltag>. Why would
              we want to use this version? It's more work, because in cases
              like this we usually want the hot text to be the title of a
              chapter or section. This obliges us to give that title an id,
              which normally isn't necessary. But you reap the benefits when
              you - or someone else - later change the title of the targeted
              chapter: the hot text will automatically change with it, no
              action required on the maintainer's part. So yes, it's more work
              at first, but more powerful too, and less maintenance later. Of
              course this only goes for links where you want the hot text to
              be equal to the content of a certain (title) element.</para>

              <important>
                <para>Please understand that the hot text in the last example
                will not be "docwritehowto-intro-title", but the
                <emphasis>content</emphasis> of the
                <emphasis>element</emphasis> whose <emphasis>id</emphasis> is
                <sgmltag class="attvalue">docwritehowto-intro-title</sgmltag>.
                That's why you'll almost always use the id of a <sgmltag
                class="element">title</sgmltag> element here: if you'd specify
                a chapter's id, the entire content of that chapter would be
                copied into the hot text. Probably not what you want...</para>
              </important>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">xref</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>An <sgmltag class="element">xref</sgmltag> is an empty
              element that you can use much like a <sgmltag
              class="element">link</sgmltag>. Here too, the linkend attribute
              is required to specify the target. In its most basic form, an
              xref looks like this:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;xref linkend="docwritehowto-introduction"/&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>The hot text is determined automatically by the processing
              software. Unfortunately, with our current build process this
              means that some awkward-looking text like "<literal>Section ,
              How I killed my grandmother</literal>" is generated, which is
              not exactly ideal.</para>

              <para>There are two ways to make the situation better. First,
              you can keep the <sgmltag class="element">xref</sgmltag> like in
              the example above and give the <emphasis>target
              element</emphasis> an <sgmltag
              class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> attribute:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;chapter id="docwritehowto-introduction" xreflabel="Intro"&gt; ... &lt;/chapter&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>The hot text will now be "<literal>Intro</literal>".
              Xreflabels can be useful if you have long titles and you want
              something shorter for link texts.</para>

              <para>Second [advanced, feel free etc.], you can specify an
              <sgmltag class="attribute">endterm</sgmltag> in the <sgmltag
              class="starttag">xref</sgmltag> tag, just as with the empty
              <sgmltag class="element">link</sgmltag> element discussed
              above:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;xref linkend="docwritehowto-introduction" endterm="docwritehowto-intro-title"/&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>Indeed this looks and works exactly as the empty-element
              version of <sgmltag class="element">link</sgmltag> - except that
              it now says xref instead of link. If an endterm is present it
              will always be used to determine the hot text, even if the
              target has an xreflabel.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">ulink</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use a <sgmltag class="element">ulink</sgmltag> to link to
              an Internet resource. The <sgmltag
              class="attribute">url</sgmltag> attribute is mandatory:</para>

              <programlisting>Click &lt;ulink url="http://docbook.org/tdg/en/"&gt;this link&lt;/ulink&gt; to read The
Definitive Guide.</programlisting>

              <para>This makes the words "<literal>this link</literal>" a
              hyperlink pointing to the URL
              <literal>http://docbook.org/tdg/en/</literal></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">email</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>You can make an email link with a <sgmltag
              class="element">ulink</sgmltag>, but it's easier to use the
              <sgmltag class="element">email</sgmltag> element. This will show
              the email address as a clickable link in the output. This line
              of XML:</para>

              <programlisting>Send mail to &lt;email&gt;firebird-docs-request@lists.sourceforge.net&lt;/email&gt; to
subscribe.</programlisting>

              <para>results in the following output: "Send mail to
              <email>firebird-docs-request@lists.sourceforge.net</email> to
              subscribe."</para>

              <para>If you want the hot text to be different from the email
              address itself, use a <sgmltag class="element">ulink</sgmltag>
              with a <literal>mailto:</literal> URL.</para>

              <warning>
                <para>If you include links to email addresses - whether with
                <sgmltag class="element">email</sgmltag> or with <sgmltag
                class="element">ulink</sgmltag> - or even if you only
                <emphasis>mention</emphasis> them in your text, and your
                document is subsequently published on the Internet, these
                email addresses will be exposed to harvesting robots used by
                spammers. This will likely increase the amount of spam sent to
                such addresses. Always make sure the owner of the address
                agrees with having it published on the Internet!</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">anchor</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>An <sgmltag class="element">anchor</sgmltag> is an empty
              element marking an exact spot in the document. It doesn't show
              up in the text that your readers see, but it can be used as a
              link target. This is useful if you want to link to a place
              somewhere in the middle of a long paragraph:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;para id="lost-at-sea"&gt;
  Blah blah blah...
  and some more...
  and then some...
  Now here's an interesting place in the paragraph I want to be able to link to:
  &lt;anchor id="captain-haddock"/&gt;There it is!
  Paragraph drones on...
  and on...
  and on...
&lt;/para&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>Having placed the anchor, you can create a link to
              it:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;link linkend="captain-haddock"&gt;Go to the interesting spot&lt;/link&gt; in that long,
long paragraph.</programlisting>

              <para>If you link to a short element, or to the beginning of an
              element, it's easier to give the element itself an id and use
              that as linkend.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Program listings, screens, literal layout, and examples</title>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">programlisting</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If you include code fragments in your doc, put them in a
              <sgmltag class="element">programlisting</sgmltag> element.
              Everything you type within a programlisting will be rendered
              verbatim, including line breaks, spaces etc. Also, a fixed-with
              font will be used in the rendered documents. The term
              <quote>program listing</quote> is to be interpreted loosely
              here: you should also use this element for SQL fragments and
              DocBook XML examples. This Howto - and especially the section
              about elements, which you are reading now - is littered with
              <sgmltag class="element">programlisting</sgmltag>'s, so you
              already know what they look like.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">screen</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use a <sgmltag class="element">screen</sgmltag> element to
              show what a user sees or might see on a computer screen in text
              mode, or in a terminal window. Here too, your layout will be
              preserved and a fixed-width font used, but the semantics are
              different. It may or may not look different from a
              programlisting in the output. Here's a short example, showing
              what happens if you try to build a non-existing target in the
              manual tree:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;screen&gt;
D:\Firebird\manual_incl_howto\src\build&gt;build ugh
java version "1.4.2_01"
Java(TM) 2 Runtime Environment, Standard Edition (build 1.4.2_01-b06)
Java HotSpot(TM) Client VM (build 1.4.2_01-b06, mixed mode)

Buildfile: build.xml

BUILD FAILED
Target `ugh' does not exist in this project.
&lt;/screen&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>And this is how it's rendered:</para>

              <screen>D:\Firebird\manual_incl_howto\src\build&gt;build ugh
java version "1.4.2_01"
Java(TM) 2 Runtime Environment, Standard Edition (build 1.4.2_01-b06)
Java HotSpot(TM) Client VM (build 1.4.2_01-b06, mixed mode)

Buildfile: build.xml

BUILD FAILED
Target `ugh' does not exist in this project.</screen>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">literallayout</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para><sgmltag class="element">literallayout</sgmltag>, like
              <sgmltag class="element">screen</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
              class="element">programlisting</sgmltag>, keeps your layout
              intact, but it usually doesn't change the font − unless you set
              the <sgmltag class="attribute">class</sgmltag> attribute to
              <sgmltag class="attvalue">monospaced</sgmltag>. It's also more
              general than the previous two in the sense that there's no
              meaning attached to its content: you can put any kind of text
              here of which you want to preserve the layout.</para>

              <para>Example source:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;literallayout&gt;
The Sick Rose

Oh Rose, thou art sick!
The invisible worm
That flies in the night,
In the howling storm,

Has found out thy bed
Of crimson joy,
And his dark secret love
Doth thy life destroy.

  -- William Blake
&lt;/literallayout&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>Output:</para>

              <literallayout>The Sick Rose

Oh Rose, thou art sick!
The invisible worm
That flies in the night,
In the howling storm,

Has found out thy bed
Of crimson joy,
And his dark secret love
Doth thy life destroy.

  -- William Blake</literallayout>

              <note>
                <para>In previous versions of this Howto, you were warned not
                to use non-monospaced <sgmltag
                class="element">literallayout</sgmltag> because it looked
                horrible in the PDF output. But this problem has since been
                solved, as you can see in the PDF.</para>
              </note>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">example</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>An <sgmltag class="element">example</sgmltag> is a formal
              example with a title. It is usually given an <sgmltag
              class="attribute">id</sgmltag> so it can be referred to from
              other places in the document. An index of examples is built
              automatically when the document is rendered. You'll often find
              <sgmltag class="element">programlisting</sgmltag>'s in an
              <sgmltag class="element">example</sgmltag>, but it may also
              contain <sgmltag class="element">screen</sgmltag>'s, <sgmltag
              class="element">para</sgmltag>'s, lists, etc.</para>

              <para>Here's an example of an <sgmltag
              class="element">example</sgmltag>:</para>

              <programlisting>&lt;example id="docwritehowto-sql-example"&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;An SQL example&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;para&gt;With this command you can list all the records in the COUNTRY 
    table:&lt;/para&gt;
  &lt;programlisting&gt;SELECT * FROM COUNTRY;&lt;/programlisting&gt;
&lt;/example&gt;</programlisting>

              <para>In the output this will look like:</para>

              <example id="docwritehowto-sql-example">
                <title>An SQL example</title>

                <para>With this command you can list all the records in the
                COUNTRY table:</para>

                <programlisting>SELECT * FROM COUNTRY;</programlisting>
              </example>

              <para>If you want an example without a mandatory title, use an
              <sgmltag class="element">informalexample</sgmltag>. Informal
              examples are also left out of the examples index</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Tables</title>

        <para>If you have ever made an HTML table for a website, you won't
        have much difficulty creating tables in DocBook. There are differences
        though, and DocBook tables are vastly richer.</para>

        <para>A <sgmltag class="starttag">table</sgmltag> consists of a
        <sgmltag class="starttag">title</sgmltag> and one or more <sgmltag
        class="starttag">tgroup</sgmltag>'s - usually one. The <sgmltag
        class="starttag">tgroup</sgmltag> element has one mandatory attribute:
        <sgmltag class="attribute">cols</sgmltag>. You must set this attribute
        to the number of columns in the <sgmltag
        class="starttag">tgroup</sgmltag>. Within a <sgmltag
        class="starttag">tgroup</sgmltag> you can place <sgmltag
        class="starttag">thead</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
        class="starttag">tfoot</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
        class="starttag">tbody</sgmltag> elements. Each of these has one or
        more <sgmltag class="starttag">row</sgmltag>'s, which in turn have as
        many <sgmltag class="starttag">entry</sgmltag>'s (cells) as you have
        specified in the <sgmltag class="attribute">cols</sgmltag> attribute.
        (You can combine cells by creating spans, but we won't go into that
        here.)</para>

        <para>So much for the basic structure. Now we'll show you an example;
        first in DocBook XML source text, and then the resulting table in the
        rendered output document. Don't worry about the <sgmltag
        class="starttag">colspec</sgmltag>'s for now; these are non-mandatory
        subelements used for finetuning.</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;table id="docwritehowto-table-dboftheyear"&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;LinuxQuestions.org poll: Database of the year 2003&lt;/title&gt;

  &lt;tgroup cols="3"&gt;
    &lt;colspec align="left" colname="col-dbname" colwidth="2*"/&gt;
    &lt;colspec align="right" colname="col-votes" colwidth="1*"/&gt;
    &lt;colspec align="right" colname="col-perc" colwidth="1*"/&gt;

    &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;entry align="center"&gt;Database&lt;/entry&gt;
        &lt;entry align="center"&gt;Votes&lt;/entry&gt;
        &lt;entry align="center"&gt;Percentage&lt;/entry&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;

    &lt;tfoot&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;Total&lt;/entry&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;1111&lt;/entry&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;99.99&lt;/entry&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/tfoot&gt;

    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;MySQL&lt;/entry&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;405&lt;/entry&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;36.45&lt;/entry&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;Firebird&lt;/entry&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;403&lt;/entry&gt;
        &lt;entry&gt;36.27&lt;/entry&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;

      ... 5 more rows not shown here ....

    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/tgroup&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>And here's the resulting table:</para>

        <table id="docwritehowto-table-dboftheyear">
          <title>LinuxQuestions.org poll: Database of the year 2003</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec align="left" colname="col-dbname" colwidth="2*" />

            <colspec align="right" colname="col-votes" colwidth="1*" />

            <colspec align="right" colname="col-perc" colwidth="1*" />

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Database</entry>

                <entry align="center">Votes</entry>

                <entry align="center">Percentage</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tfoot>
              <row>
                <entry>Total</entry>

                <entry>1111</entry>

                <entry>99.99</entry>
              </row>
            </tfoot>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>MySQL</entry>

                <entry>405</entry>

                <entry>36.45</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Firebird</entry>

                <entry>403</entry>

                <entry>36.27</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Postgres</entry>

                <entry>269</entry>

                <entry>24.21</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Oracle</entry>

                <entry>25</entry>

                <entry>2.25</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Berkeley DB</entry>

                <entry>4</entry>

                <entry>0.36</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Sybase</entry>

                <entry>3</entry>

                <entry>0.27</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>DB2</entry>

                <entry>2</entry>

                <entry>0.18</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>By the way, these are the actual results of a real poll at
        LinuxQuestions.org. As you can see, if only three more people had
        voted for Firebird we would have won. If you know who these three
        persons are, please report them to our Chief Inquisitor. He would like
        to have a little, er... <emphasis>talk</emphasis> with them :-)</para>

        <para>Tables are automatically indexed. An <sgmltag
        class="starttag">informaltable</sgmltag> has the same structure as a
        <sgmltag class="starttag">table</sgmltag> but doesn't require a title
        and is not included in the index. (This is exactly the same as with
        <sgmltag class="starttag">example</sgmltag>/<sgmltag
        class="starttag">informalexample</sgmltag>.) If you want to nest
        tables, either use a <sgmltag
        class="starttag">table</sgmltag>/<sgmltag
        class="starttag">informaltable</sgmltag> <emphasis>within</emphasis>
        an <sgmltag class="starttag">entry</sgmltag>, or an <sgmltag
        class="starttag">entrytbl</sgmltag> <emphasis>instead of</emphasis> an
        <sgmltag class="starttag">entry</sgmltag>.</para>

        <para>Tables have many more features than shown here, but we'll leave
        those for you to explore.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Admonitions</title>

        <para>DocBook has several tags to mark a block of text as a note, a
        warning, a tip, etc. In the output documents such blocks typically
        appear indented, and marked with an icon or a word to denote their
        purpose. These tags are, in alphabetical order:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <para><sgmltag class="starttag">caution</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
          class="starttag">important</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
          class="starttag">note</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
          class="starttag">tip</sgmltag>, and <sgmltag
          class="starttag">warning</sgmltag></para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>I will give you a <sgmltag class="starttag">tip</sgmltag> as an
        example; the others are used in exactly the same way:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;tip&gt;
  &lt;para&gt;
    If you insert a caution, important, note, tip, or warning element in your text, 
    don't start it with the word caution, important, note, tip, or warning, because
    these words are usually automatically generated by the rendering engine.
  &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;/tip&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>And this is the result:</para>

        <tip>
          <para>If you insert a <sgmltag class="starttag">caution</sgmltag>,
          <sgmltag class="starttag">important</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
          class="starttag">note</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
          class="starttag">tip</sgmltag>, or <sgmltag
          class="starttag">warning</sgmltag> element in your text, don't start
          it with the word <literal>caution</literal>,
          <literal>important</literal>, <literal>note</literal>,
          <literal>tip</literal>, or <literal>warning</literal>, because these
          words are usually automatically generated by the rendering
          engine.</para>
        </tip>

        <para>You may have noticed that the words <literal>caution</literal>,
        <literal>important</literal> etc. look different from the rest of the
        tip's text. How come? Well, to tell you the truth, I've surrounded
        them with special tags (first with <sgmltag
        class="starttag">sgmltag</sgmltag>'s, the second time with <sgmltag
        class="starttag">literal</sgmltag>'s) to make them look like that. But
        this made the source XML look very noisy, so I decided to remove those
        tags from the example source I presented to you.</para>

        <para>If you want to set off a block of text from its surroundings
        without marking it as a tip or whatever, use a <sgmltag
        class="starttag">blockquote</sgmltag>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Various inline elements</title>

        <para>To conclude the subsection on DocBook elements I will now
        briefly introduce a number of <firstterm>inline elements</firstterm>.
        They are called <quote>inline</quote> because they don't interrupt the
        flow of the text. If I use e.g. an <sgmltag
        class="element">emphasis</sgmltag> element:</para>

        <programlisting>Don't &lt;emphasis&gt;ever&lt;/emphasis&gt; call me fat again!</programlisting>

        <para>the result is this:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <para>Don't <emphasis>ever</emphasis> call me fat again!</para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>The word <quote>ever</quote> is emphasized, but it keeps its
        place in the sentence. We've already encountered some inline elements
        before: the various link types. Other elements - like <sgmltag
        class="element">table</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
        class="element">warning</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
        class="element">blockquote</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
        class="element">programlisting</sgmltag> - are always displayed as a
        block, set apart from the surrounding text (even if you
        <quote>inline</quote> them in your XML source). Not surprisingly,
        these are called <firstterm>block elements</firstterm>. Block elements
        often contain inline elements; the reverse is not possible.</para>

        <para>OK, let's get started with those inline elements. I'll include
        examples - both XML source and rendered output - for most of
        them:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">filename</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">command</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">application</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">envar</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use the <sgmltag class="element">filename</sgmltag> tag to
              mark file names in the broadest sense. Attributes can optionally
              indicate that the file is a header file, a directory,
              etc.</para>

              <programlisting>Place your doc in the
&lt;filename class="directory"&gt;src/docs/firebirddocs&lt;/filename&gt; subdirectory.</programlisting>

              <para>The output reads: Place your doc in the <filename
              class="directory">src\docs\firebirddocs</filename>
              subdirectory.</para>

              <para><sgmltag class="element">command</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
              class="element">application</sgmltag> are both used for
              executable programs. <sgmltag class="element">command</sgmltag>
              is usually chosen for smaller programs and internal commands;
              its content should be the exact command as given on a command
              line; <sgmltag class="element">application</sgmltag> is
              generally used for bigger programs and need not be the name of
              the executable file. Both can refer to the same program:</para>

              <programlisting>Type &lt;command&gt;netscape&amp;amp;&lt;/command&gt; in a terminal window to start 
&lt;application&gt;Netscape Navigator&lt;/application&gt;.</programlisting>

              <para>This is rendered as: Type <command>netscape&amp;</command>
              in a terminal window to start <application>Netscape
              Navigator</application>.</para>

              <para><sgmltag class="element">envar</sgmltag> denotes an
              environment variable.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">subscript</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">superscript</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Do the expected thing:</para>

              <programlisting>After inventing the formula e = mc&lt;superscript&gt;2&lt;/superscript&gt;, I really felt
like a glass of liquid H&lt;subscript&gt;2&lt;/subscript&gt;O !</programlisting>

              <para><emphasis>Output:</emphasis> After inventing the formula e
              = mc<superscript>2</superscript>, I really felt like a glass of
              liquid H<subscript>2</subscript>O !</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">varname</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">constant</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">database</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The use of <sgmltag class="element">varname</sgmltag> and
              <sgmltag class="element">constant</sgmltag> should be obvious.
              The <sgmltag class="starttag">database</sgmltag> tag is not only
              meant for databases, but also for database objects:</para>

              <programlisting>The &lt;database class="table"&gt;COUNTRY&lt;/database&gt; table has two fields:
&lt;database class="field"&gt;COUNTRY&lt;/database&gt; and
&lt;database class="field"&gt;CURRENCY&lt;/database&gt;.</programlisting>

              <para><emphasis>Output:</emphasis> The <database
              class="table">COUNTRY</database> table has two fields: <database
              class="field">COUNTRY</database> and <database
              class="field">CURRENCY</database>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">function</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">parameter</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">returnvalue</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>These three speak for themselves, I trust.</para>

              <programlisting>The &lt;function&gt;log&lt;/function&gt; function takes parameters &lt;parameter&gt;a&lt;/parameter&gt;
and &lt;parameter&gt;b&lt;/parameter&gt;.</programlisting>

              <para><emphasis>Output:</emphasis> The <function>log</function>
              function takes parameters <parameter>a</parameter> and
              <parameter>b</parameter>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">prompt</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">userinput</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">computeroutput</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para><sgmltag class="element">prompt</sgmltag> is used for a
              string inciting the user to enter some text; <sgmltag
              class="element">userinput</sgmltag> refers to text entered by
              the user (not necessarily at a prompt!); <sgmltag
              class="element">computeroutput</sgmltag> is text displayed by
              the computer:</para>

              <programlisting>Type &lt;userinput&gt;guest&lt;/userinput&gt; at the &lt;prompt&gt;login:&lt;/prompt&gt; prompt and the
server will greet you with a &lt;computeroutput&gt;Welcome, guest user&lt;/computeroutput&gt;.</programlisting>

              <para><emphasis>Output:</emphasis> Type
              <userinput>guest</userinput> at the <prompt>login:</prompt>
              prompt and the server will greet you with a
              <computeroutput>Welcome, guest user</computeroutput>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">keycap</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The text on a keyboard key, or its common name:</para>

              <programlisting>Hit the &lt;keycap&gt;Del&lt;/keycap&gt; key to erase the message, or &lt;keycap&gt;SPACE&lt;/keycap&gt;
to move on.</programlisting>

              <para><emphasis>Output:</emphasis> Hit the <keycap>Del</keycap>
              key to erase the message, or <keycap>SPACE</keycap> to move
              on.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">sgmltag</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This element is used extensively throughout this Howto: it
              marks SGML <emphasis>and</emphasis> XML tags, elements,
              attributes, entities etc.:</para>

              <programlisting>If it concerns a directory, set the &lt;sgmltag class="attribute"&gt;class&lt;/sgmltag&gt;
attribute of the &lt;sgmltag class="element"&gt;filename&lt;/sgmltag&gt; element to
&lt;sgmltag class="attvalue"&gt;directory&lt;/sgmltag&gt;.</programlisting>

              <para><emphasis>Output:</emphasis> If it concerns a directory,
              set the <sgmltag class="attribute">class</sgmltag> attribute of
              the <sgmltag class="element">filename</sgmltag> element to
              <sgmltag class="attvalue">directory</sgmltag>.</para>

              <para>Other possible values for <sgmltag
              class="element">sgmltag</sgmltag>.<sgmltag
              class="attribute">class</sgmltag> are: <sgmltag
              class="attvalue">starttag</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
              class="attvalue">endtag</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
              class="attvalue">emptytag</sgmltag>, and <sgmltag
              class="attvalue">genentity</sgmltag> (for an entity).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">emphasis</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">citetitle</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">firstterm</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use <sgmltag class="element">emphasis</sgmltag> to stress
              words in general, <sgmltag class="element">citetitle</sgmltag>
              for book titles etc., and <sgmltag
              class="element">firstterm</sgmltag> if you introduce a new word
              or concept to your readers:</para>

              <programlisting>We use &lt;firstterm&gt;DocBook XML&lt;/firstterm&gt; for our Firebird documentation. A
short introduction follows; &lt;emphasis&gt;please&lt;/emphasis&gt; read it carefully! 
If you want to know more about the subject, buy &lt;citetitle&gt;DocBook - The 
Definitive Guide&lt;/citetitle&gt;.</programlisting>

              <para><emphasis>Output:</emphasis> We use <firstterm>DocBook
              XML</firstterm> for our Firebird documentation. A short
              introduction follows; <emphasis>please</emphasis> read it
              carefully! If you want to know more about the subject, buy
              <citetitle>DocBook - The Definitive Guide</citetitle>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="element">quote</sgmltag> - <sgmltag
            class="element">literal</sgmltag></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use <sgmltag class="element">quote</sgmltag> for an inline
              qutation (as opposed to a <sgmltag
              class="element">blockquote</sgmltag>). Quote characters will be
              inserted automatically. Using <sgmltag
              class="element">quote</sgmltag> instead of typing the quote
              characters yourself (which is also perfectly legal) has the
              advantage that we can alter the type of quotation marks through
              stylesheets if we want to.</para>

              <para>A <sgmltag class="element">literal</sgmltag> is a word or
              text fragment to be taken literally. It is a rather general
              element, often used to make certain words stand out
              typographically:</para>

              <programlisting>At all costs avoid using the word &lt;literal&gt;humongous&lt;/literal&gt; in your
documentation.</programlisting>

              <para><emphasis>Output:</emphasis> At all costs avoid using the
              word <literal>humongous</literal> in your documentation.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>Should you always use these inline elements wherever you can?
        Well, if you do, you will certainly make your document richer; you'll
        make it easier to scan for filenames for instance, or to generate an
        index of all the applications mentioned in your document. On the other
        hand, there are so many of these semantic elements (in fact we've only
        discussed a <emphasis>few</emphasis> here) that if you apply them
        everywhere you can, you'll probably wind up in a straightjacket before
        you can finish your doc. This is not what we want of course: if you
        really have to go mad, please do so <emphasis>after</emphasis> you've
        committed your document :-)</para>

        <para>So, as a general advice: go a bit easy on those inlines; use
        them wherever you think it makes sense, but don't overdo it.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>To wrap up the elements</title>

        <para>You may have noticed that in the rendered documents (you're
        reading one now, unless you opened the XML version) many different
        elements have the same appearance: a <sgmltag
        class="element">filename</sgmltag>, a <sgmltag
        class="element">literal</sgmltag> and an <sgmltag
        class="element">application</sgmltag> may have the exact same
        typography; the same goes for <sgmltag
        class="element">emphasis</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
        class="element">firstterm</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
        class="element">citetitle</sgmltag>.</para>

        <para>So what's the point of all these different tags? Why not use
        just a few, like <sgmltag class="element">emphasis</sgmltag> and
        <sgmltag class="element">literal</sgmltag>, if they're going to look
        the same anyway? Well, there are two very good reasons not to:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>First, if we dropped most of our inlines in favor of say,
            <sgmltag class="element">emphasis</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
            class="element">literal</sgmltag>, the semantics would be lost.
            Remember that DocBook XML is all about structure and semantics.
            <sgmltag class="element">firstterm</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
            class="element">citetitle</sgmltag> may <emphasis>look</emphasis>
            the same as <sgmltag class="element">emphasis</sgmltag> once
            rendered, but they <emphasis>are</emphasis> not the same thing.
            The XML source knows that, even if it doesn't always show. This
            information is useful, and we don't want to lose it.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Further, we can adapt our stylesheets for each type of
            element individually. As soon as we decide that a <sgmltag
            class="element">firstterm</sgmltag> should look different from a
            <sgmltag class="element">citetitle</sgmltag>, we can arrange for
            that - but <emphasis>only</emphasis> if they are indeed marked
            with different tags, not if they are both <sgmltag
            class="element">emphasis</sgmltag>'s in the XML source.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>This concludes the sections on DocBook. With the knowledge
        presented above, you should now be able to author DocBook XML
        documents for the Firebird project. Of course if you use a dedicated
        XML editor - which, again, is highly advisable - you must also consult
        its documentation to learn how to use it; that's one thing this Howto
        doesn't cover.</para>

        <anchor id="docwritehowto-elements-end" />
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-other-writing-aspects">
    <title>Non-DocBook aspects of the writing process</title>

    <para>After the flood of DocBook information in the previous sections, we
    now briefly discuss some other important docwriting aspects: language,
    style, and copyrights.</para>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-language-style">
      <title>Language and style</title>

      <sect3 id="docwritehowto-language">
        <title>Language</title>

        <para>The Firebird community is a very diverse one, and made up of
        people with many different mother tongues. If you write your
        documentation in a language other than your own, you'll probably make
        some mistakes. This is not catastrophical, but you should at least try
        to reduce the number of errors. Some strategies to help you with this
        are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use a dictionary! Simple, effective, and blissfully
            non-hightech.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>When hesitating between two spellings of a word, or between
            several possible versions of an expression, google for the
            alternatives and look at their frequencies. Also follow some of
            the result links to see how native speakers use the word or
            expression in their texts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Have a native speaker look over your text and correct it
            where necessary.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="docwritehowto-style">
        <title>Style</title>

        <para>Don't expect a Style Guide here - I wouldn't know how to write
        one anyway. Just some guidelines and tips:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Try to write in plain, everyday language wherever possible.
            Avoid difficult words if there's a familiar, simple
            alternative.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Avoid long sentences (over 25 words) if you can; especially
            avoid two or more long sentences immediately after each
            other.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Be careful with constructs like double or triple negatives
            (<quote>I can't deny that I'm not displeased</quote>) and passive
            voice (<quote>Care should be taken...</quote>). You don't have to
            avoid them at all costs, but they can make a sentence harder to
            understand. If so, use the positive (<quote>I am pleased</quote>)
            and the active voice (<quote>Take care...</quote>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use lists to enumerate a number of parallel items, for
            instance:</para>

            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                <para>A collection of hints and tips.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>A sequence of examples (like this one).</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Steps to be followed in a procedure.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Alternative solutions to a problem.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>But if there's only a small number of short items, use a
            plain sentence instead: <quote>My mother loves three men: John,
            Dick, and Dave.</quote></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Don't overuse exclamation marks. Never use multiple
            exclamation marks or question marks. This is annoying!!!!! Or
            don't you think so???</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <sect4>
          <title>Docwriter's block</title>

          <para>Sometimes you know what you want to write, and you have all
          the words ready, but you can't get the sentence started - you just
          don't get it to <emphasis>flow</emphasis>. This is very frustrating
          and it can sometimes block the advance of your text for many
          minutes. And it's all the more frustrating because you
          <emphasis>do</emphasis> know what you want to tell your readers, but
          you don't seem to be able to produce a decent sentence. After many
          painful experiences of this kind, I've developed the following
          strategy (not that I think I'm the first):</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Write down what you have to say in loose sentences and
              chunks of words. Never mind about style, never mind if it looks
              ugly. Just write down what you want to tell the reader; make
              sure it's all there, and in the right order. If, while doing
              this, you notice that you feel unsure about something, include a
              remark at exactly that point. Make your remarks stand out from
              the surrounding text, &lt;&lt;e.g. like this&gt;&gt; or !LIKE
              THAT!</para>

              <para>This may result in a text like:</para>

              <blockquote>
                <para>CVS means Concurrent Versions System
                (&lt;&lt;check!&gt;&gt;). Purpose: managing versions of
                software. You can use it alone or with a group. You need a CVS
                client to use it. A CVS client is a program with which you can
                access a CVS repository (&lt;&lt;explain this term?&gt;&gt;).
                To find out if a CVS client is installed on your system, type
                <quote>cvs</quote> on the command line. If it's not there, go
                to this URL to download it.... [etc., etc.]</para>
              </blockquote>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If you have included any remarks, handle them first.
              <emphasis>Check</emphasis> if CVS really means Concurrent
              Versions System (it does). <emphasis>Decide</emphasis> whether
              you should really explain the term <quote>CVS repository</quote>
              at this point (you should).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Now, go over the paragraph again and try to make the text
              flow more naturally wherever you can. Chances are that this will
              be a lot easier than you expected!</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If it still looks a little clumsy, never mind - better
              clumsy and clear than smooth-flowing and fuzzy. Maybe you can
              revisit this passage later and see if you can nice it up some
              more.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

          <para>This approach works well for me. So if you're stuck in this
          way, try it out; hopefully it will help you too.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-copyrights">
      <title>Copyrights</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Copyrights of others</title>

        <para>As we write our manuals, we can consult all kinds of other
        documentation - and so we should, because we want to achieve the best
        possible result. Any information we find in publicly available
        third-party manuals, user's guides, tutorials etc. can be freely used
        in our own docs, but it is important not to confuse
        <emphasis>information</emphasis> with <emphasis>literal
        text</emphasis>. We cannot copy-and-paste text from other works into
        our own documentation, unless the author explicitly permits us to do
        so. Check the copyright notice of the work in question; if there isn't
        one, the work is automatically copyrighted under the Berne convention
        and you must assume that it's illegal to copy it - even partially.
        This is also the case if the work is freely available! Not having to
        pay for a document does not imply that you can freely copy portions of
        text and republish them in a work of your own.</para>

        <para>More specifically, the Borland InterBase 6 beta docs - although
        free - are not part of the InterBase package that was open-sourced in
        July 2000. We have asked Borland several times if we could use these
        docs <quote>as if they fell under the InterBase Public
        License</quote>, but they didn't even bother to answer. So feel free
        to use this documentation set as a source of information, but don't
        copy text from it.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Your copyright</title>

        <para>If you contribute to the Firebird documention subproject, your
        work will become part of an open-source repository. This means that
        everybody can consult and download it in source form (i.e. as DocBook
        XML files), but not only that: everybody can also legally alter,
        re-use, republish, sell and/or give away your work, or works derived
        from it, albeit under certain conditions. It is important that you
        realize this before you commit anything to the project! The Firebird
        project as a whole is covered by the Mozilla Public License; as far as
        I understand you can apply another Open Source license to your own
        contributions, but I'm not sure if you may choose a license that's
        more restrictive than the overall project license. If you want to know
        more about this, and about the conditions SourceForge imposes upon
        projects they host, consult the <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/docman/display_doc.php?docid=778&amp;group_id=1">SourceForge
        documentation pages</ulink> on the subject. And please let me know if
        you find anything that contradicts what I wrote here :-)</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-postgresql">
      <title>Using PostgreSQL docs</title>

      <para>PostgreSQL is another major open source database, with (surprise,
      surprise) many similarities to Firebird, but also many differences.
      Depending on the kind of documentation you are going to write, it may be
      beneficial to base it on existing PostgreSQL docs. Be aware though that
      if you use PostgreSQL material, you MUST include their copyright notice
      in your document!</para>

      <para>The PostgreSQL documentation homepage is here:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/">http://www.postgresql.org/docs/</ulink></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>The most recent PostgreSQL license is at:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.postgresql.org/licence.html">http://www.postgresql.org/licence.html</ulink></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>One nice thing about the PostgreSQL docs is that they are authored
      in DocBook, just like ours. However, they use DocBook SGML instead of
      XML, so some tweaking may be necessary. The DocBook SGML sources can be
      found here:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://developer.postgresql.org/cvsweb.cgi/pgsql-server/doc/src/sgml/">http://developer.postgresql.org/cvsweb.cgi/pgsql-server/doc/src/sgml/</ulink></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>Or check out the entire CVS tree, docs and all. For instructions,
      go to:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://developer.postgresql.org/docs/postgres/cvs.html">http://developer.postgresql.org/docs/postgres/cvs.html</ulink></para>
      </blockquote>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="docwritehowto-add-to-module">
    <title>Adding your document to the manual module</title>

    <para>When your doc is finished, and you have verified that it builds
    correctly, you want it added to the manual module. If this is your first
    contribution to the documentation project you'll probably have agreed with
    the coordinators that you first submit it to them for review, or that you
    temporarily put up the HTML version on a website so that it can be
    discussed on the list. After that - and maybe after some corrections are
    made - the document can be committed to the module. If you have commit
    rights you can do this yourself; if not, one of the coordinators will do
    it for you.</para>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-ask-commit-rights">
      <title>Asking for commit rights</title>

      <para>To receive commit rights you first need a SourceForge user
      account. If you haven't got one, register at <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/account/register.php">http://sourceforge.net/account/register.php</ulink>.
      Then post a message to the firebird-docs mailing list stating your SF
      user name and asking to be added to the Firebird project. The manual
      subproject leader and several Firebird project admins follow the list;
      they will consider your request. As a general rule you should ask for
      commit rights <emphasis>after</emphasis> your first contribution,
      because the people who decide on your request need something to go
      by.</para>

      <para>The following phrases currently all mean the same, by the
      way:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Being a project member.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Having commit rights.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Having read-write access to the repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-commit-dos-donts">
      <title>Dos and don'ts if you have received commit rights</title>

      <para>Once you are accepted as a project member, you have write access
      to the entire Firebird repository, not only to the manual module. There
      is no technical barrier to keep you from committing changes to other
      modules - the <literal>firebird2</literal> core module for instance, or
      even the <literal>CVSROOT</literal> module where important project
      information is stored.</para>

      <para>You may already have guessed that this is <emphasis>NOT</emphasis>
      the idea. Keep to the following rules:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Don't <emphasis>ever</emphasis> commit to other modules unless
          the people in charge of those modules explicitly ask you to do
          so.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Only commit work to the manual module if it concerns a task
          assigned to you. Even then, it's good practice to announce your
          changes and additions on the mailing list first, so the other
          doccers have a chance to comment on it. After all, this is a
          collective effort.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you think a new document or directory should be added,
          don't just create and commit it, but propose it on the list.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In practice, things may be a bit more relaxed than stated here,
      especially where it concerns your own tasks. We don't want you to feel
      unfree and you certainly shouldn't get the feeling that you have to ask
      permission for every minor change you make. But we do want you to act
      responsibly, and we want to know from each other what we are doing.
      Besides, keeping in touch with each other is often inspirational.
      Together we can make this thing work!</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="docwritehowto-commit-work">
      <title>Committing your work</title>

      <para>Even if you are a project member, you can only commit changes from
      a local copy if it was checked out with your SF login name. If you're
      still working with a copy you've checked out anonymously you must first
      make a fresh SSH checkout, and then re-apply your changes and commit
      them. Refer to the <link
      linkend="docbuildhowto-ssh-checkout">Docbuilding Howto</link> if you
      don't remember how to perform an SSH checkout.</para>

      <para>If some time has passed since your last checkout or update,
      perform an update before committing. This will get your local copy in
      sync with the repository and reduce the possibility of conflicts.</para>

      <para>Once you are ready to commit, go to the manual directory. If you
      use command-line CVS, type:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para><command>cvs update -d</command> [ only if you want to update
        first ]</para>

        <para><command>cvs commit -m "Short informational message
        here"</command></para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>After the <literal>-m</literal>, and within quotes, you type a
      short message about this commit, e.g. <literal>"Added new functions to
      API Reference"</literal> or <literal>"Errors in isql tutorial
      fixed"</literal>.</para>

      <para>Give your SF password when prompted, and all the changes you have
      made - including those in subdirectories - will be committed. Your CVS
      client knows which server to contact; this and other information is
      stored in the <filename class="directory">CVS</filename> subdirectories
      that were created upon checkout.</para>

      <para>If you use another CVS client, refer to its documentation.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>