<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../tools/docbook-dtd/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="fbvpn">
    <title>Firebird VPN Docwriter's Guide</title>

    <titleabbrev>Obtaining And Installing VPN Software</titleabbrev>

    <articleinfo>
        <date>30 March 2010</date>

        <author>
            <firstname>Norman</firstname>

            <surname>Dunbar</surname>
        </author>

        <edition>30 March 2010 Document version 1.0</edition>
    </articleinfo>

    <section id="fbvpn-vpn">
        <title>Obtaining And Installing VPN</title>

        <section id="fbvpn-introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>

            <para>In order that doc writers can upload finished documents, a VPN system is
            now required where previously, secure FTP was all that was needed. This
            document gives details on obtaining the software, installing it and testing
            that it works.</para>

            <para>Instructions on how to upload actual documents are given elsewhere in
            the Docwriters' manuals.</para>

            <para>Windows users can download a preconfigured installation package which
            will install and configure the <application>openVPN</application> software
            ready for use.</para>

            <para>Linux users need to have installed <application>openVPN</application>
            and then use a simple configuration file to allow connections to the Firebird
            network. This configuration file is all that Linux users need to
            download.</para>

            <para>The details of the server's IP address, logon and password will be given
            in an email when you apply for upload privileges. Please note that the details
            given are specific to you and you alone - no-one else can use your
            credentials.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="fbvpn-download">
            <title>Initial Download</title>

            <para>Regardless of whether you use Windows or Linux, you first need to
            connect to the server using the credentials supplied in the email that you
            received when you applied for upload privileges.</para>

            <para>Once you have logged in with the given user name and password, you will
            see two files:</para>

            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para><filename>XXXX_Firebird_VPN_config.zip</filename></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><filename>XXXX_Firebird_VPN_setup.exe</filename></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The zip file is for Linux users only, the exe is for Windows users. The
            'XXXX' part of the filename varies and is customised specifically for your use
            only. The filename will normally start with your name - which may be
            incorrectly spelt, as mine was - don't worry if this is the case. The filename
            makes no difference to the contents.</para>

            <note>
                <para>Windows users must be running Windows XP, Windows 2000 - or a higher
                version of Windows.</para>
            </note>

            <para>The Windows file is about 2MB in size as it contains an installer as
            well as the various configuration files. The Linux file contains your own
            personal certificates but not an installer. It is correspondingly
            small!</para>
        </section>

        <section id="fbvpn-installation">
            <title>Installation</title>

            <para>The installation process is different for Linux users and Windows users.
            Please use the appropriate section below according to your own
            requirements.</para>

            <para>Once complete, the system will be configured to allow you to connect to
            the Firebird server which has a network address of 192.168.2.2. This does mean
            that if you are running on a network with the same address range, then you may
            not be able to connect if a device on your network has obtained or been
            configured with the 192.168.2.2 IP address.</para>

            <para>The quick solution is to configure your router to issue IP addresses
            that start above 192.168.2.2 - that way, you will not clash with any other
            equipment on your own network when you try to connect to Firebird's
            server.</para>

            <para>On my own network, for example, I have the router configured to issue
            addresses from 192.168.2.10 onwards and I reserve the addresses below that for
            anything I wish to give a permanent IP address - my printer, for example, is
            hard coded to 192.168.2.4. Luckily nothing is yet using 192.168.2.2.</para>

            <section id="fbvpn-install-windows">
                <title>Windows Installation</title>

                <para>Once you have obtained the setup file, as described above, you
                simply double-click it to start the installation process.</para>

                <para>You will, however, need to be using Windows XP, Windows 2000 or a
                higher version - Vista, Windows 7 Windows 2003 etc. OpenVPN cannot be used
                on any release of windows previous to XP or Windows 2000.</para>

                <note>
                    <para>You will also require local administrator privileges to be able
                    to set up some parts of the installation.</para>

                    <para>Right-click on the setup file and select <userinput>Run as
                    ...</userinput> then select administrator. You will be prompted for
                    the administrator password.</para>
                </note>

                <para>Once the installer is running, you will progress through a number of
                different installer pages by clicking the <userinput>next</userinput>
                button. The following is the process you should follow:</para>

                <procedure>
                    <step>
                        <para>On the <emphasis>Welcome</emphasis> page - click
                        <userinput>next</userinput>.</para>
                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>On the <emphasis>License</emphasis> page - click
                        <userinput>accept</userinput>. If you don't agree, exit from the
                        installer.</para>
                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>On the <emphasis>Choose Components</emphasis> page - all
                        options are selected by default and you should simply click
                        <userinput>next</userinput>.</para>
                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>On the <emphasis>Install Location</emphasis> page - choose a
                        location that you are happy with. The default will be <filename
                        class="directory">c:\program files\openVPN</filename> (or
                        <filename class="directory">c:\program files
                        (x86)\openVPN</filename> on Windows 7). Click
                        <userinput>install</userinput>.</para>

                        <para>During the installation, your firewall may prompt you about
                        the installer, if so, allow the installer internet access each
                        time. You may also be prompted by some of the components that the
                        installer is attempting to install. You should allow internet
                        access to those prompts as well.</para>

                        <para>Windows will also prompt you that the program running is not
                        a Windows Logo certified application. Click the <userinput>install
                        anyway</userinput> button to continue.</para>

                        <para>Under Windows 7, the prompt will be that Windows
                        <emphasis>cannot verify the publisher of this driver
                        software...</emphasis>, click <userinput>install driver software
                        anyway</userinput>.</para>
                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>On the <emphasis>Install Complete</emphasis> page - click
                        <userinput>Next</userinput>.</para>
                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>Finally, click <userinput>finish</userinput>.</para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>

                <para>The openVPN application is not running - if all went well with the
                installation - however, in future, to start it you should click
                <command>Start -&gt; All Programs -&gt; openVPN -&gt;
                openVPNGUI</command>.</para>

                <para>Once <application>openVPN</application> is running you will see a
                new icon in your system tray. When the icon is coloured red, you are
                disconnected, when green you are connected. Double clicking this icon will
                open the connection dialogue as will right-clicking on the icon, and
                choosing <userinput>Connect</userinput> from the menu.</para>

                <para>When you attempt to connect it is possible that your firewall will
                prompt for permission to allow <filename>openvpn.exe</filename> to access
                the internet. You should allow this to connect and if possible, tell the
                firewall to always allow <filename>openvpn.exe</filename> permission to
                connect to the internet.</para>

                <para>To disconnect <application>openVPN</application> from the internet,
                double-click on the green <application>openVPN</application> icon, or,
                right-click it and select <userinput>disconnect</userinput>.</para>

                <para>You are now ready to test the installation. Make sure that
                <application>openVPN</application> is currently running.</para>
            </section>

            <section id="fbvpn-install-linux">
                <title>Linux Installation</title>

                <para>Open a terminal session and, as your own user, type in the command
                <command>whereis openvpn</command>. The response will look similar to the
                following if the <application>openVPN</application> software is already
                installed:</para>

                <screen>$ whereis openvpn
openvpn: /usr/sbin/openvpn /etc/openvpn.conf &lt;other stuff&gt;</screen>

                <para>And, if not, the result will be as follows:</para>

                <screen>$ whereis openvpn
openvpn:</screen>

                <para>If you see that the software is installed already, you can skip over
                the following sections and go directly to the section on</para>

                <section id="fbvpn-install-ubuntu">
                    <title>Ubuntu, Linux Mint etc</title>

                    <para>For Ubuntu and derivatives, the process to install
                    <application>openVPN</application> is as follows:</para>

                    <procedure>
                        <step>
                            <para>Click <command>System -&gt; Administration -&gt;
                            Synaptic Package Manager</command> if you are on Ubuntu, or,
                            <command>Menu -&gt;Package Manager</command> if running Linux
                            Mint. This will start the software package manager.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Enter your own password when (or if) prompted to do
                            so.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>In the Quick Search edit box, type in
                            <userinput>openvpn</userinput> then click
                            <userinput>search</userinput>.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>In the list of packages that subsequently appears,
                            scroll down to the <emphasis>openvpn</emphasis> entry and
                            click on the check box at the start of the line.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>You are prompted to <userinput>Mark for
                            installation</userinput>. Do so.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Click <userinput>Mark</userinput> for the list of
                            packages that are also required when you see the dialogue
                            appear.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Click the <userinput>Apply</userinput> button.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Click <userinput>Apply</userinput> in the confirmation
                            dialogue.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Wait ...</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>When all is done, click
                            <userinput>close</userinput>.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>The list of packages will now show that
                            <application>openVPN</application> version
                            <emphasis>2.1~rc19-lubuntu2</emphasis> has been installed. (In
                            my case.) Obviously, this will differ as later versions of
                            <application>openVPN</application> are produced for Ubuntu
                            etc.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Close the package manager.</para>
                        </step>
                    </procedure>
                </section>

                <section id="fbvpn-install-opensuse">
                    <title>OpenSuse</title>

                    <para>For OpenSuse the process to install
                    <application>openVPN</application> is as follows:</para>

                    <procedure>
                        <step>
                            <para>Press the ALT and F2 keys together to obtain a
                            prompt.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Type in <userinput>yast</userinput> and press
                            Enter.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Enter the root password when prompted.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Click <emphasis>Software</emphasis> on the right.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Click <emphasis>Software Management</emphasis> on the
                            left.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>In the search box, type <userinput>openvpn</userinput>
                            and click the <userinput>search</userinput> button.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>When the list of related packages is displayed, scroll
                            down until you find the one named
                            <emphasis>openvpn</emphasis>.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Right click that entry, and select
                            <userinput>install</userinput> from the menu.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Click the <userinput>accept</userinput> button.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Follow the prompts to install the correct CD or DVD etc,
                            if necessary.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Close the software manager.</para>
                        </step>
                    </procedure>
                </section>

                <section id="fbvpn-linux-configure">
                    <title>Linux Configuration</title>

                    <para>Once you have installed the software, you are ready to configure
                    it. This is a simple process and involves nothing more difficult that
                    creating a directory and unzipping the zip file that you downloaded
                    earlier.</para>

                    <para>The process is as follows:</para>

                    <procedure>
                        <step>
                            <para>Change directory to a suitable location where you will
                            create the <application>openVPN</application> configuration
                            files.</para>

                            <screen>$ cd ~</screen>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Create a directory.</para>

                            <screen>$ mkdir -p Firebird/VPN</screen>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Copy the downloaded zip file into the new
                            directory.</para>

                            <screen>$ cd Firebird/VPN
$ cp &lt;dowload location&gt;/*_Firebird_VPN_config.zip ./</screen>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Extract the required files.</para>

                            <screen>$ unzip *.zip
...</screen>
                        </step>
                    </procedure>

                    <para>You now have all the files you need to run a VPN session
                    connecting to the Firebird network.</para>
                </section>

                <section>
                    <title>Starting OpenVPN</title>

                    <para><application>OpenVPN</application> doesn't run on startup on
                    Linux installations. You are required to start it yourself as and when
                    you need it. You need to start it as root as it dynamically creates a
                    file in the <filename class="directory">/dev</filename> directory. The
                    following command should be run from a bash session while logged in as
                    your own user. It will work perfectly well on Ubuntu or Linux Mint, or
                    other Linux installations, where a dedicated root session is not
                    available.</para>

                    <screen>$ cd ~Firebird/VPN
$ su -c "/usr/sbin/openvpn --config `pwd`/firebirdsql-project.ovpn"</screen>

                    <para>Alternatively, you can start <application>openVPN</application>
                    from wherever you happen to be, as follows:</para>

                    <screen>$ su -c "/usr/sbin/openvpn --config \
~/Firebird/VPN/untangle-vpn/firebirdsql-project.ovpn"</screen>

                    <para>Regardless of which command you use, you will be prompted for a
                    password. On Ubuntu type systems, the password is your own. If you are
                    running OpenSuse, it will require the root password.</para>

                    <para>At this point, the bash session will hang after displaying a lot
                    of text, finishing with the line:</para>

                    <screen>...
Initialisation Sequence Completed</screen>

                    <para>You are now running <application>openVPN</application> and have
                    created a tunnel to the Firebird network. You are ready to test the
                    system.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Testing</title>

            <para>To test your installation, use a command line version of FTP. This is
            quick and common to both Linux and Windows. The process is as follows:</para>

            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>FTP to the Firebird server:</para>

                    <screen>$ ftp 192.168.2.2
Username: &lt;as supplied&gt;
Password: &lt;as supplied&gt;
230 logon successful
Remote system type is UNIX
Using binary mode to transfer files
</screen>

                    <para>The connection process seems to take quite a while it is
                    certainly a low slower then the old server was. This may just be a
                    glitch in the system at present and will probably speed up in the near
                    future.</para>
                </step>

                <step>
                    <para>Change to the pdf directory:</para>

                    <screen>ftp&gt; cd htdocs/devel/doc/manual/pdf</screen>
                </step>

                <step>
                    <para>List the contents of the directory:</para>

                    <screen>ftp&gt; ls
...</screen>
                </step>
            </procedure>

            <para>You now have a working VPN system and can use it to upload completed
            documents to the Firebird network.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <appendix id="fbvpn-dochist">
        <title>Document history</title>

        <para>The exact file history is recorded in the <filename
        class="directory">manual</filename> module in our CVS tree; see <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=9028">http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=9028</ulink>.
        The full URL of the CVS log for this file can be found at <ulink
        url="http://firebird.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/firebird/manual/src/docs/firebirddocs/fbdoc_vpn.xml?view=log"
        userlevel="">http://firebird.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/firebird/manual/src/docs/firebirddocs/fbdoc_vpn.xml?view=log</ulink></para>

        <para><revhistory>
                <revision>
                    <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>

                    <date>30 March 2010</date>

                    <authorinitials>ND</authorinitials>

                    <revdescription>
                        <para>Created new manual.</para>
                    </revdescription>
                </revision>
            </revhistory></para>
    </appendix>

    <appendix id="fbvpn-license">
        <title>License notice</title>

        <para>The contents of this Documentation are subject to the Public Documentation
        License Version 1.0 (the <quote>License</quote>); you may only use this
        Documentation if you comply with the terms of this License. Copies of the License
        are available at <ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/pdfmanual/pdl.pdf">http://www.firebirdsql.org/pdfmanual/pdl.pdf</ulink>
        (PDF) and <ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/manual/pdl.html">http://www.firebirdsql.org/manual/pdl.html</ulink>
        (HTML).</para>

        <para>The Original Documentation is titled <citetitle>Firebird Backup File
        Splitting Filter</citetitle>.</para>

        <para>The Initial Writer of the Original Documentation is: Norman Dunbar.</para>

        <para>Copyright (C) 2010. All Rights Reserved. Initial Writer contact:
        NormanDunbar at users dot sourceforge dot net.</para>
    </appendix>
</article>
