<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
    -->
<article id="fb-shell-scripts">
    <title>Firebird Shell Scripts</title>

    <titleabbrev>Assorted Linux/Unix Scripts</titleabbrev>

    <articleinfo>
        <date>19 October 2009</date>

        <author>
            <firstname>Norman</firstname>

            <surname>Dunbar</surname>
        </author>

        <edition>27 April 2010 - Document version 1.2</edition>
    </articleinfo>

    <section id="fbscripts-intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>After a successful installation of Firebird, the <filename
        class="directory">/opt/firebird/bin</filename> directory will contain a number of
        useful shell scripts. This manual gives details of what these scripts are for and
        how they are used.</para>

        <para>In the remainder of this manual, we will discuss the following
        scripts:</para>

        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>changeDBAPassword.sh</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>createAliasDB.sh</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>fb_config</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>changeRunUser.sh</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>restoreRootRunUser.sh</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>changeGdsLibraryCompatibleLink.sh (Classic server only.)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
            <para>The above list is correct at the time of writing and, unless otherwise
            noted, only applies to Firebird 1.5, 2.0 and 2.1 Super Server installed on a
            Linux system. Other flavours of Unix may have different scripts. I am
            currently unable to discuss those potential changes as I do not have access to
            other Unix systems.</para>
        </note>
    </section>

    <section id="fbscripts-dba-password">
        <title>ChangeDBAPassword</title>

        <titleabbrev>Changing SYSDBA's Password</titleabbrev>

        <para>The <filename>changeDBAPassword.sh</filename> script allows the password for
        the SYSDBA user to be changed and various startup scripts etc to have their
        ownership changed accordingly. The script is run in non-interactive mode as part
        of the installation process to create an initial randomly generated password which
        is stored in the <filename>/opt/firebird/SYSDBA.password</filename> file.</para>

        <para>Up until version 2.1 of Firebird, the password is subsequently used in the
        startup script <filename>/etc/rc.d/init.d/firebird</filename>, which also has a
        symlink set up to point to <filename
        class="symlink">/etc/init.d/firebird</filename>. </para>

        <para>The security database <filename>(/opt/firebird/security.fdb</filename> or
        <filename>/opt/firebird/security2.fdb</filename> - depending on your Firebird
        version) is also updated with the new password.</para>

        <caution>
            <para>The script must be run as the root user, and when run,
            <filename>changeDBAPassword.sh</filename> will prompt you for the current
            SYSDBA password and then for a new password. Both of these will appear on the
            display so for enhanced security, don't allow anyone to look over your
            shoulder when you run the script.</para>

            <para>After the script has been run, the file
            <filename>/opt/firebird/SYSDBA.password</filename> will contain the password
            in plain text, so make sure that this file is not readable by anyone except
            root.</para>
        </caution>

        <para>The following is an example of running the script to change the SYSDBA
        password from 'masterkey' to 'biroguin' which being a made up word, should be less
        crackable or guessable.</para>

        <screen># cd /opt/firebird/bin
# ./changeDBAPassword.sh
Please enter current password for SYSDBA user : masterkey
Please enter new password for SYSDBA user : biroguin
GSEC&gt; GSEC&gt;

Running ed to modify /etc/init.d/firebird
</screen>

        <caution>
            <para>Whenever you change the SYSDBA password using the
            <application>gsec</application> utility, you should also change the startup
            script file as well. To ensure a complete update, always use this script when
            changing the SYSDBA user's password. </para>

            <para>This doesn't apply when using Firebird 2.1 and above as the startup
            script no longer requires the SYSDBA password.</para>

            <para>In the example above, the last line of output will not be displayed on
            systems running Firebird 2.1 and above as the startup scripts are no longer
            changed when the SYSDBA password is modified.</para>
        </caution>
    </section>

    <section id="fbscripts-db-alias">
        <title>CreateAliasDB</title>

        <titleabbrev>Creating Database Alias Names</titleabbrev>

        <para>The <filename>createAliasDB.sh</filename> script allows the creation of a
        new database to be carried out, and an alias for that database to be created in
        the file <filename>/opt/firebird/aliases.conf</filename>.</para>

        <note>
            <para>The <filename>createAliasDB.sh</filename> script must be run as the root
            user.</para>
        </note>

        <para>If your system is not set up properly, the database creation step may fail
        but the alias will still be added to the aliases file. This could leave you
        subsequently unable to add the alias properly, as the script checks to ensure that
        you do not overwrite an existing alias. You will have to manually edit the alias
        file to remove the broken alias.</para>

        <para>All databases must be owned by the firebird user, and by the firebird group.
        The following shows a new directory being created by the root user to allow
        Firebird databases to be created.</para>

        <screen># cd /u01
# mkdir databases
# chown firebird:firebird databases
</screen>

        <para>At this point the directory <filename>/u01/databases</filename> is available
        for use as a repository for one or more Firebird databases. Obviously, in the
        above example, the <filename class="directory">/u01</filename> directory already
        existed.</para>

        <section>
            <title>createAliasDB.sh Parameters</title>

            <para>To run the <filename>createAliasDP.sh</filename> script, use a command
            line similar to the following:</para>

            <para><userinput># createAliasDB.sh &lt;new_alias&gt;
            &lt;database_name&gt;</userinput></para>

            <para>The script takes two parameters on the command line, both of which are
            mandatory:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>new_alias</userinput></para>

                    <para>The first parameter is the new alias you wish to create. This
                    alias must not already exist in the alias file, or an error will be
                    displayed and no further action taken.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>database_filename</userinput></para>

                    <para>The second parameter specifies the <emphasis>full
                    path</emphasis> to the database file. You must not specify a relative
                    path as this could lead to incorrect database filenames being used at
                    connection time. The script will reject any attempt to pass a relative
                    pathname instead of a full pathname.</para>

                    <para>A brand new empty database will be created provided that the
                    name passed to the script doesn't already exist. If the database
                    already exists, only the alias will be created and added to the alias
                    file.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="fbscripts-fb-config">
        <title>Fb_config</title>

        <titleabbrev>A Helping Hand With Makefiles</titleabbrev>

        <para>The <filename>fb_config</filename> script is intended to be used from within
        a makefile to supply various settings and compiler options which are accurate and
        specific to the installation being used.</para>

        <note>
            <para>This script can be run by any user who has been given execute privileges
            to it. You do not need to be root to use this script.</para>
        </note>

        <section>
            <title>fb_config Options</title>

            <para>To run the <filename>fb_config</filename> script, use a command line
            similar to the following:</para>

            <para><userinput>fb_config &lt;option&gt; [ &lt;option&gt;
            [...]]</userinput></para>

            <para>The script takes one or more options on the command line:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>--help</userinput></para>

                    <para>This parameter displays the list of allowed options. It should
                    not be supplied in addition to other options.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>--cflags</userinput></para>

                    <para>This option returns the list of directories where Firebird
                    include files are stored. This is required by the C and C++ compilers
                    to allow compiler #include directives to be correctly resolved. On my
                    own system, this option returns
                    '<computeroutput>-I/opt/firebird/include</computeroutput>'.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>--libs</userinput></para>

                    <para>This option returns the list of directories where Firebird
                    libraries are located and a list of those libraries that are required
                    to be linked by the linker to create a client server Firebird
                    application. This option returns '<computeroutput>-L/opt/firebird/lib
                    -lfbclient</computeroutput>' on my system.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>--embedlibs</userinput></para>

                    <para>This option returns the list of directories where Firebird
                    libraries are located and a list of those libraries that are required
                    to be linked by the linker to create an embedded Firebird application.
                    This option returns '<computeroutput>-L/opt/firebird/lib
                    -lfbembed</computeroutput>' on my system.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>--bindir</userinput></para>

                    <para>On my system, this option returns
                    '<computeroutput>/opt/firebird/bin</computeroutput>' as the full path
                    to the Firebird <filename>/bin</filename> directory.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>--version</userinput></para>

                    <para>This option returns a three part version string made up of the
                    concatenation of the Firebird build version, a dash, the package
                    version, a dot and the system architecture. My own laptop Linux system
                    returns '<computeroutput>1.5.0.4290-0.i686</computeroutput>'.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The following is a brief excerpt from a makefile which shows how to
            define two macros, FBFLAGS and FBLIBS, and initialise them to the correct
            values using fb_config. Note the use of the back tick character (`) rather
            than a single quote character (').</para>

            <programlisting>...
FBFLAGS = `fb_config --cflags`
FBLIBS = `fb_config --libs`
...</programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="fbscripts-run-user">
        <title>ChangeRunUser</title>

        <titleabbrev>Changing the Firebird Server Run User</titleabbrev>

        <para>Under Firebird 1.5 there are two versions of the
        <filename>changeRunUser.sh</filename> script, the one prefixed 'SS' is for Super
        Server installations and the one prefixed 'CS' is for Classic Server
        installations. In Firebird 2 onwards, the script is simply
        <filename>changeRunUser.sh</filename>.</para>

        <note>
            <para>The script should be run as root.</para>
        </note>

        <para>The <filename>changeRunUser.sh</filename> script allows the user and group,
        under which the Firebird server runs, to be changed. By default, this is now the
        firebird user and group, however, in previous versions the Firebird server ran as
        the root user which is undesirable from a system security point of view and
        allowed databases to be created all over the file system. With the new firebird
        user, restrictions can be placed on where databases can be created.</para>

        <para>The script changes the owing user and group of a number of files in the
        Firebird installation directory, the logfile and also the startup script
        <filename>/etc/rc.d.init.d/firebird</filename> which is used to start and stop the
        Firebird server.</para>

        <section>
            <title>ChangeRunUser.sh Parameters</title>

            <para>To run the script, use a command line similar to the following:</para>

            <para><userinput>changeRunUser.sh &lt;username&gt;
            &lt;groupname&gt;</userinput></para>

            <para>The script takes two parameters on the command line, both of which are
            optional as you will be prompted if both are omitted. If you only supply one
            parameter, it is assumed to be the username and you will be prompted for the
            groupname.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>username</userinput></para>

                    <para>This parameter sets the username under which the Firebird server
                    is to run. The supplied value is validated against entries in
                    <filename>/etc/passwd</filename>.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><userinput>groupname</userinput></para>

                    <para>This parameter sets the groupname under which the Firebird
                    server is to run. The supplied value is validated against entries in
                    <filename>/etc/group</filename>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The following example shows the use of
            <filename>changeRunUser.sh</filename> to change the owning user and group to
            firebird. The firebird user and group is actually the default when Firebird is
            installed so there is no need for you to run the script unless you have
            changed these details already.</para>

            <screen># cd /opt/firebird/bin
# ./changeRunUser.sh firebird firebird
Updating /opt/firebird
Updating startup script
Completed
</screen>

            <para>If you are running Firebird 2.1 or higher, there is no longer a prompt
            if you run this script with no parameters. The script now defaults to firebird
            for the user and group if you do not supply any parameters. Running the script
            under 2.1 gives the following:</para>

            <screen># cd /opt/firebird/bin
# ./changeRunUser.sh
Shutting down Firebird                                                done

Change Firebird install for /opt/firebird to uid=firebird gid=firebird
(User or group options can be changed by editing this script)

Press return to continue - or ^C to abort

Updating /etc file(s)
Updating /opt/firebird
Starting Firebird                                                     done
Completed.
</screen>

            <warning>
                <para>When this script prompts you to "<emphasis>Press return to continue
                ...</emphasis>" any VNC sessions connected to the <emphasis>database
                server</emphasis> will have been killed. Please ensure that you have the
                server at a quiet period and not during normal running hours when you make
                this change. This affects Suse Linux Enterprise 10 but may affect other
                Linux distributions as well.</para>
            </warning>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="fbscripts-root-user">
        <title>RestoreRootRunUser</title>

        <titleabbrev>Restoring root as the Server Run User</titleabbrev>

        <para>Under Firebird 1.5 there are two versions of the
        <filename>restoreRootRunUser.sh</filename> script. The one prefixed 'SS' is for
        Super Server installations and the one prefixed 'CS' is for Classic Server
        installations. In Firebird 2 onwards, the script is simply
        <filename>restoreRootRunUser.sh</filename>.</para>

        <note>
            <para>This script must be run as root.</para>
        </note>

        <para>This script simply restores the old style installation format whereby the
        Firebird Super Server runs as the root user and group.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="fbscripts-symlink">
        <title>ChangeGDSLibraryCompatibleLink</title>

        <titleabbrev>Running Embedded or Client-Server Apps</titleabbrev>

        <para>This script, <filename>changeGdsLibraryCompatibleLink.sh</filename>, is
        available with Classic Server installations only, and is used to change the
        symlink <filename class="symlink">libgds.so</filename> to point to the appropriate
        library for the installation. There are two possible libraries that the symlink
        can point to:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><filename
                class="libraryfile">/opt/firebird/lib/libfbclient.so</filename> for client
                server applications</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><filename
                class="libraryfile">/opt/firebird/lib/libfbembed.so</filename> for
                embedded server applications.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>After installation, the <filename class="symlink">libgds.so</filename>
        symlink points to the client server library by default so if you are running an
        embedded application, you need to run this script to point <filename
        class="symlink">libgds.so</filename> at the embedded library instead.</para>

        <note>
            <para>This script must be run as root.</para>
        </note>

        <para>The following example shows how this script is used to change from embedded
        server to client server use:</para>

        <screen># cd /opt/firebird/bin
# ./changeGdsCompatibleLibraryLink.sh
For classic server there are two optional backward compatible client
libraries. These are libfbclient.so and libfbembed.so.

libfbclient.so) enables your client to be multithreaded but must
                connect to a database via a server.
libfbembed.so)  allows the client to directly open the database file,
                but does not support multithreaded access

Your current setting is:
/usr/lib/libgds.so -&gt; /opt/firebird/lib/libfbembed.so

Which option would you like to choose (client|embed|remove) 
                                                       [client] client
#</screen>

        <para>The default option is <userinput>client</userinput> which will recreate the
        symlink to the client server library, <userinput>embed</userinput> will recreate
        the symlink to the embedded server, while <userinput>remove</userinput> will
        remove the symlink altogether.</para>

        <para>There are no messages displayed to inform you of the success of the script,
        however, if you run it again, you will notice the current setting should be
        different to that displayed when you previously ran the script.</para>
    </section>

    <appendix id="fbscripts-dochist">
        <title>Document history</title>

        <para>The exact file history is recorded in the <filename
        class="directory">manual</filename> module in our CVS tree; see <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=9028">http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=9028</ulink>.
        The full URL of the CVS log for this file can be found at <ulink
        url="http://firebird.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/firebird/manual/src/docs/firebirddocs/fbutil_scripts.xml?view=log"
        userlevel="">http://firebird.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/firebird/manual/src/docs/firebirddocs/fbutil_scripts.xml?view=log</ulink></para>

        <para><revhistory>
                <revision>
                    <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>

                    <date>22 November 2004</date>

                    <authorinitials>ND</authorinitials>

                    <revdescription>
                        <para>Created as a chapter in the Command Line Utilities
                        manual.</para>
                    </revdescription>
                </revision>

                <revision>
                    <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>

                    <date>19 October 2009</date>

                    <authorinitials>ND</authorinitials>

                    <revdescription>
                        <para>Updated for Firebird 2, minor changes to punctuation and
                        then converted to a stand alone manual.</para>
                    </revdescription>
                </revision>

                <revision>
                    <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>

                    <date>05 January 2010</date>

                    <authorinitials>ND</authorinitials>

                    <revdescription>
                        <para>Spelling correction.</para>
                    </revdescription>
                </revision>

                <revision>
                    <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>

                    <date>27 April 2010</date>

                    <authorinitials>ND</authorinitials>

                    <revdescription>
                        <para>When changing the DBA password, it is no longer the case
                        that the startup script is also amended. Other changed for version
                        2.1 added.</para>
                    </revdescription>
                </revision>
            </revhistory></para>
    </appendix>

    <appendix id="fbscripts-license">
        <title>License notice</title>

        <para>The contents of this Documentation are subject to the Public Documentation
        License Version 1.0 (the <quote>License</quote>); you may only use this
        Documentation if you comply with the terms of this License. Copies of the License
        are available at <ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/pdfmanual/pdl.pdf">http://www.firebirdsql.org/pdfmanual/pdl.pdf</ulink>
        (PDF) and <ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/manual/pdl.html">http://www.firebirdsql.org/manual/pdl.html</ulink>
        (HTML).</para>

        <para>The Original Documentation is titled <citetitle>Firebird Shell
        Scripts</citetitle>.</para>

        <para>The Initial Writer of the Original Documentation is: Norman Dunbar.</para>

        <para>Copyright (C) 2004–2009. All Rights Reserved. Initial Writer contact:
        NormanDunbar at users dot sourceforge dot net.</para>
    </appendix>
</article>
