<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
    -->
<article id="gsplit">
    <title>Firebird Backup File Splitting Filter</title>

    <titleabbrev>Gsplit - Backup File Splitting Filter</titleabbrev>

    <articleinfo>
        <date>20 October 2009</date>

        <author>
            <firstname>Norman</firstname>

            <surname>Dunbar</surname>
        </author>

        <edition>20 October 2009 – Document version 1.1</edition>
    </articleinfo>

    <section id="gsplit-intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>In the past, many operating systems imposed a limit which defined how large
        a single file could become. This limit was 2 Gb on some systems, and 4 Gb on
        others. For example, on HP-UX 10.20 or 11.00 Unix systems, the maximum file size
        is 2 Gb unless the file system has the <emphasis>largefiles</emphasis> option
        turned on. This limit still exists on some operating systems.</para>

        <para><application>Gsplit</application> is a filter utility introduced with
        <application>Interbase 5.0</application> which allows the output file from the
        <application>gbak</application> utility (when backing up a database) to be split
        into a number of chunks, or a number of chunks to be joined together and used to
        restore a database. Up until <application>Interbase 5.0</application>, dump files
        were limited to 2 Gb by the <application>gbak</application> utility itself - even
        if running on a system which allowed files to be 4 Gb.</para>

        <para>Coming up in the remainder of this manual, we will discuss the
        following:</para>

        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>Command line options for <application>gsplit</application>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><application>Gsplit</application> options and their
                parameters.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>Splitting backups using <application>gsplit</application>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>Joining backup chunks using
                <application>gsplit</application>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
            <para>From <application>Interbase 6.0</application>,
            <application>gsplit</application> is no longer required as
            <application>gbak</application> allows large files to be split directly. The
            details for <application>gsplit</application> given here are for reference
            only and you are advised to use <application>gbak</application> to split large
            backup files even if <application>gsplit</application> is supplied with your
            <application>Firebird</application> release.</para>

            <para><application>Gsplit</application> is only supplied with the Windows
            version of Firebird 1.5, it is not supplied with the Linux version. Linux
            doesn't require a separate utility as it can split files using the
            <command>split</command> command as well as using
            <application>gbak</application>.</para>
        </note>

        <warning>
            <para>In testing with Firebird 1.5 and Firebird 2.0 on Windows XP Home and
            WIndows 2000, <application>gsplit</application> doesn't seem to work properly
            and always returns an error.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>Because of the problems in getting <application>gsplit</application> to work
        correctly, as you shall see in the remainder of this manual, you are advised to
        use the splitting and joining facilities of the <application>gbak</application>
        utility itself rather than trying to make <application>gsplit</application> work
        for you.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gsplit-cmdline">
        <title>Gsplit Command line Options</title>

        <para><application>Gsplit</application> has three command line options, although,
        strictly speaking, the <userinput>-help</userinput> option isn't really valid.
        These are:</para>

        <itemizedlist spacing="normal">
            <listitem>
                <para><userinput>-split_bk_file &lt;parameters&gt;</userinput></para>

                <para>Specifies that <application>gsplit</application> is to be used to
                split the output from <application>gbak</application> into a number of
                different files as part of a database backup. This option can be shortened
                as required, provided that at least <userinput>-s</userinput> is
                specified.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><userinput>-join_bk_file &lt;parameters&gt;</userinput></para>

                <para>Specifies that <application>gsplit</application> is to be used to
                rejoin a number of files and use the result as input to
                <application>gbak</application> as part of a database restore. This option
                can be shortened as required, provided that at least
                <userinput>-j</userinput> is specified.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><userinput>-help</userinput></para>

                <para>Using the -help option, specifying an illegal option, or omitting
                all options, displays the following information:</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <screen>gsplit: invalid option '-help'
gsplit: Command Line Options Are:
gsplit -S[PLIT_BK_FILE] &lt;file&gt; &lt;size&gt;{k|m|g} [... &lt;file&gt; [&lt;size&gt;{k|m|g}]]
  or gsplit -J[OINT_BK_FILE] &lt;file&gt; [... &lt;file&gt;]
gsplit: option can be abbreviated to the unparenthesized characters
gsplit: Exiting before completion due to errors
</screen>

        <note>
            <para>Take note of the error in the above help text. The correct command line
            option to join multiple sections of a large backup file is not
            <userinput>-JOINT_BK_FILE</userinput> as shown, but is in fact
            <userinput>-JOIN_BK_FILE</userinput>.</para>
        </note>
    </section>

    <section id="gsplit-parameters">
        <title>Gsplit Command Parameters</title>

        <para>Both main <application>gsplit</application> command line options require
        parameters. When splitting a backup, the parameters are:</para>

        <itemizedlist spacing="normal">
            <listitem>
                <para><userinput>-S[PLIT_BK_FILE] &lt;file&gt; &lt;size&gt;{k|m|g} [...
                &lt;file&gt; [&lt;size&gt;{k|m|g}]]</userinput></para>

                <para>The first parameter is the first filename, followed by the maximum
                size it is allowed to be. You may specify the size in kilobytes, megabytes
                or gigabytes. There should not be any spaces between the digit(s) and the
                size specifier letter. There must be a space between the filename and the
                size however.</para>

                <para>The remainder of the parameters specify the second and subsequent
                filenames and sizes, however, the final file need not have a size
                specified as it will be used to take up the remaining bytes after the
                other files have been filled to capacity. If there is a size specified, it
                is simply ignored but no error or warning messages are displayed.</para>

                <para>If you have a backup file which will be 4 Gb in size and you only
                ask for two files, each 1 Gb in size, <application>gsplit</application>
                will ignore the size of the final file and just keep filling it up until
                the backup is complete.</para>

                <para>The utility prevents files of less than 1 Mb and will produce an
                error if you attempt to specify a file smaller than this.</para>

                <note>
                    <para><application>Gsplit</application> correctly specifies a Kilobyte
                    as 1024 bytes, a Megabyte as 1024 Kilobytes and a Gigabyte as 1024
                    Megabytes.</para>
                </note>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><userinput>-J[OIN_BK_FILE] &lt;file&gt; [...
                &lt;file&gt;]</userinput></para>

                <para>To join files together and use them to restore a database, you
                simply specify the filenames in the correct order. If they are not in the
                correct order, <application>gsplit</application> will complain and the
                restore will be abandoned.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="gsplit-splitting">
        <title>Splitting Backups</title>

        <para>To run <application>gsplit</application> , you need to use it as a filter on
        the command line for <application> gbak</application>, as the following example
        shows:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt;gbak -b norman.fdb stdout | 
    gsplit -split norman_1.fbk 1m norman_2.fbk 1m norman_3.fbk</screen>

        <warning>
            <para>The command above assumes that <envar>ISC_USER</envar> and
            <envar>ISC_PASSWORD</envar> have been defined. For the sake of this
            demonstration, this is acceptable, but in a real system, consider the security
            implications before defining these variables.</para>

            <para>In addition, the above command line has been split over two lines to
            allow the pdf generation of this manual to work. In reality, the command must
            be typed on a single line.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>It is unfortunate that the utility supplied with Firebird 1.5
        <emphasis>doesn't work</emphasis>, as the following shows:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt;gbak -b norman.fdb stdout | 
    gsplit -split norman_1.fbk 1m norman_2.fbk 1m norman_3.fbk

fail to read input from ib_stdin, errno = 9
gsplit: progam fails to generate multi-volumn back-up files

Done with volume #0, "stdout"
        Press return to reopen that file, or type a new
        name followed by return to open a different file.
  Name:^C
</screen>

        <para>If you type a filename at the prompt it will simply be used as a destination
        for a full dump of the database, so be careful not to overwrite anything
        important. I tend to hit <keycap>CTRL-C</keycap> at this point to avoid
        problems.</para>

        <para>The utility has actually created the first file in the above list,
        <filename>norman_1.fbk</filename>, and written 100 bytes to a special header which
        identifies it as a <application>gsplit</application> created file.</para>

        <warning>
            <para>The command above assumes that <envar>ISC_USER</envar> and
            <envar>ISC_PASSWORD</envar> have been defined. For the sake of this
            demonstration, this is acceptable, but in a real system, consider the security
            implications before defining these variables.</para>

            <para>In addition, the above command line has been split over two lines to
            allow the pdf generation of this manual to work. In reality, the command must
            be typed on a single line.</para>
        </warning>

        <note>
            <para>The spelling errors in 'program' and 'volume' above are as produced by
            the utility.</para>
        </note>

        <para>The command does work under Firebird 2, however, it only creates the first
        file and then prompts for a new filename for the second file as the following
        shows:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt;gbak -b norman.fdb stdout | 
    gsplit -split norman_1.fbk 1m norman_2.fbk 1m norman_3.fbk

Done with volume #1, "stdout"   Press return to reopen that file, or type a new
        name followed by return to open a different file.  Name:
</screen>

        <para>If you press return at the prompt, the second file will be named
        <filename>stdout</filename> and not <filename>norman_2.fbk</filename>. If, on the
        other hand, you supply the filename <filename>norman_2.fbk</filename> then that
        file will be written to. Unfortunately you cannot specify how large the file is
        allowed to be, if you try, the file size becomes part of the file name.</para>

        <warning>
            <para>I would say that as with Firebird 1.5's version of
            <application>gsplit</application>, using it to split a backup file is
            pointless. Use the <application>gbak</application> method to be safe.</para>
        </warning>
    </section>

    <section id="gsplit-joining">
        <title>Joining Backup Files</title>

        <para>Had the above backup actually worked, the command to restore a backup from a
        number of files created by <application>gsplit</application> would be as
        follows:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt;gsplit -join norman_1.fbk norman_2.fbk norman_3.fbk | 
    gbak -c stdin create_norman.fdb</screen>

        <warning>
            <para>The above command line has been split over two lines to allow the pdf
            generation of this manual to work. In reality, the command must be typed on a
            single line.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>If you have a number of split backup files created using
        <application>gbak</application> itself and not filtered through
        <application>gsplit</application>, you cannot use
        <application>gsplit</application> to stitch them together for a restore as the
        following example shows:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt;gsplit -join norman_1.fbk norman_2.fbk norman_3.fbk | 
    gbak -c stdin create_norman.fdb
gsplit: expected GSPLIT description record
gsplit: Exiting before completion due to errors
gsplit: progam fails to join multi-volumn back-up files
gbak: ERROR: expected backup description record
gbak: Exiting before completion due to errors
</screen>

        <warning>
            <para>The above command line has been split over two lines to allow the pdf
            generation of this manual to work. In reality, the command must be typed on a
            single line.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>It appears that <application>gsplit</application> and
        <application>gbak</application> have different header information in the backup
        files and the two are not compatible.</para>

        <note>
            <para>The spelling errors in 'program' and 'volume' above are as produced by
            the utility.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Even with the version of <application>gsplit</application> supplied with
        Firebird 2, joining it's own partial files doesn't work:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt;gsplit -join norman_1.fbk norman_2.fbk norman_3.fbk | 
    gbak -c stdin create_norman.fdb

gbak:do not recognize domain attribute 13 -- continuing
gbak: ERROR:do not recognize record type 11
gbak:Exiting before completion due to errors

gsplit: expected GSPLIT description record
gsplit: Exiting before completion due to errors
gsplit: progam fails to join multi-volumn back-up files</screen>
    </section>

    <appendix id="gsplit-dochist">
        <title>Document history</title>

        <para>The exact file history is recorded in the <filename
        class="directory">manual</filename> module in our CVS tree; see <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=9028">http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=9028</ulink>.
        The full URL of the CVS log for this file can be found at <ulink
        url="http://firebird.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/firebird/manual/src/docs/firebirddocs/fbutil_gsplit.xml?view=log"
        userlevel="">http://firebird.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/firebird/manual/src/docs/firebirddocs/fbutil_gsplit.xml?view=log</ulink></para>

        <para><revhistory>
                <revision>
                    <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>

                    <date>21 December 2004</date>

                    <authorinitials>ND</authorinitials>

                    <revdescription>
                        <para>Created as a chapter in the Command Line Utilities
                        manual.</para>
                    </revdescription>
                </revision>

                <revision>
                    <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>

                    <date>20 October 2009</date>

                    <authorinitials>ND</authorinitials>

                    <revdescription>
                        <para>Some updates for Firebird 2 and converted to a stand alone
                        manual.</para>
                    </revdescription>
                </revision>
            </revhistory></para>
    </appendix>

    <appendix id="gsplit-license">
        <title>License notice</title>

        <para>The contents of this Documentation are subject to the Public Documentation
        License Version 1.0 (the <quote>License</quote>); you may only use this
        Documentation if you comply with the terms of this License. Copies of the License
        are available at <ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/pdfmanual/pdl.pdf">http://www.firebirdsql.org/pdfmanual/pdl.pdf</ulink>
        (PDF) and <ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/manual/pdl.html">http://www.firebirdsql.org/manual/pdl.html</ulink>
        (HTML).</para>

        <para>The Original Documentation is titled <citetitle>Firebird Backup File
        Splitting Filter</citetitle>.</para>

        <para>The Initial Writer of the Original Documentation is: Norman Dunbar.</para>

        <para>Copyright (C) 2004–2009. All Rights Reserved. Initial Writer contact:
        NormanDunbar at users dot sourceforge dot net.</para>
    </appendix>
</article>
