<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
-->
<chapter id="fbutils-gsplit">
  <title>GSPLIT - Firebird Backup File Splitting Filter</title>

  <section id="fbutils-gsplit-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>In the past, many operating systems imposed a limit which defined
    how large a single file could become. This limit was 2 Gb on some systems,
    and 4 Gb on others. For example, on HP-UX 10.20 or 11.00 Unix systems, the
    maximum file size is 2 Gb unless the file system has the
    <emphasis>largefiles</emphasis> option turned on. This limit still exists
    on some operating systems.</para>

    <para><application>GSPLIT</application> is a filter utility introduced
    with <application>Interbase 5.0</application> which allows the output file
    from the GBAK utility (when backing up a database) to be split into a
    number of chunks, or a number of chunks to be joined together and used to
    restore a database. Up until <application>Interbase 5.0</application>,
    dump files were limited to 2 Gb by the <application>GBAK</application>
    utility itself - even if running on a system which allowed files to be 4
    Gb.</para>

    <para>Coming up in this chapter, we have :</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Command line options for
        <application>GSPLIT</application>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><application>GSPLIT</application> options and their
        parameters.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Splitting backups using
        <application>GSPLIT</application>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Joining backup chunks using
        <application>GSPLIT</application>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>From <application>Interbase 6.0</application>,
      <application>GSPLIT</application> is no longer required as
      <application>GBAK</application> allows large files to be split directly.
      The details for <application>GSPLIT</application> given here are for
      reference only and you are advised to use
      <application>GBAK</application> to split large backup files even if
      <application>GSPLIT</application> is supplied with your
      <application>Firebird</application> release.</para>

      <para><application>GSPLIT</application> is only supplied with the
      Windows version of Firebird 1.5, it is not supplied with the Linux
      version. Linux doesn't require a separate utility as it can split files
      using the <command>split</command> command as well as using
      <application>GBAK</application>.</para>
    </note>

    <warning>
      <para>In testing with Firebird 1.5, on Windows XP Home,
      <application>GSPLIT</application> doesn't seem to work and always
      returns error 9.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>Because of the problems in getting <application>GSPLIT</application>
    to work correctly, as you shall see in the remainder of this chapter, you
    are advised to use the splitting and joining facilities of the
    <application>GBAK</application> utility itself rather than trying to make
    <application>GSPLIT</application> work for you.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="fbutils-gsplit-cmdline">
    <title>GSPLIT Command line Options</title>

    <para><application>GSPLIT</application> has three command line options,
    although, strictly speaking, the <userinput>-help</userinput> option isn't
    really valid. These are :</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
        <para><userinput>-split_bk_file &lt;parameters&gt;</userinput></para>

        <para>Specifies that <application>GSPLIT</application> is to be used
        to split the output from <application>GBAK</application> into a number
        of different files as part of a database backup. This option can be
        shortened as required, provided that at least
        <userinput>-s</userinput> is specified.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><userinput>-join_bk_file &lt;parameters&gt;</userinput></para>

        <para>Specifies that <application>GSPLIT</application> is to be used
        to rejoin a number of files and use the result as input to
        <application>GBAK</application> as part of a database restore. This
        option can be shortened as required, provided that at least
        <userinput>-j</userinput> is specified.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><userinput>-help</userinput></para>

        <para>Using the -help option, specifying an illegal option, or
        omitting all options, displays the following information :</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <screen>gsplit: invalid option '-help'
gsplit: Command Line Options Are:
gsplit -S[PLIT_BK_FILE] &lt;file&gt; &lt;size&gt;{k|m|g} [... &lt;file&gt; [&lt;size&gt;{k|m|g}]] or
gsplit -J[OINT_BK_FILE] &lt;file&gt; [... &lt;file&gt;]
gsplit: option can be abbreviated to the unparenthesized characters
gsplit: Exiting before completion due to errors
</screen>

    <note>
      <para>Take note of the error in the above help text. The correct command
      line option to join multiple sections of a large backup file is not
      <userinput>-JOINT_BK_FILE</userinput> as shown, but is in fact
      <userinput>-JOIN_BK_FILE</userinput>.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="fbutils-gsplit-parameters">
    <title>GSPLIT Command Parameters</title>

    <para>Both main <application>GSPLIT</application> command line options
    require parameters. When splitting a backup, the parameters are :</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
        <para><userinput>-S[PLIT_BK_FILE] &lt;file&gt; &lt;size&gt;{k|m|g}
        [... &lt;file&gt; [&lt;size&gt;{k|m|g}]]</userinput></para>

        <para>The first parameter is the first filename, followed by the
        maximum size it is allowed to be. You may specify the size in
        kilobytes, megabytes or gigabytes. There should not be any spaces
        between the digit(s) and the size specifier letter. There must be a
        space between the filename and the size however.</para>

        <para>The remainder of the parameters specify the second and
        subsequent filenames and sizes, however, the final file need not have
        a size specified as it will be used to take up the remaining bytes
        after the other files have been filled to capacity. If there is a size
        specified, it is simply ignored but no error or warning messages are
        displayed.</para>

        <para>If you have a backup file which will be 4 Gb in size and you
        only ask for two files, each 1 Gb in size,
        <application>GSPLIT</application> will ignore the size of the final
        file and just keep filling it up until the backup is complete.</para>

        <para>The utility prevents files of less than 1 Mb and will produce an
        error if you attempt to specify a file smaller than this.</para>

        <note>
          <para><application>GSPLIT</application> correctly specifies a
          Kilobyte as 1024 bytes, a Megabyte as 1024 Kilobytes and a Gigabyte
          as 1024 Megabytes.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><userinput>-J[OIN_BK_FILE] &lt;file&gt; [...
        &lt;file&gt;]</userinput></para>

        <para>To join files together and use them to restore a database, you
        simply specify the filenames in the correct order. If they are not in
        the correct order, <application>GSPLIT</application> will complain and
        the restore will be abandoned.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="fbutils-gsplit-splitting">
    <title>Splitting Backups</title>

    <para>To run <application>GSPLIT</application> , you need to use it as a
    filter on the command line for <application> GBAK</application>, as the
    following example shows :</para>

    <screen>C:\&gt;gbak -b norman.fdb stdout | 
    gsplit -split norman_1.fbk 1m norman_2.fbk 1m norman_3.fbk</screen>

    <warning>
      <para>The command above assumes that <envar>ISC_USER</envar> and
      <envar>ISC_PASSWORD</envar> have been defined. For the sake of this
      demonstration, this is acceptable, but in a real system, consider the
      security implications before defining these variables.</para>

      <para>In addition, the above command line has been split over two lines
      to allow the pdf generation of this manual to work. In reality, the
      command must be typed on a single line.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>It is unfortunate that the utility doesn't seem to work, as the
    following shows :</para>

    <screen>C:\&gt;gbak -b norman.fdb stdout | 
    gsplit -split norman_1.fbk 1m norman_2.fbk 1m norman_3.fbk
fail to read input from ib_stdin, errno = 9
gsplit: progam fails to generate multi-volumn back-up files
Done with volume #0, "stdout"
        Press return to reopen that file, or type a new
        name followed by return to open a different file.
  Name:^C
</screen>

    <para>If you type a filename at the prompt it will simply be used as a
    destination for a full dump of the database, so be careful not to
    overwrite anything important. I tend to hit <keycap>CTRL-C</keycap> at
    this point to avoid problems.</para>

    <para>The utility has actually created the first file in the above list,
    <filename>norman_1.fbk</filename>, and written 100 bytes to a special
    header which identifies it as a <application>GSPLIT</application> created
    file.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>The command above assumes that <envar>ISC_USER</envar> and
      <envar>ISC_PASSWORD</envar> have been defined. For the sake of this
      demonstration, this is acceptable, but in a real system, consider the
      security implications before defining these variables.</para>

      <para>In addition, the above command line has been split over two lines
      to allow the pdf generation of this manual to work. In reality, the
      command must be typed on a single line.</para>
    </warning>

    <note>
      <para>The spelling errors in 'program' and 'volume' above are as
      produced by the utility.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="fbutils-gsplit-joining">
    <title>Joining Backup Files</title>

    <para>Had the above backup actually worked, the command to restore a
    backup from a number of files created by <application>GSPLIT</application>
    would be as follows :</para>

    <screen>C:\&gt;gsplit -join norman_1.fbk norman_2.fbk norman_3.fbk | 
    gbak -c stdin create_norman.fdb</screen>

    <warning>
      <para>The above command line has been split over two lines to allow the
      pdf generation of this manual to work. In reality, the command must be
      typed on a single line.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>If you have a number of split backup files created using
    <application>GBAK</application> itself and not filtered through
    <application>GSPLIT</application>, you cannot use
    <application>GSPLIT</application> to stitch them together for a restore as
    the following example shows :</para>

    <screen>C:\&gt;gsplit -join norman_1.fbk norman_2.fbk norman_3.fbk | 
    gbak -c stdin create_norman.fdb
gsplit: expected GSPLIT description record
gsplit: Exiting before completion due to errors
gsplit: progam fails to join multi-volumn back-up files
gbak: ERROR: expected backup description record
gbak: Exiting before completion due to errors
</screen>

    <warning>
      <para>The above command line has been split over two lines to allow the
      pdf generation of this manual to work. In reality, the command must be
      typed on a single line.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>It appears that <application>GSPLIT</application> and
    <application>GBAK</application> have different header information in the
    backup files and the two are not compatible.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The spelling errors in 'program' and 'volume' above are as
      produced by the utility.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
</chapter>
