<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
-->
<chapter id="fbutils-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The Firebird 1.5 distribution kit installs a number of useful utility
  programs to assist in the running of your Firebird server &amp; databases.
  This book introduces you to the various utilities, some of which are more
  useful than others.</para>

  <para>The utilities can all be found in the <filename
  class="directory">/bin</filename> directory (or <filename
  class="directory">\bin</filename> folder on Windows) under the Firebird
  installation root. On Linux the utilities can be found in <filename
  class="directory">/opt/firebird/bin</filename> while on Windows, the default
  location is <filename class="directory">c:\program
  files\firebird\firebird_1_5\bin</filename>.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><application>FB_LOCK_PRINT</application> is the utility which
      prints out details of the internal database lock page.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><application>GBAK</application> is the database backup &amp;
      restore utility. It also allows various parameters internal to the
      database to be changed.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><application>GDEF</application> is a metadata utility which was
      removed from Interbase 4.0 and returned in the Open Source version 6.
      <application>GDEF</application> is probably redundant.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><application>GFIX</application> allows attempts to fix corrupted
      databases, starting and stopping of databases, resolving 'in limbo'
      transactions between multiple database, changing the number of page
      buffers and so on.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><application>GPRE</application> is the pre-processor which
      converts source code, which can be written in a number of languages,
      containing various embedded SQL 'pseudo code' into correctly formatted
      calls to the Firebird engine.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><application><link
      linkend="fbutils-gsec">GSEC</link></application> is the security
      database manipulation utility. It allows the DBA (or any privileged
      user) the ability to maintain user accounts for various Firebird
      databases. Using various options, users can be added, amended or deleted
      from the security database.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><application>GSPLIT</application> is a filter which allows the
      limitations on maximum file sizes, found on some operating systems, to
      be avoided when creating backups of large databases. This utility is
      supplied on Windows only and, unfortunately, seems not to work. Luckily,
      <application>GBAK</application> allows backup files to be split into
      multiple parts, so <application>GSPLIT</application> is not required. On
      Unix systems there are suitable operating system utilities that can be
      used instead of <application>GSPLIT</application>, if required.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><application>GSTAT</application> allows the Firebird administrator
      the ability to gather statistics about the general health and
      utilisation of various parts of the database.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><application>ISQL</application> is the interactive utility that
      allows ad-hoc queries to be run against a Firebird database. It is
      console based - as are many of the utilities - and is supplied with all
      distributions of Firebird. <application>ISQL</application> is usually
      the best place to try out your scripts and commands in the first
      instance.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>QLI is the original Query Language Interpreter which was removed
      from Interbase 4.0 but returned in Interbase 6.0 because of the decision
      to Open Source Interbase.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <note>
    <para>This book is a work in progress. Each chapter details a separate
    utility and as each one is completed to my satisfaction, I shall add it to
    the CVS repository where it will be available for download. In this
    manner, there will be a slow and gradual build up of hopefully useful
    manuals.</para>
  </note>

</chapter>
