<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
-->
<article id="nbackup">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Firebird's nbackup tool</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Paul</firstname>

      <surname>Vinkenoog</surname>
    </author>

    <edition>1 December 2006 – Document version 1.0</edition>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="nbackup-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><firstterm>nbackup</firstterm> is a new backup utility that comes
    with Firebird 2.0. It offers possibilities not present in
    <firstterm>gbak</firstterm> - Firebird's pre-existing backup tool - but
    doesn't replace the latter. Both programmes have their strengths and
    weaknesses; they will likely coexist for some time to come.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="nbackup-overview">
    <title>nbackup features - an overview</title>

    <para>With nbackup, you can perform two different groups of tasks:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Making and restoring of both full and
        <firstterm>incremental</firstterm> backups. An <firstterm>incremental
        backup</firstterm> only contains the mutations since some specific
        previous backup.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Locking the main database file so you can subsequently back it
        up yourself with copying or backup tools of your own choice. In this
        mode, nbackup doesn't back up anything; it just creates the conditions
        under which you can safely make the backup yourself. There's a
        provision for restoring here, too.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Both modes can operate on an active database, without hindering
    connected users. The backup created will always reflect the state of the
    database <emphasis>at the beginning of the operation</emphasis>. In these
    respects nbackup doesn't differ from gbak.</para>

    <section id="nbackup-advantages">
      <title>Advantages of nbackup</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Both modes:</emphasis> high speed (as high as
          hardware and OS will allow), because nbackup doesn't look at the
          actual data. In backup mode the contents are written more or less
          blindly to the backup file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Backup/restore mode:</emphasis> time and disk space
          savings, because you don't need to make a full backup every time.
          This can make a huge difference with databases in the gigabyte
          range.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Lock/unlock mode:</emphasis> total freedom in your
          choice of backup, copy, and/or compression tools.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="nbackup-limitations">
      <title>Limitations of nbackup</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>nbackup will not sweep and compact your database the way gbak
          does.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can't change the database owner with an nbackup
          backup/restore cycle, like you can with gbak.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>nbackup can't make <firstterm>transportable
          backups</firstterm>, that is: backups you can restore on an
          incompatible platform or under another server version.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>At this moment, nbackup should not be used on multi-file
          databases.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>nbackup can only back up local databases.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>We'll discuss nbackup's various functions extensively in the
      following sections.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="nbackup-backups">
    <title>Making and restoring backups</title>

    <para>To begin with: <filename>nbackup.exe</filename> is located in the
    <filename class="directory">bin</filename> subdirectory of your Firebird
    folder. Typical locations are e.g. <filename class="directory">C:\Program
    Files\Firebird\Firebird_2_0\bin</filename> (Windows) or <filename
    class="directory">/opt/firebird/bin</filename> (Linux). Just like most of
    the tools that come with Firebird, nbackup has no graphical interface; you
    launch it from the command prompt (or from within a batch file or
    application).</para>

    <section id="nbackup-backups-full">
      <title>Full backups</title>

      <section>
        <title>Making full backups</title>

        <para>To make a full database backup, the command syntax is:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <programlisting>nbackup [-U <replaceable>&lt;user&gt;</replaceable> -P <replaceable>&lt;password&gt;</replaceable>] -B 0 <replaceable>&lt;database&gt;</replaceable> [<replaceable>&lt;backupfile&gt;</replaceable>]</programlisting>
        </blockquote>

        <para>For instance:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <screen>C:\Data&gt; nbackup -B 0 inventory.fdb inventory_1-Mar-2006.nbk</screen>
        </blockquote>

        <para id="nbackup-backups-comments">Comments:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The parameter <parameter>-B</parameter> stands for backup
            (gee!). The <firstterm>backup level</firstterm> 0 indicates a full
            backup. Backup levels greater than 0 are used for incremental
            backups; we'll discuss those later on.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Instead of a database filename you may also specify an
            alias.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Instead of a backup filename you may also specify
            <systemitem>stdout</systemitem>. This will send the backup to
            standard output, from where you can redirect it to e.g. a tape
            archiver or a compression tool.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <parameter>-U</parameter> (user) and
            <parameter>-P</parameter> (password) parameters may be
            omitted:</para>

            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                <para>if you're logged on as superuser (<systemitem
                class="username">root</systemitem>, <systemitem
                class="username">Administrator</systemitem>...), or</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>if the environment variables <envar>ISC_USER</envar> and
                <envar>ISC_PASSWORD</envar> are set.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>For clarity and brevity, these parameters are not used in
            the examples.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The different parameters (<parameter>-B</parameter>,
            <parameter>-U</parameter> and <parameter>-P</parameter>) may occur
            in any order. Of course each parameter should be immediately
            followed by its own argument(s). In the case of
            <parameter>-B</parameter> there are three of them: backup level,
            database, and backup file - in that order!</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the <parameter>-B</parameter> parameter comes last, you
            <emphasis>may</emphasis> leave out the name of the backup file. In
            that case nbackup will compose a filename based on the database
            name, the backup level, and the current date and time. This can
            lead to a name clash (and a failed backup) if two backup commands
            of the same level are issued in the same minute.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <warning>
          <para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> use nbackup for multi-file
          databases. This can lead to corruption and loss of data, despite the
          fact that nbackup will not complain about such a command.</para>
        </warning>

        <section id="nbackup-backups-workings">
          <title>A word on the inner workings</title>

          <para>Note: What follows here is not necessary knowledge to use
          nbackup. It just gives a rough (and incomplete) image of what
          happens under the hood during execution of nbackup
          <parameter>-B</parameter>:</para>

          <procedure>
            <step>
              <para>First of all, the main database file is locked by changing
              an internal state flag. From this moment on, any and all
              mutations in the database are written to a temporary file - the
              difference file or <firstterm>delta file</firstterm>.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Then the actual backup is made. This isn't a straight file
              copy; restoring must be done by nbackup as well.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Upon completion of the backup, the contents of the delta
              file are integrated with the main database file. After that, the
              database is unlocked (flag goes back to <quote>normal</quote>)
              and the delta is removed.</para>
            </step>
          </procedure>

          <para>The functionality of steps 1 and 3 is provided by two new SQL
          statements: <database>ALTER DATABASE BEGIN BACKUP</database> and
          <database>ALTER DATABASE END BACKUP</database>. Contrary to what the
          names suggest, these statements do <emphasis>not</emphasis> take
          care of making the actual backup; rather, they create the conditions
          under which the main database file can be safely backed up. And to
          be clear: you don't need to issue these commands yourself; nbackup
          will do that for you, at the right moments.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Restoring a full backup</title>

        <para>A full backup is restored as follows:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <programlisting>nbackup [-U <replaceable>&lt;user&gt;</replaceable> -P <replaceable>&lt;password&gt;</replaceable>] -R <replaceable>&lt;database&gt;</replaceable> [<replaceable>&lt;backupfile&gt;</replaceable>]</programlisting>
        </blockquote>

        <para>For instance:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <screen>C:\Data&gt; nbackup -R inventory.fdb inventory_1-Mar-2006.nbk</screen>
        </blockquote>

        <para id="nbackup-restore-comments">Comments:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You don't specify a level for a restore.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>When restoring, the <parameter>-R</parameter> parameter
            <emphasis>must</emphasis> come last, for reasons that will become
            clear later.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the specified database exists already and there are no
            connections, it will be overwritten without any warning! If there
            are users connected, the restore fails and you get an error
            message.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Here too, you may omit the name of the backup file. If you
            do, nbackup will prompt you for it. <emphasis>However, this
            function is currently broken (at least under Windows). If you
            specify your backup file name(s) like this, you'll get an error
            message and a failed restore.</emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="nbackup-backups-incr">
      <title>Incremental backups</title>

      <section>
        <title>Making incremental backups</title>

        <para>To make an incremental (<quote>differential</quote>) backup we
        specify a backup level greater than 0. An incremental backup of level
        <replaceable>N</replaceable> always contains the database mutations
        since the most recent level <replaceable>N-1</replaceable>
        backup.</para>

        <para>Examples:</para>

        <para>One day after the full backup (level 0), you make one with level
        1:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <screen>C:\Data&gt; nbackup -B 1 inventory.fdb inventory_2-Mar-2006.nbk</screen>
        </blockquote>

        <para>This backup will only contain the mutations of the last
        day.</para>

        <para>One day later again, you make another one with level 1:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <screen>C:\Data&gt; nbackup -B 1 inventory.fdb inventory_3-Mar-2006.nbk</screen>
        </blockquote>

        <para>This one contains the mutations of the last
        <emphasis>two</emphasis> days, since the full backup, not only those
        since the previous level-1 backup.</para>

        <para>A couple of hours on we go for a level-2 backup:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <screen>C:\Data&gt; nbackup -B 2 inventory.fdb inventory_3-Mar-2006_2.nbk</screen>
        </blockquote>

        <para>This youngest backup only contains the mutations since the most
        recent level-1 backup, that is: of the last few hours.</para>

        <note>
          <para>All the <link
          linkend="nbackup-backups-comments">comments</link> that have been
          made about full backups also apply to incremental backups.</para>
        </note>

        <warning>
          <para>Again: do not use nbackup for multi-file databases.</para>
        </warning>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Restoring incremental backups</title>

        <para>When restoring incremental backups you must specify the entire
        chain of backup files, from level 0 through the one you wish to
        restore. The database is always built up from the ground, step by
        step. (It is this stepwise adding until the database is restored that
        gave rise to the term <emphasis>incremental backup</emphasis>.)</para>

        <para>The formal syntax is:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <programlisting>nbackup [-U <replaceable>&lt;user&gt;</replaceable> -P <replaceable>&lt;password&gt;</replaceable>] 
        -R <replaceable>&lt;database&gt;</replaceable> [<replaceable>&lt;backup0&gt;</replaceable> [<replaceable>&lt;backup1&gt;</replaceable> [<replaceable>...</replaceable>] ] ]       </programlisting>
        </blockquote>

        <para>So restoring the level-2 backup from the previous example goes
        as follows:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <screen>C:\Data&gt; nbackup -R inventory.fdb inventory_1-Mar-2006.nbk
           inventory_3-Mar-2006.nbk inventory_3-Mar-2006_2.nbk</screen>
        </blockquote>

        <para>Of course the line has been split here for layout reasons only -
        in reality you type the entire command and only hit
        <keycap>Enter</keycap> at the end.</para>

        <para>Comments (in addition to the <link
        linkend="nbackup-restore-comments">comments with restoring a full
        backup</link>):</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Because it is not known beforehand how many filenames will
            follow the <parameter>-R</parameter> switch (as we don't specify a
            level when restoring), nbackup considers all arguments after the
            <parameter>-R</parameter> to be names of backup files. It is for
            this reason that no other parameter (<parameter>-U</parameter> or
            <parameter>-P</parameter>) may follow the list of
            filenames.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>There is no formal limit to the number of backup levels, but
            in practice it will rarely make sense to go beyond 3 or 4.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <section>
          <title>Non-connecting links</title>

          <para>What happens if you accidentally leave out a file, or specify
          a series of files that don't all belong together? You could imagine
          that you specify <filename>inventory_2-Mar-2006.nbk</filename> by
          mistake instead of <filename>inventory_3-Mar-2006.nbk</filename> in
          the above example. Both are level-1 backup files, so in both cases
          we get a nice <quote>0, 1, 2</quote> level series. But our level-2
          file is incremental to the level-1 backup of 3 March, not to the one
          of 2 March.</para>

          <para>Fortunately such a mistake can never lead to an incorrectly
          restored database. Each backup file has its own unique ID.
          Furthermore, each backup file of level 1 or above contains the ID of
          the backup on which it is based. When restoring, nbackup checks
          these IDs; if somewhere in the chain the links don't connect, the
          operation is cancelled and you get an error message.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="nbackup-backups-pract">
      <title>A practical application</title>

      <para>An nbackup-based incremental backup scheme could look like
      this:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Each month a full backup (level 0) is made;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Each week a level-1;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A level-2 backup daily;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A level-3 backup hourly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As long as all backups are preserved, you can restore the database
      to its state at any hour in the past. For each restore action, a maximum
      of four backup files is used. Of course you schedule things in such a
      way that the bigger, time-consuming backups are made during off-peak
      hours. In this case the levels 0 and 1 could be made at weekends, and
      level 2 at night.</para>

      <para>If you don't want to keep everything for eternity, you can add a
      deletion schedule:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Level-3 backups are deleted after 8 days;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Level-2s after a month;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Level-1s after six months;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Full backups after two years, but the first one of each year
          is kept.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This is only an example of course. What's useful in an individual
      case depends on the application, the size of the database, its activity,
      etc.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="nbackup-backups-readon">
      <title>Read on?</title>

      <para>At this point you know everything you need in order to make and
      restore full and/or incremental backups with nbackup. You only need to
      read any further if you want to use backup tools of your own choice for
      your Firebird databases (see <link
      linkend="nbackup-lock-unlock"><citetitle>Locking and
      unlocking</citetitle></link>), or if you want to override the default
      name or location of the delta file (see <link
      linkend="nbackup-deltafile"><citetitle>Setting the delta
      file</citetitle></link>).</para>

      <para>If you have no craving for any of that: good luck in you work with
      nbackup!</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="nbackup-lock-unlock">
    <title>Locking and unlocking</title>

    <para>If you prefer to use your own backup tools or just make a file copy,
    nbackup's lock-unlock mode comes into view. <quote>Locking</quote> means
    here that the main database file is frozen temporarily, not that no
    changes can be made to the database. Just like in backup mode, mutations
    are directed to a temporary delta file; upon unlocking, the delta file is
    merged with the main file.</para>

    <para>As a reminder: <filename>nbackup.exe</filename> lives in the
    <filename class="directory">bin</filename> subdir of your Firebird folder.
    Typical locations are e.g. <filename class="directory">C:\Program
    Files\Firebird\Firebird_2_0\bin</filename> (Windows) or <filename
    class="directory">/opt/firebird/bin</filename> (Linux). There's no GUI;
    you launch it from the command prompt (or from within a batch file or
    application).</para>

    <section id="nbackup-lock-and-backup">
      <title>Locking the database and backing up yourself</title>

      <para>A typical session in which you make your own backup goes as
      follows:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Lock the database with the <parameter>-L</parameter> (lock)
          switch:</para>

          <blockquote>
            <programlisting>nbackup [-U <replaceable>&lt;user&gt;</replaceable> -P <replaceable>&lt;password&gt;</replaceable>] -L <replaceable>&lt;database&gt;</replaceable></programlisting>
          </blockquote>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Now copy/backup/zip the database file to your heart's content,
          with your own choice of tools. A simple file copy is also
          possible.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Unlock the database with <parameter>-N</parameter>
          (uNlock):</para>

          <blockquote>
            <programlisting>nbackup [-U <replaceable>&lt;user&gt;</replaceable> -P <replaceable>&lt;password&gt;</replaceable>] -N <replaceable>&lt;database&gt;</replaceable></programlisting>
          </blockquote>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>The last command will also cause any mutations - which have been
      written to the delta file - to be merged into the main file.</para>

      <para>The backup you made contains the data as they were at the moment
      the database was locked, regardless how long the locked state has
      lasted, and regardless how long you may have waited before making the
      actual backup.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>What goes for backup/restore also applies to the lock/unlock
        switches: do not use them on multi-file databases. Until things have
        changed, don't let nbackup loose on multi-file databases at
        all!</para>
      </warning>
    </section>

    <section id="nbackup-restore-and-fixup">
      <title>Restoring a backup made after <quote>nbackup -L</quote></title>

      <para>An copy of a locked database is itself a locked database too, so
      you can't just copy it back and start using it. Should your original
      database get lost or damaged and the self-made copy needs to be restored
      (or should you wish to install the copy on another machine), proceed
      like this:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Copy/restore/unzip the backed-up database file yourself with
          the necessary tools.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Now unlock the database, <emphasis>not</emphasis> with the
          <parameter>-N</parameter> switch, but with <parameter>-F</parameter>
          (fixup):</para>

          <blockquote>
            <programlisting>nbackup -F <replaceable>&lt;database&gt;</replaceable></programlisting>
          </blockquote>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>Why are there two unlock switches, <parameter>-N</parameter> en
      <parameter>-F</parameter>?</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>-N</parameter> first sees that any changes made
          since the locking by <parameter>-L</parameter> are merged into the
          main database file. After that, the database goes back into normal
          read/write mode and the temporary file is deleted.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>-F</parameter> only changes the state flag of the
          self-restored database to <quote>normal</quote>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>So you use:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>-N</parameter> after having
          <emphasis>made</emphasis> a copy/backup yourself (to reverse the
          <parameter>-L</parameter> issued earlier);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>-F</parameter> after having
          <emphasis>restored</emphasis> such a backup yourself.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>It is a bit unfortunate that the last switch should be called
        <parameter>-F</parameter> for Fixup. After all, it doesn't fix
        anything; it only <emphasis>unlocks</emphasis> the database. The
        <parameter>-N</parameter> (uNlock) flag on the other hand performs not
        only an unlock, but also a fixup (integration of mutations into the
        main file). But we'll have to live with that.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="nbackup-lock-unlock-extrainfo">
      <title>Under the hood</title>

      <para>Note: This section doesn't contain any necessary knowledge, but
      provides some extra information which could deepen your understanding of
      the various switches.</para>

      <!--These two orderedlists should really be procedures, but I want compact spacing!-->

      <para><command>nbackup <parameter>-L</parameter></command> does the
      following:</para>

      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Connect to the database;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Start a transaction;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Call ALTER DATABASE BEGIN BACKUP (this statement has been
          discussed in the <link linkend="nbackup-backups-workings">extra
          information on nbackup -B</link>);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Commit the transaction;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Disconnect from the database.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para><command>nbackup <parameter>-N</parameter></command> follows the
      same steps, but with <quote><database>...END BACKUP</database></quote>
      in step 3.</para>

      <para><command>nbackup <parameter>-F</parameter></command> works as
      follows:</para>

      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The restored database file is opened;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Within the file, the state flag is changed from locked
          (<constant>nbak_state_stalled</constant>) to normal
          (<constant>nbak_state_normal</constant>);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The file is closed again.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <note>
        <para>nbackup -F operates purely on file level and can therefore even
        be performed without a Firebird server running. Any
        <parameter>-U</parameter> or <parameter>-P</parameter> parameters
        added to the command will be completely ignored.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="nbackup-deltafile">
    <title>Setting the delta file</title>

    <para>By default, the delta file lives in the same directory as the
    database itself. It also has the same name as the database file, but with
    <filename class="extension">.delta</filename> appended. There is usually
    no reason to change this, but it can be done if need be – though not via
    <application>nbackup</application> itself. Make a connection to the
    database with any client that allows you to enter your own SQL statements
    and give the command:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <programlisting>alter database add difference file '<replaceable>path-and-filename</replaceable>'</programlisting>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The custom delta file specification is persistent in the database;
    it is stored in the system table <database>RDB$FILES</database>. To revert
    to the default behaviour, issue the following statement:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <programlisting>alter database drop difference file</programlisting>
    </blockquote>

    <note>
      <title>Notes</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you specify a bare file name with <database>ADD DIFFERENCE
          FILE</database>, the delta will likely <emphasis>not</emphasis> be
          created in the same directory as the database, but in the current
          directory as seen from the server. On Windows this may e.g. be the
          system directory. The same logic applies to relative paths.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The entire directory path must already exist. Firebird doesn't
          attempt to create any missing directories.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you want to change your custom delta specification, you
          must first <database>DROP</database> the old one and then
          <database>ADD</database> the new one.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </note>
  </section>

  <appendix id="nbackup-dochist">
    <title>Document history</title>

    <para>The exact file history is recorded in the <filename
    class="directory">manual</filename> module in our CVS tree; see <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=9028">http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=9028</ulink></para>

    <para><revhistory>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>

          <date>21 Oct 2005</date>

          <authorinitials>PV</authorinitials>

          <revdescription>
            <para>First edition.</para>
          </revdescription>
        </revision>

        <revision>
          <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>

          <date>1 Dec 2006</date>

          <authorinitials>PV</authorinitials>

          <revdescription>
            <para>Removed <quote>beta</quote> reference in edition info.
            Changed warning against specifying backup file names interactively
            with nbackup -R. Removed <quote>(or will be)</quote> from first
            sentence in Document History.</para>

            <para>Changed <literal>C:\Databases</literal> to
            <literal>C:\Data</literal> in the examples, just to keep the lines
            from running out of the shaded <sgmltag
            class="starttag">screen</sgmltag> areas in the PDF.</para>

            <para>Added section <citetitle>Setting the delta file</citetitle>,
            and changed section <citetitle>Read on?</citetitle>
            accordingly.</para>
          </revdescription>
        </revision>
      </revhistory></para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="nbackup-license">
    <title>License notice</title>

    <para>The contents of this Documentation are subject to the Public
    Documentation License Version 1.0 (the <quote>License</quote>); you may
    only use this Documentation if you comply with the terms of this License.
    Copies of the License are available at <ulink
    url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/pdfmanual/pdl.pdf">http://www.firebirdsql.org/pdfmanual/pdl.pdf</ulink>
    (PDF) and <ulink
    url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/manual/pdl.html">http://www.firebirdsql.org/manual/pdl.html</ulink>
    (HTML).</para>

    <para>The Original Documentation is titled <citetitle>Firebird's nbackup
    tool</citetitle>.</para>

    <para>The Initial Writer of the Original Documentation is: Paul
    Vinkenoog.</para>

    <para>Copyright (C) 2005, 2006. All Rights Reserved. Initial Writer
    contact: paulvink at users dot sourceforge dot net.</para>
  </appendix>
</article>