<?xml version = "1.0" encoding = "UTF-8"?>
<!-- For standalone validation, uncomment the following DOCTYPE declaration. -->
<!-- DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"> "file:../docs/docbookx/docbookx.dtd" -->
<preface><title>Docbook</title>
	<para>This manual is written using the <application>Docbook XML DTD</application> to allow authors to concentrate on structuring their subject matter logically without needing to worry about presentation format. David Jencks created the first basic Firebird Docmentation setup by taking the structure from the <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org"><emphasis>JBoss Project</emphasis></ulink>.</para>
	<para>This preface contains all necessary informations when you want to contribute to the Firebird Documentation Project. The XML transformation framework included in the <application>Firebird</application> CVS is entirely <application>Java</application> based and includes transformations to HTML (both web-like and printable) and PDF. Transformation control is conducted through the <application>Java</application> default build tool <application>Ant</application>.</para>
	<formalpara><title>Step by step description for setting up your environment</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Setup a working CVS environment and checkout the latest <application>Firebird</application> manual from the CVS tree (module = "manual").</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Download and install the latest <ulink url="http://java.sun.com"><emphasis>Sun JRE or JDK</emphasis></ulink>. Make sure you have the JAVA_HOME environment variable set to the directory where you have installed Java. Also add the "bin" directory to your search path.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Download and install your favorite XML editor for your platform. For Linux and Windows I recommend <ulink url="http://www.scintilla.org/SciTE.html"><emphasis>SciTE</emphasis></ulink> which supports syntax highlighting and easy browsing in XML files via folding. I also heard good things about <ulink url="http://www.jedit.org"><emphasis>JEdit</emphasis></ulink>. <application>jEdit</application> is a <application>Java</application> based editor which can be extended with a XML plugin to get sophisticated features like tag completion or syntax checking.</para>
				<note>When you choose a different editor make sure it fully supports Unicode (UTF-8).</note>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</formalpara>
	<formalpara><title>Firebird Documentation Project guidelines</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use tags to indicate the logical structure of the content, not to attempt to specify appearance. To reiterate, attempts to use the structural Docbook tags to influence presentation appearance are unlikely to produce useable results on all presentation platforms (HTML and PDF).</para>
				<para>In general you should use tags whenever possible. Have a look at the current documentation to get a ffeling of the availble tags and how they are used throughout the docs.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Do what you can to ensure you turn in a valid DocBook file.</para><para>If you notice any parser errors during documentation build, correct them to ensure XML validity. If you get absolutely stuck notify one of the documentation admins. The reviewers will correct any DocBook errors you create, but please try to reduce the number of errors.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>All <![CDATA[<chapter> and <section> ]]> tags must have an id attribute. The id must be all lower case, with dashes seperating words: <![CDATA[ <section id="migration-mssql"> ]]>.</para><para>This is very important since it allows other documentation writers to refer to your chapters and sections. For tables and figures you only need to put id's in if you wish to link to them.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>When referring to chapters, sections, code samples, figures and other parts of documentation use either <![CDATA[<link> or <xref>]]> element.</para><para><![CDATA[<xref> ]]> element is more powerful since it creates both link and link text. You should use it whenever possible.</para><para>For example: If there is a figure somewhere in the documentation <![CDATA[<figure id="mssql-to-firebird-data-types">]]> then using <![CDATA[<xref linkend="mssql-to-firebird-data-types"/>]]> creates both the link to that figure as well as link text. Link text is usually autogenerated (in case of figures - figure number) or assigned by the author of that link target.</para><para><![CDATA[<link>]]> element also creates links, but you can assign link text. For example:<![CDATA[<link linkend="mssql-to-firebird-data-types">mapping MSSQL to Firebird data types</link>]]></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use <![CDATA[<ulink>]]> element to create links to other URLs. For example:<![CDATA[<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org">OASIS, the home of Docbook</ulink>]]></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>When trying to decide between an ordered and unordered list, simply ask yourself the following question: "Does the order of the listed items matter?" or "If I change the order of the listed items, does that change the meaning of the list?". If you answer "No" to either question, then an unordered list is likely the logical choice.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</formalpara>
	<formalpara><title>Useful links</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Docbook DTD's are maintained by <ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org"><emphasis>OASIS</emphasis></ulink>, an independent consortium.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The principal maintainer of Docbook is <ulink url="http://www.nwalsh.com"><emphasis>Norman Walsh </emphasis></ulink>, a member of XSL working group, and Sun Microsystems employee.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>An introduction to the most used parts of Docbook can be found at <ulink url="http://www.caldera.de/~eric/crash-course/HTML"><emphasis>http://www.caldera.de/~eric/crash-course/HTML</emphasis></ulink>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A reference to Docbook is <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/html/docbook.html"><emphasis>http://www.docbook.org/tdg/html/docbook.html</emphasis></ulink>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A reference to XML and XSL technologies is <ulink url="http://xml.coverpages.org/"><emphasis>http://xml.coverpages.org/</emphasis></ulink>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/html/docbook.html"><emphasis>Norman Walsh and Leonard Muellner's Docbook handbook</emphasis></ulink> is available online.</para>
				<note>This book appears to be pre-XSL and describes DSSSL based formatting.</note>
				<para></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The used XSLT Parser <ulink url = "http://saxon.sourceforge.net"><emphasis>Saxon 6.5.2</emphasis></ulink>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The used build tool is <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant"><emphasis>Jakarta Ant 1.5.1</emphasis></ulink>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>For generating PDF output the <ulink url="http://xml.apache.org/fop"><emphasis>Formatting Objects Processor (FOP) 0.20.4</emphasis></ulink> was choosen.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</formalpara>
</preface>