<?xml version = "1.0" encoding = "UTF-8"?>
<preface>
	<title>Docbook</title>
    <para>This manual is written using the Docbook XML DTD to allow authors to concentrate on structuring their subject matter logically without needing to worry about presentation format.  The XML to presentation transformation structure is taken from that set up for the <ulink url = "http://www.jboss.org">
			<citetitle>JBoss project</citetitle>
		</ulink>.  The preface to the jboss manual includes an excellent summary of reasons to use Docbook.</para>
	<para>The XML transformation framework included in the firebird cvs is entirely java based and includes transformations to html (both web-like and printable) and pdf.  Transformation control is conducted through the build tool ant.  To compile presentation versions of the manual, open a terminal window in the manual/src/build directory and type ./build.sh (build.bat for windows users) to get a list of available compilation targets.  For example, ./build.sh defaulthtml generates the web html pressentation.  The results will be found in the manual/dist directory.</para>
	<para>The cvs project does not include an xml editor.  Although a plain text editor can be used, a much more suitable choice is emacs + psgml, available for both unix like and windows systems.</para>
	<para>Here is a collection of useful Docbook, tool, and emacs links.</para>
    <para><orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Docbook DTD's are maintained by OASIS, an independent consortium - <ulink url = "http://www.oasis-open.org">
			<citetitle>http://www.oasis-open.org</citetitle>
		</ulink>.</para>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The principal maintainer of Docbook is Normal Walsh <ulink url = "http://www.nwalsh.com">
			<citetitle>http://www.nwalsh.com</citetitle>
		</ulink> , a member of 
XSL working group, and Sun Microsystems employee.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>An introduction to the most used parts of Docbook can be found at  <ulink url = "http://www.caldera.de/~eric/crash-course/HTML">
			<citetitle>http://www.caldera.de/~eric/crash-course/HTML</citetitle>
		</ulink></para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A reference to Docbook is   <ulink url = "http://www.docbook.org/tdg/html/docbook.html">
			<citetitle>http://www.docbook.org/tdg/html/docbook.html</citetitle>
		</ulink></para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A reference to XML and XSL technologies is   <ulink url = "http://xml.coverpages.org/">
			<citetitle>http://xml.coverpages.org/</citetitle>
		</ulink></para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Norman Walsh and Leonard Muellner's Docbook book is available online at <ulink url = "http://www.docbook.org/tdg/html/docbook.html">
			<citetitle>http://www.docbook.org/tdg/html/docbook.html</citetitle> </ulink> Note that this book appears to be pre-XSL and describes DSSSL based formatting.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The java tools that perform the transformation are all from apache: the xml/xsl parsers and pdf generator (fop) are at <ulink url = "http://xml.apache.org">
			<citetitle>http://xml.apache.org</citetitle> </ulink>
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The ant build tool is at <ulink url = "http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">
			<citetitle>http://jakarta.apache.org/ant</citetitle> </ulink>
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Emacs normally comes with linux systems, for windows visit <ulink url = "http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/windows">
			<citetitle>http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/windows</citetitle> </ulink>. it is not clear to me if this includes psgml, the sgml/xml editor.  I could only get psgml to work with emacs, trying with xemacs failed completely.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Good instructions for the sgml/xml plugin for emacs includes  <ulink url = "http://www.snee.com/bob/sgmlfree/emcspsgm.html">
			<citetitle>http://www.snee.com/bob/sgmlfree/emcspsgm.html</citetitle> </ulink>  The pdf chapter from his book is expecially useful.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A shorter reference for the sgml/xml plugin for emacs is  <ulink url = "http://www.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/doc/texi/psgml.html">
			<citetitle>http://www.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/doc/texi/psgml.html</citetitle> </ulink>
		</para>
	</listitem>
    </orderedlist>
</para>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Docbook documentation guidelines</title>
		<para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>Use tags to indicate the logical structure of the content, not to attempt to specify appearance.</para> 
		<para>To reiterate, attempts to use the structural Docbook tags to influence presentation appearance are unlikely to produce useable results on all presentation platforms (html and pdf).</para> 
                  
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		<para>Do what you can to ensure you turn in a valid DocBook file.</para> 

       		<para>If you notice any parser errors during documentation build, correct them to ensure XML validity. If you get absolutely stuck notify
	        one of the documentation leads. The reviewers will correct any DocBook errors you create, but please try to reduce the number of errors.
		</para>
	    <para>Constructing valid Docbook xml is much easier with the use of a xml-dtd aware editor such as emacs + psgml.</para>
		</listitem>	
		<listitem>
                <para>All <![CDATA[<chapter> and major <section> ]]> tags must have an id attribute. The id must be all lower case, with dashes seperating 
		words: <![CDATA[ <section id="migration-mssql"> ]]>
		</para>

		<para>This is very important since it allows other documentation writers to refer to your chapters and sections</para>	
		</listitem>	
		<listitem>
		<para>
               	When trying to decide between an ordered and unordered list, simply ask yourself the following question: "Does the order of the 
		listed items matter?" or "If I change the order of the listed items, does that change the meaning of the list?". If you answer "No" 
		to either question, then an unordered list is likely the logical choice.</para>
		</listitem>
                
                <listitem>
		<para>
		When referring to chapters, sections, code samples, figures and other parts of documentation use either <![CDATA[<link> or <xref>]]> 
		element. </para>

		<para><![CDATA[<xref> ]]> element is more powerful since it creates both link and link text. You should use it whenever possible.</para>
		<para>For example: If there is a figure somewhere in the documentation <![CDATA[<figure id="mssql-to-firebird-data-types">]]> then using 
		<![CDATA[<xref linkend="mssql-to-firebird-data-types"/>]]> creates both the link to that figure as well as link text. Link text is usually
		autogenerated (in case of figures - figure number) or assigned by the author of that link target.</para>
                  
                <para><![CDATA[<link>]]> element also creates links, but you assign link text.  For example:
		<![CDATA[<link linkend="mssql-to-firebird-data-types">mapping MSSQL to Firebird data types</link>]]></para>
			
                </listitem>

		<listitem>
		<para>Use <![CDATA[<ulink>]]> element to create links to other URLs. For example:
		<![CDATA[<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org">OASIS, the home of Docbook</ulink>]]>
		</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>	
	</para>
	</formalpara>
	
</preface>