<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- For standalone validation, uncomment the following DOCTYPE declaration. -->
<!-- DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"> "file:../docs/docbookx/docbookx.dtd" -->
<!-- book id="usingfirebird" -->
<chapter id="ufb-cs">
  <title>About Clients and Servers</title>

  <para>In this chapter we take a look at the essential pieces of
  client/server systems as they are implemented in Firebird and examine how
  applications interact with the client and server.</para>

  <section id="ufb-cs-clients">
    <title>What is a Firebird client?</title>

    <para>A Firebird client is a program, usually written in a high-level
    language such as C, C++, Delphi, Java, PHP or Perl, that provides end-user
    access to the features and tools of the Firebird database management
    system and to data stored in databases. The
    <application>isql</application> interactive SQL utility is an example of a
    client application.</para>

    <para>In the client/server model, applications never touch the database
    physically. Any application process converses with the server through the
    Firebird client library which resides on the client workstation. It
    surfaces a programming interface of function call structures known as the
    Firebird API. This client library must be installed on every user's
    workstation. Generally, other layers are also involved in the interface
    between the application program and the Firebird client, providing generic
    or application-language-specific mechanisms for populating and calling the
    API functions.</para>

    <para>Firebird clients typically reside on remote workstations and connect
    to a Firebird server running on a host node in a network. Firebird also
    supports local connection, that is, a client application, the Firebird
    client library and the Firebird server all executing on the same physical
    box.</para>

    <para>Firebird clients need not run on the same type of hardware and/or
    operating system as the server they connect to. It is quite common to have
    a number of Windows 98 or XP workstations talking to a server that runs
    under Windows NT, 2000 or 2003, or any of several flavours of UNIX or
    Linux.</para>

    <figure id="ufb-cs-fig-csmodel">
      <title>The Firebird client/server model</title>

      <graphic fileref="images/ClientServer.png" format="PNG" />
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="ufb-cs-clientlib">
    <title>The Firebird client library</title>

    <para>The Firebird client library provides an Application Programming
    Interface (API) with functions for connecting to servers and working with
    databases. The library functions communicate with the server(s) using a
    dedicated Firebird client/server protocol that sits on top of the general
    network protocol provided by the OS.</para>

    <para>All client applications and middleware must use the API in some way
    to access Firebird databases. The Firebird API is backwardly compatible
    with the InterBase API. The <citetitle>InterBase API Guide</citetitle>
    (available at <ulink
    url="http://www.ibphoenix.com/downloads/60ApiGuide.zip">http://www.ibphoenix.com/downloads/60ApiGuide.zip</ulink>)
    contains extensive documentation on the use the API in applications.
    Additional features available in the Firebird API are documented in the
    Firebird release notes.</para>

    <section id="ufb-cs-clientlib-filenames">
      <title>Client filenames</title>

      <para>The Firebird client library files are <filename
      class="libraryfile">fbclient.dll</filename> (Windows), <filename
      class="libraryfile">libfbclient.so</filename> (Linux network client) and
      <filename class="libraryfile">libfbembed.so</filename> (Linux local
      client with embedded engine, Classic only). In order not to break
      certain existing applications, a copy of <filename
      class="libraryfile">fbclient.dll</filename> with the old name <filename
      class="libraryfile">gds32.dll</filename> can be installed on Windows
      machines. On Linux, legacy <filename
      class="libraryfile">libgds*</filename> symlinks are installed
      automatically.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ufb-cs-server">
    <title>The server</title>

    <para>The Firebird server is a program that runs on a machine with which
    client workstations can communicate by way of a network. Clients connect
    to databases physically located on this server host machine. The same
    machine that hosts the executing Firebird server process must host the
    Firebird databases in its own storage space. Only the server process has
    direct, filesystem-level access to the database files. The server is fully
    network-enabled, serving multiple connections simultaneously, in response
    to requests from other nodes in the network. If the network runs under
    TCP/IP protocol, the scope of the network is virtually limitless.</para>

    <para>In the Superserver architecture, the server process is
    multi-threaded. In Classic, a new process is started for each
    connection.</para>

    <section id="ufb-cs-server-tasks">
      <title>Server tasks</title>

      <para>The server's job is to</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>regulate access by transactions to individual sets of
          data;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ensure that each transaction gets and keeps a consistent view
          of the permanently stored data which it has requested through the
          client;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>receive requests to modify or delete a row and either:</para>

          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>grant a transaction exclusive write access to the row,
              or</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>deny access if another transaction already has a write
              pending;</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>maintain the statistics for each database;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>maintain and refer to the metadata for each database, in order
          to manage transactions, data and
          <quote>house-cleaning</quote>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Clients' requests result in the server performing tasks such
      as</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>creating new databases;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>creating new data structures inside databases;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>validating and compiling source code for procedures;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>searching tables for data matching provided criteria;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>collating, sorting and tabulating sets of data;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>passing sets of data back to the requesting client;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>modifying the values of data;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>inserting new data into tables;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>removing (deleting) data;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>executing compiled procedures;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>routing messages to clients.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-server-multiple">
      <title>Multiple servers</title>

      <para>Starting at version 1.5, you can have multiple Firebird servers
      running on the same machine. Firebird 1.5 servers can also coexist with
      a Firebird 1.0 or InterBase server. Some extra configuration steps are
      required though.</para>

      <para>One thing to be aware of is that Firebird
      1.5.<replaceable>n</replaceable> under Windows needs the
      <parameter>CreateInternalWindow</parameter> configuration parameter to
      be set to 0 in order to run multiple servers. As a side effect, the
      local connection protocol is disabled (you can still connect to local
      databases via <systemitem class="systemname">localhost</systemitem>
      though). This limitation no longer exists in Firebird 2, and the
      <parameter>CreateInternalWindow</parameter> parameter has been removed
      in that version.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-server-filenames">
      <title>Server filenames</title>

      <para>Server binaries on Windows are called
      <filename>fbserver.exe</filename> (Superserver) and
      <filename>fb_inet_server.exe</filename> (Classic). On Linux, the same
      names are used, but without the <filename
      class="extension">.exe</filename> extension.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ufb-cs-embedded">
    <title>Client and server combined: Firebird Embedded Server</title>

    <titleabbrev>Firebird Embedded Server</titleabbrev>

    <section id="ufb-cs-embedded-windows">
      <title>Embedded server on Windows</title>

      <para>The Windows <firstterm>Embedded Server</firstterm> is a
      Superserver engine plus client rolled into one library, called <filename
      class="libraryfile">fbembed.dll</filename>. It is available as a
      separate download package. The embedded server (introduced with Firebird
      1.5) was specifically designed to facilitate deployment of applications
      that ship with a Firebird server included. Installation is just a matter
      of unpacking the DLL and a few other files to the desired location. The
      security database is not used at all: anyone can connect to any
      database, as long as the user running the application has
      filesystem-level access rights to the database(s) in question.</para>

      <para>You can have multiple embedded servers running at the same time,
      and you can have multiple apps connecting to the same embedded server.
      Having a regular server already running isn't a problem either. However,
      an embedded server locks a database file for its own exclusive use after
      successful connection. This means that you cannot access the same
      database from multiple embedded server processes simultaneously (or from
      any other servers, once an embedded server has locked the file).</para>

      <para>The embedded server has no facility to accept any network
      connections. Only true local access is possible, with a connect string
      that doesn't contain a host name (not even <systemitem
      class="systemname">localhost</systemitem>).</para>

      <para>Needless to say, this is not for your regular client-server
      database usage, as it bypasses a lot of security features. It's using
      Firebird as a desktop database system.</para>

      <note>
        <para>A Firebird embedded server DLL can also be used as a network
        client. That is, if a regular Firebird server is listening for
        connections on the target computer, you can connect to databases on
        that system using a network-style connect string like
        <systemitem>inca:C:\School\Databases\Pupils.fdb</systemitem>.</para>

        <para>This also implies that if a regular server is active on your
        local computer, you can connect to local databases through that
        regular server with your embedded server as a client using the
        <quote><systemitem>localhost:</systemitem></quote> syntax. This may
        seem contradictory to what has been said before about the absence of
        network support, but bear in mind that if you connect to <systemitem
        class="systemname">localhost</systemitem> (or any other host), you are
        not using the embedded <emphasis>server</emphasis>; you're only using
        the <emphasis>client</emphasis> part of <filename
        class="libraryfile">fbembed.dll</filename> to connect to another
        server. You'll have to provide a valid user name and password for this
        to work.</para>

        <!--This used to go wrong in 2.0 with:
  Statement failed, SQLCODE = -923
  connection rejected by remote interface
...but that was probably in a beta or RC. It works fine in 2.0 final.-->
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-embedded-deploy">
      <title>Embedded server deployment</title>

      <para>First, download the Embedded server kit from SourceForge. It's
      typically named
      <filename>Firebird-<replaceable>n.n.n.xxxx</replaceable>_embed_win32.zip</filename>,
      with <replaceable>n.n.n.xxxx</replaceable> the Firebird version and
      build number.</para>

      <para>After unzipping, you'll find the embedded server <filename
      class="libraryfile">fbembed.dll</filename> in the root directory of the
      package, along with some other files. Additionally, there are three
      subdirectories <filename class="directory">doc</filename>, <filename
      class="directory">intl</filename> and <filename
      class="directory">udf</filename>.</para>

      <para>To make your application work with the embedded server:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Copy <filename class="libraryfile">fbembed.dll</filename> into
          your application directory. Rename it to <filename
          class="libraryfile">fbclient.dll</filename> or <filename
          class="libraryfile">gds32.dll</filename>, depending on what your
          application expects as a Firebird client filename. Many applications
          still look for <filename class="libraryfile">gds32.dll</filename>.
          Firebird command-line tools like <application>isql</application> and
          <application>gbak </application>– which you can also run against the
          embedded server – want <filename
          class="libraryfile">fbclient.dll</filename>. You can also make
          copies with both names.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Also copy <filename>firebird.msg</filename> and <filename
          class="libraryfile">ib_util.dll</filename> to your application
          directory. Copy <filename>aliases.conf</filename> if your
          application uses aliases to connect. The configuration file
          <filename>firebird.conf</filename> is only needed if you want to
          change the Firebird root directory; this will be discussed
          later.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>For Firebird 2 or higher, copy the <filename
          class="libraryfile">icu*.dll</filename> libraries too.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>From the <filename class="directory">intl</filename> and
          <filename class="directory">udf</filename> directories, copy
          whatever your application or databases may need to same-named
          folders under your application directory.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Now if you run your application it will use the embedded
          server DLL to connect to any local database you desire,
          <emphasis>provided that the Windows user who runs the application
          has sufficient access rights to the database file(s) in
          question!</emphasis> Any combination of user name and password is
          accepted, as long as neither is an empty string (a space is OK
          though).</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>The most important benefit of all this is that you can easily pack
      the Firebird Embedded files with your application and have them
      installed or unzipped at your users' computers without having to perform
      a separate Firebird install there (with all the additional worries of
      sufficient privileges, possible interference with already present
      Firebird or InterBase servers, etc. etc.). You can also have several
      embedded server versions (say 1.5.3 and 2.0) running on the same
      computer without the need for special configuration steps to keep them
      out of each other's way.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Please note that, even though the security database is bypassed,
        SQL privileges – specified in the database itself – still apply: if
        you connect as Firebird user <database>ZIGGY</database> and
        <database>ZIGGY</database> doesn't have access to table
        <database>STARDUST</database>, you won't get into that table. This is
        not as worrying as it seems, because you can connect as any user you
        like, including <database>SYSDBA</database>, with a dummy
        password.</para>
      </note>

      <section>
        <title>Placing the Firebird files elsewhere</title>

        <para>By default, Firebird Embedded Server considers the folder that
        <filename class="libraryfile">fbembed.dll</filename> lives in (under
        whatever name) as the Firebird root directory. In the setup described
        above, this is your application directory. You may want to place the
        Firebird files somewhere else, so as not to clutter your application
        directory. To do this, you must tell the server where to look for
        them.</para>

        <para>Let's say you want the Firebird files to reside in a folder
        called <filename class="directory">D:\FbEmbedded</filename>:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Copy <filename>firebird.conf</filename> to your application
            directory and edit the <parameter>RootDirectory</parameter>
            parameter like this:</para>

            <blockquote>
              <programlisting>RootDirectory = D:\FbEmbedded</programlisting>
            </blockquote>

            <para>Alternatively, you may set the <envar>FIREBIRD</envar>
            environment variable to achieve the same. If both the
            configuration file parameter and the <envar>FIREBIRD</envar> envar
            are present, the latter takes precedence. <emphasis
            role="bold">Warning:</emphasis> the <envar>FIREBIRD</envar>
            environment variable will be picked up by every Firebird server on
            the system (embedded or not) at startup, and override their
            registry settings and configuration file parameters. So use it
            with care, if at all.<!--Still true for Firebird 2? YES, but it's Bad...--></para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Copy/move the following items to <filename
            class="directory">D:\FbEmbedded</filename>:</para>

            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                <para><filename>firebird.msg</filename></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><filename>aliases.conf</filename> (if used)</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>the <filename class="directory">intl</filename> and
                <filename class="directory">udf</filename> subdirs plus
                contents (in so far as needed)</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>The following files however <emphasis>must</emphasis> be
            left in your application's directory:</para>

            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                <para>Any and all copies/renames of <filename
                class="libraryfile">fbembed.dll</filename></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><filename>firebird.conf</filename></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><filename
                class="libraryfile">ib_util.dll</filename></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>for Firebird 2 and up: the <filename
                class="libraryfile">icu*.dll</filename> libraries</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <!--Nickolay sez (13-11-2003):
"Windows client library is thread-safe, can do
"IPSERVER (old W32 local), XNET (AFAIR, $xnet prefix, undocumented),
"TCP/IP and named pipes connections.
"
"libfbembed.so is thread-unsafe, can do TCP/IP connections and local
"connections via embedded engine.
"
"libfbclient.so is thread-safe, but can do only TCP/IP connections.

Jim sez (23-5-2004)
"Small note of nomenclature.  The thing that executes database commands 
"is an engine.  The things that listens to the network or IPC channel is 
"a server.  The original engine didn't care whether it was embedded or 
"part of a server.  Neither does the Vulcan engine.  The pre-Vulcan 
"firebird engines care intensely.
-->
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-embedded-linux">
      <title>Embedded server on Linux?</title>

      <para>The Linux Classic server comes with a client library called
      <filename class="libraryfile">libfbembed.so</filename> which is used for
      local connections. This library contains a full Firebird engine, which
      explains why it's so much bigger than the Superserver client library.
      Local connections through this library are part of the user application
      process, not of a separate server process. Therefore, the user of the
      library must have filesystem-level access rights to the database – just
      as with Windows Embedded. So yes, this is a true embedded server.</para>

      <para>There are also some differences. First, Linux Classic doesn't
      require an exclusive lock on the databases it opens. The database
      remains accessible from other clients. A further – very important –
      difference is that Linux Classic validates every login against the
      security database: no connections with phony user names or passwords
      here! Finally, you can't just ship <filename
      class="libraryfile">libfbembed.so</filename> with your application and
      use it to connect to local databases. Under Linux, you always need a
      properly installed server, be it Classic or Super.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ufb-cs-appdev">
    <title>Application development</title>

    <para>Once a database has been created and populated, its information can
    be accessed through a client application. Some applications – such as the
    Firebird <application>isql</application> tool, <application>EMS SQL
    Manager</application>, <application>IB_SQL</application>,
    <application>IBAccess, <application>Database
    Workbench</application></application>,
    <application>FlameRobin</application> and
    <application>IBOConsole</application> – provide the capability to query
    data interactively and to create new metadata.</para>

    <para>Any application developed as a user interface to one or more
    Firebird databases will use the SQL query language, both to define the
    sets of data that can be stored and to pass requests to the server about
    rows it wants to update, insert into or delete from. SQL statements also
    convey the values which the application wants to be applied to those
    rows.</para>

    <para>Firebird implements a set of SQL syntaxes which have a high degree
    of compliance with the recognised SQL-92 and SQL-99 standards. The
    Firebird API provides complete structures for packaging SQL statements and
    the associated parameters, as well as for receiving the results.</para>

    <section id="ufb-cs-appdev-embed">
      <title>Embedded SQL in Firebird applications</title>

      <para>Firebird provides the capability to embed SQL statements in
      applications written in C/C++ and some other programming languages. The
      code is then passed through <emphasis>gpre</emphasis>, the
      pre-processor, which substitutes the embedded SQL statements with
      equivalent host language code that calls functions in Firebird's client
      API library. The gpre pre-processor generates a file that the host
      language compiler can compile.</para>

      <para>A special, extra subset of SQL-like source commands is available
      for this style of application, which are pre-processed into internal
      macro calls to the API. Known as Embedded SQL (ESQL), it provides a
      simpler, high-level language syntax for the programmer, that gpre can
      interpret and re-code according to the more complex structure of the
      equivalent API calls.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The <citetitle>InterBase Embedded SQL Guide</citetitle> (<ulink
        url="http://www.ibphoenix.com/downloads/60EmbedSQL.zip">http://www.ibphoenix.com/downloads/60EmbedSQL.zip</ulink>)
        provides extensive documentation on this subject.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-appdev-stat-dyn">
      <title>Predefined vs. dynamic queries</title>

      <para>Some queries have to be run in exactly the same form every time
      they are needed. Queries like this are good candidates for embedding in
      the host language and pre-processing by gpre. The pre-processor turns
      them into API function calls, giving a somewhat better performance than
      SQL that has to be interpreted at runtime.</para>

      <para>But many applications need to build queries that are at least
      partially dependent on information provided by the user – freely entered
      in a text box, or selected from a list of options. This is called
      <firstterm>Dynamic SQL</firstterm> or <firstterm>DSQL</firstterm>; that
      is, SQL code whose form is not (or not exactly) known at design time.
      DSQL can be embedded and preprocessed too, but some additional
      requirements and restrictions apply. More on this – again – in the
      <citetitle>InterBase Embedded SQL Guide</citetitle>.</para>

      <!--Instead of elaborating on component interfaces is this section, shouldn't we confine
ourselves to a few concise remark here, and move the bulk of the following paras to the
sections on components?-->

      <para>Delphi and C++ data access components provide properties and
      methods to analyse and parse DSQL request statements and manage the
      results passed back. Applications that use ODBC or other generic
      interfaces always work with DSQL statements, even if the user doesn't
      always see them. Query-by-example and other visual query tools for
      instance provide the user with a convenient, easy to use, and often
      <quote>SQL-free</quote> interface to extract, modify or delete data from
      the database. Yet the underlying code translates the user's input into
      DSQL statements, which are subsequently passed to the ODBC (or other)
      layer.</para>

      <para>Component interfaces provide methods and properties for building
      and preparing SQL template statements, allowing you to use placeholders
      for value criteria. At run-time, the application supplies input
      parameters of the appropriate data type to complete the statement.
      Provision is made also for retrieving output parameters from statements
      that return results after they are executed.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Of course the use of data access components isn't limited to
        dynamic SQL. You can also store static SQL strings – known at design
        time – in them.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-appdev-rad">
      <title>RAD environments and component suites</title>

      <para>With the rise of rapid application development (RAD) tools in the
      past decade, the encapsulation of the API functions in suites of
      components presents a variety of attractive application development
      options for Firebird developers.</para>

      <section>
        <title>The Borland Database Engine (BDE)</title>

        <para>Borland markets <quote>enterprise versions</quote> of a number
        of integrated development tools – Delphi, Kylix, C++Builder, JBuilder
        and some older products – which can use the proprietary Borland
        Database Engine and native SQL Links InterBase drivers as a
        <quote>black box</quote> middleware layer to make InterBase and,
        latterly, Firebird databases behave like desktop databases. BDE
        version 5.2 and its associated InterBase driver, which first shipped
        with Delphi 6E, supports both Firebird and InterBase version 6,
        although it has known bugs affecting the Dialect 3 date and time data
        types.</para>

        <para>Because the BDE's purpose is to surface a generic,
        database-vendor-independent, client-centered data access layer to the
        IDE tools, it flattens out the differences between a wide range of
        different database systems. Hence, it limits the capability of
        applications to exploit the best features of Firebird, particularly
        multiple transactions per connection, control of transaction aging and
        concurrency control.</para>

        <para>The BDE can be useful where you need to develop an application
        that might be used with a choice of back-ends, of which Firebird is
        only one. Be warned however that people have reported problems with
        Firebird database access via the BDE, and these are likely to increase
        in number and severity as Firebird continues to move further away from
        InterBase.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>SQLDirect</title>

        <para>SQLDirect is a shareware, lightweight replacement for the BDE.
        It supports Firebird at least up to and including version 1.5. Visit
        <ulink
        url="http://www.sqldirect-soft.com">http://www.sqldirect-soft.com</ulink>
        for more information and free trial versions.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>DBExpress and Datasnap</title>

        <para>DBExpress and Datasnap were introduced in later versions of the
        Borland tools to provide alternative generic interfaces to databases.
        They replace the BDE by moving its functionality into expanded native
        drivers for supported databases. Like the BDE, they do not support
        multiple concurrent transactions. They are of especial use where a
        data interface is required that is independent of the idiosyncrasies
        of different database management systems. The InterBase native drivers
        should provide adequate support for Firebird databases where
        optimising client/server performance is not high among the
        objectives.<!--Is that still the case?--></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Direct-to-API Components</title>

        <para>In response to the shortcomings of the BDE, a number of
        component suites have become available for Delphi and Borland
        C++Builder that bypass the BDE layer completely and encapsulate the
        Firebird API directly:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>IBObjects</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>IB Objects is a rich set of visual and non-visual database
              components that has been stable since 1997. It offers two
              BDE-free suites for data access; one compatible with the native
              Delphi and C++ Builder TDatasource and visual controls, the
              other completely independent of the Delphi data access
              architecture and supplied with its own visual controls.</para>

              <para><ulink
              url="http://www.ibobjects.com">http://www.ibobjects.com</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>FIBPlus</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>FIBPlus is another well-known and stable suite for Delphi
              and BCB. Developed from Gregory Deatz's FreeIBComponents suite,
              it offers a connectivity based on TDataset. It doesn't include
              any visual components, but it can work perfectly together with
              the Borland visual database classes, as well as with third-party
              visual data-aware components.</para>

              <para><ulink
              url="http://www.devrace.com/en/fibplus/">http://www.devrace.com/en/fibplus/</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>ZeosLib</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>ZeosLib is a set of free, open-source database
              connectivity components for Delphi, FreePascal/Lazarus, Kylix
              and C++ Builder. It supports a number of database systems,
              including Firebird. Because the ZeosLib components are based on
              TDataset, you can use them together with the Borland visual
              database controls.</para>

              <para><ulink
              url="http://zeos.firmos.at/portal.php">http://zeos.firmos.at/portal.php</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>IBX (InterBase Express)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>IBX was also developed from the FreeIBComponents. Its
              TDataset-based data access components were purchased for
              developing as a proprietary product by Borland. Components
              encapsulating the new Services API were added. It was left
              unfinished in 1999. The IBX source code was opened under the
              InterBase Public License in 2000 and it continues to be
              developed as an open source project. <!--Really?-->Borland
              distributes versions of IBX with some Delphi, Kylix and C++
              Builder versions.</para>

              <caution>
                <para>Since InterBase and Firebird are diverging more and
                more, and Borland has (quite understandably) no intention to
                keep IBX Firebird-compatible, you should probably
                <emphasis>not</emphasis> use it with Firebird versions 1.5 and
                higher (although most features will still be
                supported).</para>
              </caution>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>UIB (Unified InterBase)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a set of non-visual components for Delphi, BCB,
              Kylix, Lazarus and FPC, supporting Firebird, InterBase and
              Yaffil. A ready-to-use SQL monitor (Windows only) is also
              available:</para>

              <para><ulink
              url="http://www.progdigy.com/modules.php?name=UIB">http://www.progdigy.com/modules.php?name=UIB</ulink></para>

              <para>The UIB components are also contained in the JEDI Visual
              Component Library (JVCL):</para>

              <para><ulink
              url="http://homepages.borland.com/jedi/jvcl/">http://homepages.borland.com/jedi/jvcl/</ulink></para>

              <para>Both UIB and the JVCL are freely available open-source
              products.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-appdev-other">
      <title>Other connectivity components and drivers</title>

      <section>
        <title>Microsoft <quote>open connectivity</quote></title>

        <para>Third-party ODBC and OLE-DB drivers are available for Windows
        programmers using Microsoft and other vendors' programming tools. The
        Firebird ODBC driver development page is at <ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=devel&amp;sub=odbc">http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=devel&amp;sub=odbc</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Java</title>

        <para>A pure Java Type 4 JDBC driver called Jaybird is developed
        within the Firebird project. Jaybird is compliant with both the new
        JCA standard for application server connections to enterprise
        information systems and the established JDBC standard.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Firebird has abandoned re-implementation of the Borland
          InterClient and Interserver platform-independent client
          layers.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Official documentation and download links for Jaybird are at
        <ulink
        url="http://jaybirdwiki.firebirdsql.org/">http://jaybirdwiki.firebirdsql.org</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>.NET</title>

        <para>The Firebird ADO.NET Data Provider, developed as a Firebird
        subproject, re-implements the client API functions in C#.
        Consequently, .NET developers only need the data provider to talk to a
        Firebird server; there's no need to install a regular Firebird client.
        Home page: <ulink
        url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=devel&amp;sub=netprovider">http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=devel&amp;sub=netprovider</ulink>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-appdev-api">
      <title>API applications</title>

      <para>The Firebird client program supports two discrete application
      programming interface (API) modules. The most important is the core API,
      through which all database work is performed. A much smaller API module,
      the Services API, provides functions for accessing various command-line
      and other utilities from application programs. Developers can write
      high-level programming or script language applications that populate the
      data structures and call the API functions directly.</para>

      <section id="ufb-cs-appdev-coreapi">
        <title>The Firebird core API</title>

        <para>Programmers who want to use the core API have to write code for
        allocating and populating the data structures that provide the
        communication layer between the client library and the server.
        Interactive SQL clients, component interfaces and embedded SQL
        <quote>hide</quote> these structures from the programmer by
        encapsulating them in their own higher level interfaces. Writing code
        that calls the API functions directly can be more powerful and
        flexible, with the following benefits:</para>

        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Memory allocation control</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>No precompiling necessary</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Access to transaction handles and options</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Full access to error messages</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="ufb-cs-appdev-coreapi-funcs">
        <title>Core API function categories</title>

        <para>Based on their operation targets, we can divide the API
        functions into the following categories:</para>

        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Database connection control</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Transaction control</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Statement execution</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Blob functions</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Array functions</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Security functions</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Informational functions</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Type conversions</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="ufb-cs-appdev-servicesapi">
        <title>The Services API</title>

        <para>The opened InterBase 6.0 code from which Firebird was developed
        surfaced for the first time an application programming interface (API)
        providing a function call interface to certain server activities such
        as backup/restore, statistics and user management. Many of these calls
        provide programming interfaces to the code in the command-line tools.
        A few lower-level server functions are included as well, some of which
        overlap functions already available in the core API.</para>

        <important>
          <para>Before Firebird 1.5, the Services API was only available with
          Firebird Superserver. Support for the entire Services API in Classic
          Server versions was completed in Firebird 1.5.1.</para>
        </important>

        <para>Borland's InterBase Express (IBX) components include a subset –
        known as the Service components – encapsulating access to services API
        calls from some versions of their Delphi, Kylix and C++Builder
        development environments. Be aware however that IBX does not
        officially support Firebird. The higher your Firebird version, the
        more chance of incompatibilities and errors if you use IBX.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>IBPP</title>

        <para>IBPP is a C++ interface to the Firebird API. It is a class
        library written in <quote>pure</quote> C++ and hence not dependent on
        any specific programming environment, component set or even OS. You
        can use it anywhere you want Firebird connectivity in your C++
        programs.</para>

        <para>IBPP was created and is maintained independently of the Firebird
        project. It is available for free and comes with its own very liberal
        license. The IBPP home page is at <ulink
        url="http://www.ibpp.org">http://www.ibpp.org</ulink>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ufb-cs-serverprog">
    <title>Server-side programming</title>

    <para>Among Firebird's powerful features for dynamic client/server
    application programming is its capability to precompile source code on the
    server, storing the object code right inside the database in most cases.
    Such procedures and functions are executed completely on the server,
    optionally returning values or data sets to the client application.
    Firebird provides three styles of server-side programming capability:
    stored procedures, triggers and user-defined functions (UDFs).</para>

    <section id="ufb-cs-serverprog-storedprocs">
      <title>Stored procedures</title>

      <para>Firebird's procedural language (PSQL) implements extensions to its
      SQL language, providing conditional logic, flow control structures,
      exception handling (both built-in and user-defined), local variables, an
      event mechanism and the capability to accept input arguments of almost
      any type supported by Firebird. It implements a powerful flow control
      structure for processing cursors which can output a dataset directly to
      client memory without the need to create temporary tables. Such
      procedures are called from the client with a <database>SELECT</database>
      statement and are known to developers as <firstterm>selectable stored
      procedures</firstterm>. Procedures that don't return a dataset (although
      they may return result variables) are called <firstterm>executable
      stored procedures</firstterm>; they are called with <database>EXECUTE
      PROCEDURE</database>.</para>

      <para>Stored procedures can call other stored procedures and can be
      recursive. All stored procedure execution, including selection of data
      sets from procedures and embedded calls to other procedures, is under
      the control of the single transaction that calls it. Accordingly, the
      work of a stored procedure call will be cancelled totally if the client
      rolls back the transaction.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-serverprog-triggers">
      <title>Triggers</title>

      <para>Triggers are special procedures created for specific tables, for
      automatic execution during the process of committing DML work to the
      server. Any table can have any number of triggers to be executed before
      or after inserts, updates and deletions. Execution order is determined
      by a position parameter in the trigger's declaration. Triggers have some
      PSQL extensions not available to regular stored procedures or to dynamic
      SQL, most notably the context variables <database>OLD</database> and
      <database>NEW</database> which, when prefixed to a column identifier,
      provide references to the existing and requested new values of the
      column. Triggers can call stored procedures, but not other
      triggers.</para>

      <para>Work performed by triggers will be rolled back if the transaction
      that prompted them is rolled back.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-serverprog-limitations">
      <title>PSQL limitations</title>

      <para>Stored procedures and triggers can not start transactions, since
      they are under transaction control themselves.</para>

      <para>PSQL does not allow the execution of DDL (Data Definition
      Language) statements: it is strictly meant to operate on
      <emphasis>data</emphasis>, not on the structure of your database.
      Although you can circumvent this limitation with the <database>EXECUTE
      STATEMENT</database> syntax introduced in Firebird 1.5, it is generally
      considered unwise to do so. (Just because we give you a spade, it
      doesn't mean that you have to dig your own grave.)</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ufb-cs-serverprog-udf">
      <title>User-defined functions</title>

      <para>By design, in order to preserve its small footprint, Firebird
      comes with a very modest arsenal of internally-defined (native) data
      transformation functions. Developers can write their own very precise
      functions in familiar host-language code such as C/C++, Pascal or Object
      Pascal to accept arguments and return a single result. Once an external
      function – UDF – is declared to a database, it becomes available as a
      valid SQL function to applications, stored procedures and
      triggers.</para>

      <para>Firebird supplies two libraries of ready-to-use UDFs: <systemitem
      class="library">ib_udf</systemitem> and <systemitem
      class="library">fbudf</systemitem>. Firebird looks for UDF libraries in
      its own <filename class="directory">UDF</filename> subdirectory or in
      other directories specified in the Firebird configuration file. In
      Firebird 1.5 and upward this is done with the
      <parameter>UDFAccess</parameter> parameter; in earlier versions with
      <parameter>external_function_directory</parameter>.</para>

      <note>
        <para>In versions prior to 1.5 the <systemitem
        class="library">fbudf</systemitem> library is only available on
        Windows.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ufb-cs-multidb">
    <title>Multi-database applications</title>

    <!--Should logically be a subsection of "Application development"-->

    <para>Firebird applications can work with several databases at the same
    time through the client library – something that not all relational
    database systems allow. Tables from separate databases can not be joined
    to return linked sets, but cursors can be used to combine
    information.</para>

    <para>If consistency across database boundaries is required, Firebird can
    manage output sets from querying multiple databases inside a single
    transaction. Firebird implements automatic two-phase commit when data
    changes occur, to ensure that changes cannot be committed in one database
    if changes in another database, within the same transaction context, are
    rolled back or lost through a network failure.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>