<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../../tools/docbook-dtd/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ufb-preface">
  <title>About this book</title>

  <section id="ufb-preface-wip">
    <title>Work in progress!</title>

    <para>This document is a work in progress. The Firebird documenters – all
    volunteers who work on this project in their spare time – will publish
    more chapters as they go along. As we are but a few, the pace is pretty
    slow. However, the few chapters that <emphasis>are</emphasis> present are
    up to date and will hopefully be a useful source of information for
    you.</para>

    <para>If you find any errors or inconsistencies, please report them to the
    maintainers. Email addresses are at the end of the book.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ufb-preface-origins">
    <title>Origins</title>

    <para><citetitle>Using Firebird</citetitle> is not a new book. The <ulink
    url="http://www.ibphoenix.com">IBPhoenix</ulink> editors wrote it years
    ago for distribution on their Developer's CD, when Firebird was still at
    version 1.0. Since then we have seen the arrival of Firebird 1.5 and 2.0,
    and most of the book is now in serious need of updating. In 2005 the
    IBPhoenix company decided to open-source the entire 26-chapter manual and
    hand it over to the Firebird Project for upgrading and maintenance.</para>

    <para>We would like to thank IBPhoenix here for making this work freely
    available.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ufb-preface-moredocs">
    <title>More documentation</title>

    <para>If you're new to Firebird or want to brush up on the basics, read
    the <citetitle>Firebird Quick Start Guide</citetitle> first. There's one
    available for every version of Firebird. Pick up yours from <ulink
    url="http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=doc">http://www.firebirdsql.org/index.php?op=doc</ulink>.
    This is also a good starting place to find links to more Firebird
    documentation.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>