<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../../../tools/docbook-dtd/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="fblangref25-intro">
  <title>About the Firebird SQL Language Reference</title>
  <subtitle>for Firebird 2.5</subtitle>
  <para><command>This Firebird SQL Language Reference is the first comprehensive manual to cover
  all aspects of the query language used by developers to communicate, through their applications,
  with the Firebird relational database management system.  It has a long history.</command></para>
  <section id="fblangref25-intro-subject">
    <title>Subject Matter</title>
      <para>The subject matter of this volume is wholly Firebird's implementation of the SQL
      relational database language.  Firebird conforms closely with international standards for SQL, from
       data type support, data storage structures, referential integrity mechanisms, to
       data manipulation capabilities and access privileges.  Firebird also implements a robust
       procedural language&mdash;procedural SQL (PSQL)&mdash; for stored procedures, triggers and
       dynamically-executable code blocks.  These are the areas addressed in this volume.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="fblangref25-intro-authors">
    <title>Authorship</title>
    <para>The material for assembling this Language Reference has been accumulating in the tribal lore
    of the open source community of Firebird core developers and user-developers for 15 years.
    The gift of the InterBase 6 open source codebase in July 2000 from the (then) Inprise/Borland conglomerate was
    warmly welcomed.  However, it came without rights to existing documentation. Once the code base
    had been forked by its owners for private, commercial development, it became clear that the 
    open source, non-commercial Firebird community would never be granted right of use.</para>
    <para>The two important books from the InterBase 6 published set were the <citetitle>Data Definition
    Guide</citetitle> and the <citetitle>Language Reference</citetitle>. The former covered the data
    definition language (DDL) subset of the SQL language, while the latter covered most of the rest.
    Fortunately for Firebird users over the years, both have been easy to find on-line as PDF books.</para>
    <section id="fblangref25-intro-authors-lru">
      <title>Language Reference Updates</title>
      <para> The <citetitle>Data Definition Guide</citetitle>, covering the creation and maintenance of
      metadata for databases, was <quote>good enough</quote> for several years: the data definition
      language (DDL) of a DBMS is stable and grows slowly in comparison to the data manipulation language (DML)
      employed for queries and the PSQL used for server-based programming.</para>
      <para>The leader of the Firebird Project's documentation team, Paul Vinkenoog, took up the cause for
      documenting the huge volume of improvements and additions to DML and PSQL as Firebird advanced through
      its releases.  Paul was personally responsible for collating, assembling and, to a great extent,
      authoring a cumulative series of <quote>Language Reference Updates</quote>&mdash;one for every major release
      from v.1.5 forward.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="fblangref25-intro-bigbook">
      <title>Gestation of the Big Book</title>
      <para>From around 2010, Paul, with Firebird Project lead Dmitry Yemanov and a documenter colleague Thomas Woinke,
      set about the task of designing and assembling a complete SQL language reference for Firebird.  They began with
      the material from the LangRef Updates, which is voluminous.  It was going to be a big job but, for all concerned,
      a spare-time one.</para>
      <para>Then, in 2013-4, two benefactor companies&mdash;MICEX amd IBSurgeon&mdash;funded three writers to take up
      this stalled book outline and publish a Firebird 2.5 Language Reference in Russian. They wrote the bulk of the 
      missing DDL section from scratch and wrote, translated or reused DML and PSQL material from the LangRef Updates,
      Russian language support forums, Firebird release notes, read-me files and other sources.  By the end of 2014,
      they had the task almost complete, in the form of a Microsoft Word document.</para>

      <section id="fblangref25-intro-funding">
        <title>Translation . . .</title>
        <para>The Russian sponsors, recognising that their efforts needed to be shared with the
        world-wide Firebird community, asked some Project members to initiate a crowd-funding campaign to have the
        Russian text professionally translated into English.  The translated text would be edited and converted to 
        the Project's standard DocBook format for addition to the open document library of the Firebird Project.  From
        there, the source text would be available for translation into other languages for addition to the 
        library.</para>
        <para>The fund-raising campaign happened at the end of 2014 and was successful.  In June, 2015, professional
        translator Dmitry Borodin began translating the Russian text.  From him, the raw English text went in stages 
        for editing and DocBook conversion by Helen Borrie&mdash;and here is <citetitle>The Firebird SQL Language Reference
        for V.2.5</citetitle>, by...everyone!</para>
      </section>

      <section id="fblangref25-intro-translation">
        <title>. . . and More Translation</title>
        <para>Once the DocBook source appears in CVS, we hope the trusty translators will start making versions in
        German, Japanese, Italian, French, Portuguese, Spanish, Czech.  Certainly, we never have enough translators 
        so please, you Firebirders who have English as a second language, do consider translating some sections 
        into your first language.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="fblangref25-intro-contributors">
      <title>Contributors</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Direct Content</emphasis></para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>Dmitry Filippov (writer)</listitem>
        <listitem>Alexander Karpeykin (writer)</listitem>
        <listitem>Alexey Kovyazin (writer, editor)</listitem>
        <listitem>Dmitry Kuzmenko (writer, editor)</listitem>
        <listitem>Denis Simonov (writer, editor, coordinator)</listitem>
        <listitem>Paul Vinkenoog (writer, designer)</listitem>
        <listitem>Dmitry Yemanov (writer)</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Resource Content</emphasis></para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>Adriano dos Santos Fernandes</listitem>
        <listitem>Alexander Peshkov</listitem>
        <listitem>Vladyslav Khorsun</listitem>
        <listitem>Claudio Valderrama</listitem>
        <listitem>Helen Borrie</listitem>
        <listitem>and others</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Translation</emphasis></para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Dmitry Borodin, megaTranslations.ru</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Editing and Conversion of English Text</emphasis></para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Helen Borrie</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ACKNOWLEDGMENTS -->
  <section id="fblangref25-acknowledgements">
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>
        <para>The first full language reference manual for Firebird would not have
        eventuated without the funding that finally brought it to fruition.  We acknowledge
        these contributions with gratitude and thank you all for stepping up.</para>
        <bridgehead id="sponsors_donors" renderas="sect3">Sponsors and Other Donors</bridgehead>
          <bridgehead id="sponsors01-native" renderas="sect4">Sponsors of the Russian Language 
          Reference Manual</bridgehead>
            <simplelist type="horiz" columns="1">
              <member><ulink url="http://www.moex.com">Moscow Exchange</ulink> (Russia) </member>
            </simplelist>
            <blockquote>
              <para><emphasis>Moscow Exchange is the largest exchange holding in Russia and Eastern Europe,
              founded on December 19, 2011, through the consolidation of the MICEX (founded in 1992) and RTS
              (founded in 1995) exchange groups. Moscow Exchange ranks among the world's top 20 exchanges
              by trading in bonds and by the total capitalization of shares traded, as well as among the
              10 largest exchange platforms for trading derivatives.</emphasis></para>
            </blockquote>
            <simplelist type="horiz" columns="1">
              <member><ulink url="http://www.ib-aid.com">IBSurgeon</ulink> (<ulink url="http://ibase.ru">ibase.ru</ulink>)
              (Russia)</member>
            </simplelist>
            <blockquote>
              <para><emphasis>Technical support and developer of administrator tools for the Firebird 
              DBMS.</emphasis></para>
            </blockquote>

          <!-- -->
          <bridgehead id="sponsors01-translate" renderas="sect4">Sponsors of the Translation Project</bridgehead>
            <simplelist type="horiz" columns="1">
              <member><ulink url="http://www.syntess.nl">Syntess Software BV</ulink> (Netherlands)</member>
              <member><ulink url="http://www.mitaro.li">Mitaro Business Solutions</ulink> (Liechtenstein)</member>
            </simplelist>
          <!-- -->
          <bridgehead id="donors" renderas="sect4">Other Donors</bridgehead>
            <para>Listed below are the names of companies and individuals whose cash contributions covered 
            the costs for translation into English, editing of the raw, translated text and conversion of
            the whole into the Firebird Project's standard DocBook 4 documentation source format.
              <simplelist type="horiz" columns="2">
                <member>Integrity Software Design, Inc. (U.S.A.)</member> <member>dimari GmbH (Germany)</member>
                <member>beta Eigenheim GmbH (Germany)</member> <member>KIMData GmbH (Germany)</member>
                <member>Jason Wharton (U.S.A)</member> <member>Trans-X (Sweden)</member>
                <member>Sanchez Balcewich (Uruguay)</member> <member>Cointec Ingenieros y Consultores, S.L. (Spain)</member>
                <member>Aage Johansen (Norway)</member> <member>Mattic Software (Netherlands)</member>
                <member>Andr&eacute; Knappstein (Germany)</member> <member>Paul F. McGuire (U.S.A.)</member>
                <member>Marcus Marques da Rocha (Brazil)</member> <member>Martin Kerkhoff</member>
                <member>Thomas Vedel (Denmark)</member> <member>Bulhan Bulhan (Australia)</member>
                <member>Alexandre Benson Smith (Brazil)</member> <member>Guillermo Nabrink (Brazil)</member>
                <member>Pierre Voirin (France)</member> <member>Heiko Tappe (Germany)</member>
                <member>Doug Chamberlain (U.S.A.)</member> <member>Craig Cox (U.S.A.)</member>
                <member>OMNet, Inc. (Switzerland)</member> <member>Alfred Steller (Germany)</member>
                <member>Konrad Butz (Germany)</member> <member>Thomas Smekal (Canada)</member>
                <member>Carlos H. Cantu (Brazil)</member> <member>XTRALOG SARL (France)</member>
                <member>Laszlo Urmenyi (Brazil)</member> <member>Fernando Pimenta (Brazil)</member>
                <member>Rudolf Grauberger (Germany)</member> <member>Thomas Steinmaurer (Austria)</member>
                <member>Rene Lobsiger (Switzerland)</member> <member>Hian Pin Tjioe</member>
                <member>Xavier Codina</member> <member>Mick Arundell (Australia)</member>
                <member>Russell Belding (New Zealand)</member> <member>Anticlei Scheid (Brazil)</member>
                <member>Luca Minuti (Italy)</member> <member>Mark Rotteveel (Netherlands)</member>
                <member>Chris Mathews (U.S.A.)</member> <member>Hannes Streicher (Germany)</member>
                <member>Wolfgang Lemmermeyer (Germany)</member> <member>Paolo Sciarrini (Italy)</member>
                <member>Acosta Belzusarri</member> <member>Daniel Motos Guerra</member>
                <member>Alberto Alfonso Luna</member> <member>Simeon Bodurov</member>
                <member>Cees Meijer</member> <member>Robert Nixon</member>
                <member>Olivier Dehorter (France)</member> <member>Andr&aacute;s Omacht (Hungary)</member>
                <member>Web Express</member> <member>Sergio Conzalez</member>
                <member>Marc Bleuwart</member> <member>Gabor Boros</member>
                <member>Shaymon Gracia Campos</member> <member>Cserna Zsombor (Hungary)</member>
                <member>David Keith</member> <member>Uwe Gerold</member>
                <member>Daniele Teti (Italy)</member> <member>Pedro Pablo Busto Criado</member>
                <member>Istvan Szabo</member> <member>Spiridon Pavlovic</member>
                <member>J. L. Garcia Naranjo</member> <member>A. Morales Morales</member>
                <member>Helen Cullen (New Zealand)</member> <member>Francisco Ibarra Ozuna</member>
              </simplelist>
            </para>
          <!-- -->
        <!-- -->
  </section>
  <!-- end ack -->

</chapter>
