<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="langref25-datatypes">
  <title>Data types</title>
  <section id="langref25-datatypes-numtypes">
    <title>Numeric types</title>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-smallint">
      <title><database>SMALLINT</database></title>
      <para><database>SMALLINT</database> is the 16-bit signed integer type.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>SMALLINT</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para><database>SMALLINT</database> numbers range from -2<superscript>15</superscript> to
      2<superscript>15</superscript>-1, or from -32768 to 32767.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-integer">
      <title><database>INTEGER</database></title>
      <para><database>INTEGER</database> is the 32-bit signed integer type.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>INTEGER</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>A shorthand form <database>INT</database> is also available.</para>
      <para>INTEGER numbers range from -2<superscript>31</superscript> to
      2<superscript>31</superscript>-1, or from -2147483648 to 2147483647.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-bigint">
      <title><database>BIGINT</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>BIGINT</database> is the 64-bit signed integer type.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>BIGINT</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para><database>BIGINT</database> numbers range from -2<superscript>63</superscript> to
      2<superscript>63</superscript>-1, or from -9223372036854775808 to
      9223372036854775807.</para>
      <note>
        <para>The BIGINT data type is available in Dialect 3 only.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-float">
      <title><database>FLOAT</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>FLOAT (precision)</database> is the approximate number with the binary
      precision equal to or greater than specified by the &lt;precision&gt;.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>FLOAT [(precision)]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>The precision must be positive, but there's no explicit upper limit (however, it's
      physically limited by 32767). If the precision declaration is omitted, then zero value is
      implied.</para>
      <para>If the precision is less than 8 then the FLOAT data type is internally implemented as
      a single precision floating-point value (commonly it is 32-bit). The FLOAT data type with a
      greater declared precision is implemented as a double precision floating-point value
      (commonly it is 64-bit). Both formats are covered by the IEEE 754 standard.</para>
      <para>The declared precision is not strictly enforced, it only dictates the choice between
      the two supported binary precisions.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-real">
      <title><database>REAL</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>REAL</database> is the approximate number with the binary precision less
      than 8.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>REAL</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>REAL is a predefined FLOAT data type implemented as a single precision floating-point
      value, so please refer to the appropriate section for the details.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-double">
      <title><database>DOUBLE PRECISION</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>DOUBLE PRECISION</database> is the approximate number with the binary
      precision equal to or greater than 8.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>DOUBLE PRECISION</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>DOUBLE PRECISION is a predefined FLOAT data type implemented as a double precision
      floating-point value, so please refer to the appropriate section for the details.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-longfloat">
      <title><database>LONG FLOAT</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>LONG FLOAT</database> is the approximate number with the binary precision
      equal to or greater than 8.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>LONG FLOAT [(precision)]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>LONG FLOAT is non-standard alternative to the DOUBLE PRECISION data type, so please
      refer to the appropriate section for the details. The optional precision declaration is
      ignored.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-numeric">
      <title><database>NUMERIC</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>NUMERIC (precision, scale)</database> is the exact number with the decimal
      precision and scale specified by the &lt;precision&gt; and &lt;scale&gt;.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>NUMERIC [precision [, scale]]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>The scale of NUMERIC is the count of decimal digits in the fractional part, to the
      right of the decimal point. The precision of NUMERIC is the total count of decimal digits in
      the number.</para>
      <para>The precision must be positive, the maximum supported value is 18. The scale must be
      zero or positive, up to the specified precision.</para>
      <para>If the scale is omitted, then zero value is implied, thus meaning an integer value of
      the specified precision, i.e. NUMERIC (P) is equivalent to NUMERIC (P, 0). If both the
      precision and the scale are omitted, then precision of 9 and zero scale are implied, i.e.
      NUMERIC is equivalent to NUMERIC (9, 0).</para>
      <para>The internal representation of the NUMERIC data type may vary. Numerics with the
      precision up to (and including) 4 are always stored as scaled short integers (SMALLINT).
      Numerics with the precision up to (and including) 9 are always stored as scaled regular
      integers (INTEGER). Storage of higher precision numerics depends on the SQL dialect. In
      Dialect 3, they are stored as scaled large integers (BIGINT). In Dialect 1, however, large
      integers are not available, therefore they are stored as double precision floating-point
      values (DOUBLE PRECISION).</para>
      <para>The effective precision limit for the given value depends on the corresponding
      storage. For example, NUMERIC (5) will be stored as INTEGER, thus allowing values in the
      precision range up to (and including) NUMERIC (9). So beware that the declared precision is
      not strictly enforced.</para>
      <para>Values outside the range limited by the effective precision are not allowed. Values
      with the scale larger than the declared one will be rounded to the declared scale while
      performing an assignment.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-decimal">
      <title><database>DECIMAL</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>DECIMAL (precision, scale)</database> is the exact number with the decimal
      scale specified by the &lt;scale&gt; and the decimal precision equal to or greater than the
      value of the specified &lt;precision&gt;.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>DECIMAL [precision [, scale]]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>A shorthand form <database>DEC</database> is also available.</para>
      <para>DECIMAL data type is almost identical to the NUMERIC data type, so please refer to the
      appropriate section for the details. The only difference is that DECIMAL is never internally
      stored as a small integer, so its minimal effective precision is equal to 9.</para>
      <note>
        <para>Accordingly to the SQL standard, NUMERIC is declared to be a strict data type which
        enforces the declared precision, while DECIMAL can accept more decimal digits than
        declared. In Firebird, however, both enforce the effective precision rather than the
        declared one, with NUMERIC being just a bit stricter in the lower precision range.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="langref25-datatypes-chartypes">
    <title>Character types</title>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-char">
      <title><database>CHARACTER</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>CHARACTER (length)</database> is the fixed-length string with the character
      length equal to the specified &lt;length&gt;.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>CHARACTER [(length)] [CHARACTER SET charset]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>A shorthand form <database>CHAR</database> is also available.</para>
      <para>The declared length must be positive. If the length specification is omitted, length
      of 1 (one character) is implied. The maximum supported byte length is 32767, thus the
      maximum supported character length depends on the declared character set.</para>
      <para>The CHARACTER data type definition may include the character set name, so that all the
      characters of the string value belong to the declared character set. If the character set
      name is omitted, the database-wise default character set is implied. See the complete list
      of supported character sets in Appendix B.</para>
      <para>Values of the CHARACTER data type are right padded with the appropriate padding
      character up to the declared length, and are physically stored this way. However, the
      trailing padding characters are semantically insignificant and ignored when comparing
      CHARACTER values. Strings longer than the declared length are not accepted, unless the
      excess characters are all equal to the appropriate padding character, in this case the
      string is truncated to the declared length.</para>
      <note>
        <para>The default padding character is the space character (ASCII code 0x20) and it
        applies to the every character set except OCTETS which represents binary strings and thus
        has binary zero (ASCII code 0x00) as the padding character.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-nchar">
      <title><database>NATIONAL CHARACTER</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>NATIONAL CHARACTER (length)</database> is the fixed-length string with the
      character length equal to the specified &lt;length&gt; and having the predefined character
      set of ISO8859_1.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>NATIONAL CHARACTER [(length)]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>Shorthand forms <database>NATIONAL CHAR</database> and <database>NCHAR</database> are
      also available.</para>
      <para>Besides having the character set hardcoded, NATIONAL CHARACTER data type is absolutely
      equal to the CHARACTER data type, so please refer to the appropriate section for the
      details.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-varchar">
      <title><database>CHARACTER VARYING</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>CHARACTER VARYING (length)</database> is the varying-length string with the
      character length limited by the specified &lt;length&gt;.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>CHARACTER VARYING (length) [CHARACTER SET charset]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>Shorthand forms <database>CHAR VARYING</database> and <database>VARCHAR</database> are
      also available.</para>
      <para>The declared length is mandatory and it must be positive. The maximum supported byte
      length is 32765, thus the maximum supported character length depends on the declared
      character set.</para>
      <para>The CHARACTER data type definition may include the character set name, so that all the
      characters of the string value belong to the declared character set. If the character set
      name is omitted, the database-wise default character set is implied. See the complete list
      of supported character sets in Appendix B.</para>
      <para>Values of the CHARACTER VARYING data type are never padded. Internally, the CHARACTER
      VARYING values are prefixed with the 16-bit length counter, so they are stored using the
      actual string length. Strings longer than the declared length are not accepted.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-nvarchar">
      <title><database>NATIONAL CHARACTER VARYING</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>NATIONAL CHARACTER VARYING (length)</database> is the varying-length string
      with the character length limited by the specified &lt;length&gt; and having the predefined
      character set of ISO8859_1.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>NATIONAL CHARACTER VARYING [(length)]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>A shorthand form <database>NATIONAL CHAR VARYING</database> is also available.</para>
      <para>Besides having the character set hardcoded, NATIONAL CHARACTER VARYING data type is
      absolutely equal to the CHARACTER VARYING data type, so please refer to the appropriate
      section for the details.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="langref25-datatypes-datetimetypes">
    <title>Date/time types</title>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-date">
      <title><database>DATE</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>DATE</database> represents the temporal value containing the year-month-day
      part.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>DATE</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>DATE values range from 01-Jan-0001 to 31-Dec-9999.</para>
      <para>Internally, DATE values are stored as 32-bit signed integers, representing the offset
      (in days) from the baseline date (17-Nov-1858).</para>
      <note>
        <para>This definition applies to Dialect 3 only. In Dialect 1, the DATE data type is a
        replacement for the TIMESTAMP data type, thus containing both date and time parts. See the
        appropriate section for the details.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-time">
      <title><database>TIME</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>TIME</database> represents the temporal value containing the
      hour-minute-second part, including second fractions.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>TIME</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>TIME values range from 00:00:00.0000 AM to 23:59:59.9999 PM.</para>
      <para>Internally, TIME values are stored as 32-bit scaled unsigned integers, representing
      both the number of seconds passed since the day start (which is a baseline, so that zero
      time value means a midnight) and the number of second fractions passed since the start of
      the current second. The scale value is 10000, so the supported precision is 1/10000 second
      (100 microseconds).</para>
      <note>
        <para>The TIME data type is available in Dialect 3 only.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-timestamp">
      <title><database>TIMESTAMP</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>TIMESTAMP</database> represents the temporal value containing both
      year-month-day and hour-minute-second parts, including second fractions.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>TIMESTAMP</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>TIMESTAMP values range from 01-Jan-0001 00:00:00.0000 AM to 31-Dec-9999 23:59:59.9999
      PM.</para>
      <para>Internally, TIMESTAMP values are stored as a combination of two 32-bit integers, each
      representing its own part (date or time), so its total size is 64 bits. See prior sections
      for the storage details.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="langref25-datatypes-bintypes">
    <title>Binary types</title>
    <section id="langref25-datatypes-blob">
      <title><database>BLOB</database> data type</title>
      <para><database>BLOB</database> is the data type representing text or binary data of
      arbitrary length.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Syntax:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>BLOB [SUB_TYPE subtype]
   [SEGMENT SIZE segsize]
   [CHARACTER SET charset]</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Shortcuts:</title>
        <para><blockquote>
            <programlisting>BLOB (segsize)
BLOB (segsize, subtype)
BLOB (, subtype)</programlisting>
          </blockquote></para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>By default, every blob internally consists of a chained list of segments, each up to
      64KB in size. Small segments are combined together so that they could share the same disk
      page. There are three storage levels of blobs. Blobs of level 0 fit on a single disk page
      and may even reside at the same data page where the rest of the fields are stored. Blobs of
      level 1 are always stored on dedicated disk pages and consist of the root page (which itself
      does not store any blob data but contains an inventory of other data pages) and a number of
      data pages the blob content is splitted among. Blobs of level 2 extend the aforementioned
      scheme by having a root inventory page which enumerates other inventory pages that in turn
      point to the data pages containing the blob contents. This three-level storage layout along
      with the database page size establish the practical size limit for blobs, which is equal to
      2GB for the maximum supported page size of 16KB.</para>
      <para>So it can be said that BLOB segments represent the logical blob structure rather than
      the physical one. They do not directly affect the blob storage on disk and the appropriate
      low-level I/O operations performed by Firebird internally, but they define the granulation
      of the blob contents and the way how the blob is accessed at the interface layer. If you
      need to read the whole blob, you should iterate through all the segments. If you need to
      read just a few bytes in the middle of the blob, you should read all the segments preceding
      these bytes.</para>
      <note>
        <para>There is also a concept of so called streamed blobs. They are not splitted into
        separate segments and are directly accessible for reading and writing from any specified
        position. The choice between segmented and streamed blobs is done by the application
        developer when creating the blob contents, it's not covered by the BLOB declaration in
        SQL.</para>
      </note>
      <para>The BLOB sub-type describes the blob contents. While Firebird usually does not guess
      about the internal structure of the BLOB data, there are some predefined sub-types that may
      affect the BLOB handling. The BLOB sub-type can be declared via either the corresponding
      numeric value, or by using a mnemonic name for the predefined sub-types, e.g.:</para>
      <para><blockquote>
          <programlisting>BLOB SUB_TYPE 0
BLOB SUB_TEXT BINARY</programlisting>
        </blockquote></para>
      <para>If the BLOB sub-type is omitted, sub-type of 0 (BINARY) is implied. However, if the
      BLOB declararion includes the character set (ses below), then sub-type of 1 (TEXT) is
      implied.</para>
      <para>BLOB sub-types can be negative, zero or positive values in the range from -32768 to
      32767. Negative BLOB sub-types are user-defined ones and can be used by application
      developers to distinguish between different formats of binary contents. Zero BLOB sub-type
      is predefined for binary blobs that are processed transparently without any assumptions
      about their contents. BLOB sub-type of 1 is predefined for text blobs that are processed
      similarly to the character data types. They may be treated like very long character strings,
      including conversions from and to character data types, usage in the various string-wise
      operators and built-in functions, and so on. Binary and text blobs can be used by
      application developers as well. Positive BLOB sub-types greater than 1 are reserved for
      internal use, they are not allowed for user blobs.</para>
      <!-- Should the table {mnemonic-value} of the predefined sub-types be published? -->
      <para>The BLOB segment size defines the number of bytes to be processed (read or written) by
      a single interface operation with that blob. It must be a positive value limited by 65535
      bytes. If the BLOB segment size is omitted, then the value of 80 bytes is implied. The BLOB
      segment size also</para>
      <para>The BLOB declaration may include the character set name, so that all the characters
      the blob contents consists of belong to the specified character set. The character set can
      be specified for text and binary blobs only. If this happens for a binary blob, then the
      sub-type gets implicitly changed to TEXT. If the character set name is omitted, the
      database-wise default character set is implied. See the complete list of supported character
      sets in Appendix B.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="langref25-datatypes-arrays">
    <title>Arrays</title>
    <para>To be written.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="langref25-datatypes-comparison">
    <title>Comparison rules</title>
    <para>Values of the same data type are compared accordingly to the natural rules of the
    corresponding data type. Blobs are compared either byte-wise or character-wise for binary and
    text blobs respectively, using their entire contents.</para>
    <para>Mixed-type comparisons, however, are processed using the special priority rules. The
    value with the data type of the less priority is implicitly converted to the data type of the
    value with greater priority and then both values are compared naturally. The priority list is
    the following (starting with the least priority):</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>CHARACTER, CHARACTER VARYING</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>SMALLINT</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>INTEGER</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>BIGINT</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>REAL</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>DOUBLE PRECISION</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>DATE, TIME</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>TIMESTAMP</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The derived data types (NUMERIC, DECIMAL, FLOAT, LONG FLOAT) are compared accordingly to
    the priorities of their underlying data types. Scaled numeric values are adjusted to their
    maximal scale before comparing.</para>
    <para>Character strings are compared without regard to their trailing padding characters, if
    any. International character strings (any character set except NONE, OCTETS and ASCII) are
    compared accordingly to their collation rules, explicit or implicit.</para>
    <para>When DATE or TIME value is converted to TIMESTAMP, it gets its missing part completed.
    DATE values get zero time part (midnight), TIME values get the today's date as their date
    part.</para>
    <para>If one of the comparison arguments is a blob, then custom rules are used. In this case,
    the second argument gets converted to a string value (binary or character) and then the string
    comparison rules apply.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="langref25-datatypes-coercion">
    <title>Coercion rules</title>
    <para>There are situations where a few values of different data types must provide the unified
    result. In this case, those values should be converted to their common (less restrictive) data
    type. Below are the rules applied (in the specified order) for those implicit
    conversions:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If any data type is BLOB, the result is also BLOB</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If any data type is CHARACTER VARYING, or if one data type is CHARACTER and another
        one is numeric or date/time, the result is CHARACTER VARYING</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If any data type is CHARACTER, the result is also CHARACTER</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If any datatype is an approximate numeric, then each data type must be numeric and
        the result is an approximate numeric</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If all data types are exact numerics, the result is an exact numeric with the
        maximal precision and maximal scale</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If any data type is DATE, TIME or TIMESTAMP, then each data type must be the same
        DATE, TIME or TIMESTAMP and the result is also the same DATE, TIME or TIMESTAMP</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>If the coercion result is BLOB and there is any binary blob in the list, the resulting
    blob is also binary.</para>
    <para>If the coercion results in a text blob, the resulting charset is derived using the
    following rules:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If any input character set is OCTETS, the resulting character set is also
        OCTETS</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If any input character set is neither NONE nor ASCII, it is chosen as the resulting
        character set</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If any input character set is ASCII, or if any input part is numeric or date/time,
        result is ASCII</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Otherwise, result is NONE</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="langref25-datatypes-collation">
    <title>Collation rules</title>
    <para>To be written.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
